Welcome to Marshall LMS, a complete
featurerich learning management system
built entirely from the ground up. This
isn't just some basic platform. No, this
is a full-blown system where you can
create, manage, and sell your own online
courses with a seamless experience for
both you and your students. Sounds
ambitious? Well, we are making it happen
from scratch. Let's start with the
basics. a beautiful public-f facing
landing page and a course catalog
designed to engage students right away.
They can browse individual courses,
explore detailed overviews, see the full
curriculum, and thanks to a seamless
Stripe integration, purchase access
instantly. But before anything can be
bought, users need to authenticate.
Whether you are a creator or a customer,
logging in is simple. Choose GitHub O
off or go with your email. If you log in
with your email, we will send a one-time
passcode OTP to verify your identity
fast and secure. Just copy paste it and
you are authenticated.
And that's just the beginning. As a
creator, you get access to a powerful
admin dashboard with beautiful analytics
to help you track your success. You will
have a fully custom course creation and
editing suite complete with a slick
modern rich text editor built from
complete scratch. Uploading files, well,
we've built a custom drag and drop zone
to make it effortless. Behind the
scenes, uploads are handled securely
using pre-signed URLs and stored in a S3
bucket. Production grade, scalable, and
fast. And when it's time to edit a
course, you have two powerful tabs. One
to update your basic course info and
another one to manage the course
structure. The course structure page
unlocks a whole new level of control.
Using an intuitive drag and drop
interface, you can reorder chapters and
lessons with ease. Just drag and drop
them into place. It's seamless. Oh, and
of course, we take security seriously
with Arkhat. Our platform is protected
against bots, XSS, SQL injection, and
other common attacks. We also
implemented weight limits and bot
detection so that our app stays fast and
secure. Now, let's flip to the student
experience. Once enrolled, students get
a personalized dashboard showing the
enrolled courses and the individual
progress on each course. But the real
magic happens in the course player page.
A clean two panel layout with a sidebar
for navigating chapters and lessons, a
main area with a beautiful video player,
and all lesson content, and of course, a
completion button that lets users track
their journey through your course.
Progress tracking is critical and we've
made it a breeze. And if you are
wondering how we will make all of this
possible, then let me break it down real
quick. We are using NexJS15
for smooth server rendered magic paired
with taven CSS for a clean responsive UI
and fully customized with shad and UI
components. Authentication is powered by
better off with both email OTP and
GitHub ooth off support. Thanks to
Arkjet, we are protected from the ground
up. Payments are handled via Stripe with
full checkout integration. And on the
back end, we are using Prisma with a
neon hosted Postgress database, modern,
fast, and scalable. By the end of this
tutorial, you won't just understand how
to build an LMS. No, you will have built
your own one ready for real users, real
payments, and real impact. So, what do
you think? Did you enjoy it? Are you
excited to get started? I hope so. This
is literally the biggest and most
comprehensive video I have ever made. I
rewrote the code seven times. Yes, seven
times
just to make sure that everything is
clean, scalable, and secure. Throughout
the video, I put a big focus on best
practices and solid security measures so
that you can build something rock solid
which can make you millions of dollars
per month without falling apart in the
process. And here's the best thing.
Everything that we will use in this
video is 100% free and does not require
any credit card. Now that you know what
we are going to build and how we are
going to build it, there are only three
more things that you have to do before
we can dive in. First of all, grab some
water. Hydration is important. You want
to drink a lot of water. Secondly, grab
a keyboard and a mouse. You will write a
lot of code. And lastly, please don't
forget to like and subscribe. It takes
only 1 second, but it would mean so much
to me and my heart. So, please do it.
Oh, and also, maybe you should consider
becoming a channel member to get access
to videos before they are released and
to get access to more special videos.
And finally, huge shout out to Ark Chat
for making this huge video possible.
Without them, none of this would have
ever happened. So, thank you. And now
it's time to get started. So let's roll
the video which I recorded for you guys.
Let's go. All right, friends. So let's
get started. I'm already on the NexJS
website. So let's head over to the
documentation to installation. And right
here they already provide us with an
installation command to create a brand
new Nex.js project. The only problem is
it uses npm as a package manager and I
don't want to use npm. The reason is
quite simple. Later on, we will install
dependencies and npm will throw version
errors. It will say, "Hey, this
dependency version is not compatible
with React 19." Therefore, in this
video, we will use PNPM. PNPM is a
better alternative to npm, which is also
faster and more efficient. And more
importantly, once we install
dependencies, it won't throw any version
errors. You can still use npm. you will
just have to force all of the
installations. So, installing PNPM is
quite simple. Just head over to the
documentation to installation and here
you will find all of the I guess ways on
how to install PNPM. Either use npm or
use homebrew. So, I think you have now
installed PNPM. This means let's create
a brand new project. So, in my terminal,
I will cd into my YouTube directory. And
then inside of here, let's run PNPM
create next- app at latest. This will
create a new Nex.js project. And using
this at latest, we will also install the
latest version of Next.js. This CLI will
now ask us a few questions. So I want to
name my project Marshall-Y
or Marshall LMS-YouTube.
Then I want to use TypeScript. I want to
use ESLint. I want to use tent. I don't
want to use the source directory. I will
use the app router. I will use turbo
pack. And I won't customize the default
import alias. Now, here's one thing
which I want to quickly mention and
that's that you can still continue
watching this tutorial. If you use
JavaScript, it's fine. Nevertheless, my
recommendation to you is to actually use
TypeScript. It's a massive gamecher and
it will help you a lot in your deaf
workflow. So, it's great for developer
experience. If you have zero experience
with Typescript, then I will link a
video on the top right or top left
corner. Uh, I created a little primer
and this will help you a lot to
understand the basics of TypeScript. And
also in this video, we will only use the
basics. And as you see the CLI now
created a brand new project. It
installed a few dependencies which means
we can open our project in our preferred
editor. So as you see I already opened
the project. If you want to do the same
just go to the top click on file and
then on open folder. And now on the
right side you already see the project
structure which was created when we
created the project. Let's quickly
analyze it. So we first of all have a TS
config file. This is the configuration
file for TypeScript. Then we have a
readme file. If you want to, you can
update it. We also have a post CSS file.
This is for tin CSS. Then we have a
package.json file. Inside of here, we
list all of our dependencies. So as an
example, we have React 19 installed and
X.js 15.3 installed. It could be that
once you watch this video that there's
already a newer version of NexJS
released. Let's say 15.5 or 15.6. It
does not matter. This video is
compatible with all of the NexJS
versions. It does not matter what
version of Nex.js you have installed.
And then we also have a few dev
dependencies. These are dependencies
which only show up in your development
environment. And once you publish your
application or once you go production,
these won't show up in your production
bundle size. Then what else do we have
right here? We have the next doconfig
file inside of here. We will configure
next.js. So as an example, we will use
the image component later on which means
we will also have to whitelist a few
domains and we will do it right here.
Then what else do we have? We have the
eslint.config file. Later on we will
update it a bit. Then we have our git
ignore file. Please make sure that yourv
file is added right here because you
don't want to commit your secrets to
your public GitHub repo. Even if it's
private, please don't commit them. Then
we also have a public folder and inside
of here we will store all of our public
assets. This means for example images,
videos, fonts, stuff like that. Then we
also have our app folder and this is
literally the most important folder in
this whole project directory because
inside of here we will create our routes
but also all of our logic and let's
start from the top. We first of all have
a faf icon. You can update it later on.
We also have a globalscs file and inside
of here we already configured t1 css.
Then we have a layout file and a
page.tsx.
I expect you to know the absolute basics
of Nex.js for this video. This means I
think you should all know what a
page.tsx is and what a layout.tsx is. In
short, a page.tsx defines a route. A
layout.tsx wraps your pages. This for
example is the root layout which means
all of our pages are rendered right here
as children. Later on we will for
example create a dashboard route. this
dashboard route will be rendered as a
child. This means if we render for
example above our children a hello world
then this hello world will be persisted
on all routes which also means it won't
be rerendered. And if we open our
page.tsx you will also find a bit of
demo code. So let's I guess see how it
looks like. Let's start our dev server.
So let's open our terminal. You can do
that either with commandj. This is a
shortcut or you can go to the top click
on terminal and then new terminal and
then in my terminal I will run pnpm
rundef. This will start our def server
on localhost 3000. Let's copy the URL
and let's open it in a new tab in
chrome. And voila, this is our index
page. This is our I guess demo route
which NexJS created. Yeah, it looks
quite nice. But this is of course not
what we want to render. So let's again
go back and let's update our page.tsx.
Let's go to the return statement and
let's delete everything in the return
statement. Let's create a diff an h1 and
inside of here let's say hello world. If
I again go back you will see on the top
left corner hello world. And then let's
also test out our layout. So if I go to
my layout and if I render for example,
hey this is the nav bar above our
children, then you will also see it on
the top. This means our layout works.
Our H1 works. Let's also see if t1 CSS
works. So let's style our H1. Let's say
text to XL font bold text red 500. Let's
save it. Let's go back. And yes, as you
see, tin CSS works exactly as expected.
And I guess we can get started with our
application. So what's the first thing
that I want to start with? Well, I want
to start with our login page, with our
authentication page. So let's again go
back to our codebase. Let's first of all
delete this H1 from our layout. We don't
need it anymore. And let's create our
authentication page. So let's go into
our app folder. Let's create a new
folder. And inside of here, I want to
create a route group. Therefore, let's
use parentheses and then in the
parentheses, let's say off. And now we
have a route group. But what even is a
route group? Good question. Let's head
over to the documentation. So, if you
search for route groups, then you'll see
that route groups are a folder
convention that let you organize routes
by category or team. This means these
folders won't be mapped to the URL. So
this convention indicates the folder is
for organizational purposes and should
not be included in the routes URL path.
So we will only use it to organize our
project directory but it won't be linked
to our URL. So let's again go back and
then in our off route group we want to
create our lockin route the actual
route. So let's create another child
folder. This will be our login folder or
our lockin route. And then in the lockin
folder, we want to create a page.tsx to
actually create our route. Because
again, how do you create a route in
nextJS? Well, you create a folder with a
name and then you create a page.tsx. In
this folder, this defines a route in
next.js. And then in the page.tsx, we
want to create an export default
function. Let's call it lock in page.
Let's invoke it. And then we can open
it. Inside of here, I will create an
return statement. And then I want to
return a div h1. And I will say hello
from the login page.
If I save this and again go back, then
you'll see that I don't see the login
page right here. That's because we have
to navigate to this new page. So let's
go to the URL and let's navigate to
/lockin. If I click on enter, you will
see right here, hello from the login
page. Nice. But now let's also style it.
And inside of here, I want to render a
card. Now, here's the thing. In this
video, we will reuse a lot of
components. We will use buttons, inputs,
labels, uh, for example, cards, and
stuff like that. These components should
all be styled pretty much the same way.
They should be accessible. They should
look nice and stuff like that. You could
create components yourself. Create them
from the base. I guess create all of the
HTML, style them with tin CSS and stuff
like that. But this would be quite hard
because you want to also make them
accessible. It would take a lot of time
and it's also something which I wouldn't
recommend. Therefore, in this video, we
will use shad and UI. Shatn UI is a
component library which is styled and
accessible. And the nice thing is it's
also very very easy to customize. Also,
they are not really a component library.
rather they just provide the building
blocks to create your own component
library. So if you didn't know, Shatzi
and UI is built on top of radics UI.
Radics UI is also a component library
with the only difference that it's not
styled. It provides the base layer
primitives which are accessible. Shhat
CN UI takes these primitives, styles
them, and pretty much gives them to you
for free. And therefore we will use shad
C and UI. So let's head over to the
documentation. You can also right here
check out all of the components. The
accordion component, the badge
component, the card component. The card
component is for example what we will
use in a second to create our login
form. But let's first of all install SH
CN UI. So let's click on installation.
We want to pick our framework. In this
case, this is Nex.js. And then the first
step is to run the innit command. So,
let me copy this installation command.
Let's go back. Let's open the terminal.
And then inside of here, I will just
paste it. And also, it's important that
you copy the PNPM command. If you use
npm, then please copy the npm command.
And also, I forgot to mention it at the
start, but bun is also a good
alternative to npm. It's also faster,
it's more efficient, and it also does
not have these installation problems
with React 19. And let's again go back.
As you see the CLI will ask us a few
questions. So what base color would we
like to use or which base color? I would
like to use the neutral color. It will
now check our registry. It will then
update the CSS variables. It will
install all of the necessary
dependencies. And then our project was
successfully initialized. So let's see
what chat CNN UI created. So we first of
all have a components file or
components.json file. This is pretty
much the configuration file for chats
and ui. So as you see we use react
server components typescript. Then we
have the path to our CSS file and stuff
like that. If you want to you can also
update the configuration right in this
file. Then we also installed a few
dependencies. So for example, class
variance authority clsx lucid react and
lucid react for example is an icon
library. So let's copy the URL. Let's
open it in a new tab. This is the icon
library. So as you see these are all of
the icons. They look nice. They are
consistent and that's probably also the
reason why CN chose this icon library as
a default. I for example also use this
icon library on my website and it looks
nice. So let's again go back then. What
else has been added? Well, we also have
a new lip folder with an utils file. And
this is just our CN helper which we can
then later on use to create dynamic
styles. Let's also already install a few
components. So let's again go back to
shad CN UI and let's install the button
component. So let's again use pnpm.
Let's copy the um installation command
and then let's paste it in our terminal.
As you see, it created the component.
And if we open our explorer, then you
will find a new components folder. In
the components folder, we now store all
of the shad C and UI components which we
install. So this is a huge difference to
standard component libraries. For
example, if you use MUI, all of the code
will be abstracted in the note modules
folder, but chat and UI literally gives
you the code for you to use and update.
So this is our button component. As you
see, we use this uh radics UI primitive
to make everything accessible and then
chart C and UI styles everything using
tin CSS. And I want to install a few
components. So I want to use the card. I
want to use the input component, the
label component, and to not do
everything manually. Please head over to
my YouTube description and there you
will find an installation command to
literally install all of the components
which we will need in this video. So I
will just copy it from my notion file.
Let's again go back. I will open my
terminal and then I will paste it inside
of here. So as you see these are all of
our components like for example the
alert dialogue component, the form
component, the dialogue component, sona
which is our toast library, the text
area component. You can go through all
of these components individually. Just
copy the name, go to shhats and UI and
for example type in sona. Again sona is
for example our toast library. So if we
click on show toast, this will be the
library or this will be the toast which
will be created. So let's click on
enter. This will install all of these
components as you see right here. And
this means if I again open my components
folder, you will find all of the
components right here. So let's again
close this. Let's close this. And then
in our page.tsx, we can start by styling
or by creating our UI for the login
page. So let's delete everything in the
return statement. And let's start with
the cart component. The cart component
is imported from the components folder.
Then in the cart, I want to render my
cart header component. In the cart
header, I want to render the card title
component. And then for the car title,
let's just say welcome back exclamation
mark. Let's also give the car title a
class name and this will be text XL.
Underneath the car title, I will render
the car description. And inside of here,
I will say log in with your GitHub or
email account.
If I again go back and do a hard
refresh, I will see my card right here.
Okay. Yeah, it's too big. And I guess it
does not look very nice right now. So,
we want to make the width a bit smaller.
It should also be centered and stuff
like that. Therefore, let's again go
back and instead of applying the styles
right here to our cart, we will instead
create a layout file which will wrap all
of the children in our off uh right here
in our off route group. So in the off
folder, let's create a layout.tsx file.
And please make sure that you create a
file in the off route group and not in
the lockin folder because later on we
will also create a verify request route
in the off uh route group. And I want to
also share the layout with this route.
In the layout file, let's create an
export default function. Let's call it
off layout. Let's invoke it. And then
let's open it. Inside of here, I will
create a return statement. I will return
a div. And then in the div I want to
return my children. As you see right
here, I get an error and it says cannot
find name children. So we will get our
children through the params. So let's
destructure the params. Let's get our
children. As you see, I get an error and
it says binding element children
implicitly has an any type and I already
know what the type of children is and
the type is react node. So let's give
our children the type of React note
which is imported from React. As you see
the error is now gone which means if I
again go back and do a hard refresh
everything still works as expected. If I
for example render an H1 above our
children and say hey this is the nav or
the off layout nav and again go back
then you will see it above our cart. So
this is how our layout works. And then I
want to give my div a class name. Let's
say this will be flex width of full,
maximum width of SM, flex of call, and
then gap of six. If I save this and
again go back, you will see that the our
cut now takes a smaller width. And this
already looks way better. Nevertheless,
it's not centered. And that's not quite
what I want. So to fix it, let's wrap
this div in another div. So let's create
a div. Let's wrap this div in this div
which we just created. And let's also
give it a class name. This will be a
position of relative. Let's say flex
minimum height of svh. svh is pretty
similar to viewport height. Then let's
say flex of column and then items center
and just the five center. This means we
pretty much take the whole width and the
whole height and then we center
everything in the middle. Which means
our card should now also be in the
center. And that's exactly what
happened. So let's again go back to our
page.tsx and let's continue styling our
lockin form. So underneath our cart
header, we can render our cart content
which is imported from the components.
And then in the cart content, I want to
render a button component. This is
imported from the components. And inside
of here, I will for now say signin with
GitHub. If I save this and again go back
then you will find the button right
here. But let's be honest, it does not
look very nice. Therefore, let's again
go back and let's update the button a
bit. So I want to also render the GitHub
icon. So in the button, but I guess
before the text, let's get our GitHub
icon from Lucid React. This is
self-closing. And let's also give it a
class name which will be size four. This
means width four and height four. This
is pretty much just the short form. You
could also say width four, height four.
You just have to write more code. So
let's again say size four. And then
let's save it. And let's go back. And as
you see, yes, this looks quite nice.
Let's also give it the full width. So
let's give our button a class name. And
this will be width full. Let's give our
button also a variant. This will be
outline. And I think this should already
look way better. And yes, it now takes
the whole width. And we also have a
different variant. One thing which
currently annoys me quite a bit is white
mode which means I want to implement
dark mode. So let's head over back to
shhatsy and UI let's go to the
documentation and then in the navbar or
I'm sorry in the sidebar on the left
side you will find the dark mode
section. So right here we can add dark
mode as a framework we use next.js. So
let's select this and then we want to
first of all install next- themes. So
let's copy the installation command and
then I will paste it in my terminal. So
next- themes will allow us to store the
theme I guess preference in local
storage. This means once the user does a
hard refresh, we will keep the
preference I guess saved. So if the user
for example selected dark mode and if
the user then does a hard refresh, dark
mode will stay persisted. You can also
see it in the charts and UI website. If
I select light mode and do a hard
refresh, the theme is kept persisted. So
the next step is to create a theme
provider. So let's copy the name theme
provider.tsx. This will be the name of
the component itself. Let's again go
back. Let's open the explorer. Then I
want to go to my components to the UI
folder and let's create the theme
provider.tsx file. Then I want to copy
the code and then I will paste it into
the theme provider file. And as you see
this component is also marked as use
client which means this component is a
client component. What does this mean?
Well, this means that this component
will get a JavaScript bundle shipped to
it because this component needs the
client site to work as expected. So
let's again close the theme provider and
we want to wrap our children with this
theme provider. So let's copy the theme
provider. Let's go back and then I will
wrap the children in this theme
provider. Please make sure that you
import the theme provider from your
components not from next- themes. If you
import it from next- themes, you will
get errors because it will say hey this
component does not work or I guess this
package does not work in a server
component and that's also the reason why
we created this separate component.
Next- themes needs a JavaScript bundle
and therefore you have to mark the
component as use client. Let's also mark
or give this HTML tag a property which
will be suppress hydration warning. And
I guess this should already be it. So
let's again go back. What's the next
step? Well, the next step is to create a
theme toggle or in other words a mode
toggle. So let's click or let's test it
out. So this is what we will create. If
the user clicks on this theme toggle, he
will get three options. Light theme,
dark theme or system theme. And if the
user does a selection, the theme will
automatically update. So let's go to the
code. Let's copy the code example. Let's
open our explorer. And then in the
components folder in the UI folder, I
will create a new theme toggle.tsx
file. Let's again paste the code inside
of here. And as you see, it looks nice.
Let's also update the function name. So
instead of mode toggle, I will call it
theme toggle. So let's open our index
page. And then underneath the H1 I will
render my theme toggle component which I
will import from my components folder.
This is self-closing. Let's again go
back and if I go to the index page we
will get an error. So let's again
restart our dev server and then I will
again do a hard refresh. And as you see
right here on the left side I get my
theme toggle. If I select light theme I
get light theme. If I select dark theme
I get my dark theme. And then let's
continue with our lockin route or in
other words with our lockin form. So
underneath my button I want to render
like a little separator line. It will be
a separator line and then over the
separator line we will say or continue
with and then underneath the separator
line we will render our email input. So
the user can either log in using GitHub
this means of off or using email. So
underneath the button let's render a div
element. Then I want to create a span
element. And inside of here I will say
or continue with. If I save this and
again go back you will find this text
right here. This does not look very nice
right now. So let's style our div. Let's
give it a class name. This will be
relative text center text smol
after colon insert zero after colon top
1/2. Let's for now write the styles. I
will explain them later on. Then let's
also say after Z0 so the Z index. Then I
want to also say after which will be
flex. Then also after which will be
items of center. Then also after which
will be border top. And then also after
which will be border border. This means
the color of our border. If I save this
and again go back you will find this
separator line. And you know what it
looks quite nice to be honest with you.
So these after classes are there to
create this line. That's also why we
created so many. This is just I guess a
little trick to create this line. And
then to render the text over the line.
Then let's again go back and let's also
uh update our span. So let's give it a
class name which will be relative Z 10.
Let's also give it a bg color and this
will be BG card. So background. And
let's also say padding X of two. If I
save this and again go back then you
will see that this looks absolutely
beautiful. So if I zoom in a bit you
will see we have this separator line. So
on the left side and then on the right
side. And then we render the text pretty
much over this separator line. It looks
so nice to be honest with you. And let's
maybe also darken the text a bit because
it's currently too light. So let's again
go back and let's give the text a color
of muted foreground. If I save this and
again go back you'll see yeah this looks
beautiful and also as you see I use
these classes muted foreground bgard
border border these are not your
standard tin CSS classes. So what is
this? Well these are CSS labels. So if
you open your globals CSS file you will
see that shiy and UI configured this
file. It created its own CSS labels and
then it also added all of the colors for
these CSS variables. So let me show you
an example. So right here we have our
popover foreground. This defines the CSS
label but it does not define any color.
The color itself is actually defined in
the root object I guess. So if you
search for our pop over foreground then
you will see that we define the color
using okch.
So, OKLCH is the successor of HSL. It's
a better alternative to HSL. It's better
for colors and stuff like that. I also
already made a video on OKLCH. So, if
you go to YouTube and open my channel,
then you will find this video right here
which is called how to use Shhatzy and
UI the right way. Inside of there I talk
about oklcch how shad cy and UI works
and how to customize your components the
right way. And then in our lockin form I
want to render my input or I want to
render my email input. So underneath
this div which we just created for our
separator we can create another div. And
let's give this div a class name which
will be grid and then also gap 3. This
will only create the spacing between our
email input and then the submit button.
But I will show it to you in a second.
Don't worry. Then let's create another
div inside of here. This will be the
wrapper div for our label and our input.
So let's give it a class name which will
be grid and then also gap 2. In this
div, let's render a label component.
This is imported from the components
folder. And here's the thing. Please
listen to me. Please don't import your
components from Radics UI. If you import
your component from radics UI, you will
get a lot of errors and also the UI or I
guess the end result won't look as
expected. So whenever I import
components, I always import them from
the components folder. Please do the
same. And now let's import the label
component from the components and I want
to say email. And let's also give the
label an HTML 4 property. And this will
be equal to email. Underneath our label,
I want to render the input component
again imported from the components.
Let's give this input a type which will
be email and then also a placeholder.
And for the placeholder, I will just say
macample.com.
If I save this and again go back, you
will see this input right here which
looks absolutely beautiful. Let's also
render the submit button underneath our
input. So let's go underneath this wpper
div which has this gap too and then I
can again render the button component
which I already imported and inside of
here I will just say lock in or continue
with email. If I save this and again go
back you will see yeah this looks quite
nice but there's still one problem.
Currently there's no gap between our
separator and our content. So let's
again go back. Let's scroll a bit to the
top. And as you see, all of our content
is rendered in the card content
component. Therefore, it would also make
a lot of sense to pretty much create
like a I guess gap. So, let's give our
card content a class name. And then this
will be flex flex of column and gap
four. If I save this and again go back,
you will see that we now finally have a
bit of spacing. Also, if you're
wondering why I use right here flex
column and then right here grid, well,
honestly, there's no difference. You can
either use grid or flex column. The
result is the same. And honestly, I
think our lock and form looks beautiful.
Nevertheless, there are still a few
things which I want to update. So, for
example, on the top left corner, I want
to render a go back button. Then above
my card, I want to render my logo. And
then underneath my card, I want to
render like a little click on the terms
and privacy policy to learn more or
something like that. So therefore, let's
again head over back to our layout and
then let's update our layout. So
currently we render two divs. One div
which pretty much centers everything and
then the other diff which gives our
children this nice little maximum width.
Let's go above this maximum width div
and let's first of all create this back
button. So let's use the link component.
This is provided by next /link and this
will allow us to redirect the user. Now
you might ask me, hey John, why do we
use the link component and why don't we
just use the standard ATA tag? Well,
it's quite simple. The link component
provides us with two key benefits. First
of all, prefetching and then also client
side navigation. The A tag does not
provide any prefetching and also when
you navigate the user it will make a
hard navigation or it will do a hard
navigation which means the whole page
will refresh. We don't want that. So
let's delete the A tag and let's use the
link component. And again, if you're not
sure about all of the components or if
you don't know everything, this is fine.
The documentation is your best friend.
Just go to the documentation and search,
for example, for the link component.
Right here, you will see the link
component is a React component that
extends the HTML element to provide
prefetching and client side navigation
between routes. As you see, quite
simple. So let's again go back and our
link component currently complains and
that's because we are missing one
property which is the href and if the
user clicks on the link I want to
redirect the user to the index page and
then for our link I want to say or I
want to render the arrow left icon arrow
left is imported from lucid react this
is self-closing and let's also give it a
class name which will be size four and
then after our arrow left icon I will
also say back this means if I again go
back, you will see this right here. And
yeah, this link looks quite ugly. And
you know what I mean? What did I expect?
I did not add any class names. Of
course, the link looks quite boring and
ugly, I would say. So, here's the thing.
I want you to style the link exactly as
the chat and UI button. It should look
exactly the same. The same rounding, the
same paddings, the same shadow.
Literally, everything should be the
same. So, for example, we can go to the
button component and how about we just
copy all of these class names and paste
them right here for our link component.
Well, this will actually work. But you
know what? This is quite annoying and
not scalable. So, is there any other
solution? Yes, there is. There is a even
better solution and that's to also add a
class name and then use the button
variance function. So, let's import it
from the components and let's invoke the
function. So, here's the thing. This
function as mentioned is imported from
the components from the button component
and it pretty much injects all of these
styles right here into our link. This
means if I again go back what do we have
right here? Well, we have a link which
is styled exactly the same as a shad CN
button. And also from now on I will say
CN and not shad CN UI. So this button
looks quite nice but I want to position
it uh on the top left corner. Therefore,
let's again go back and then for the
link or right here in the button
variance, I will structure it. I want to
give it a variant which will be outline
and then also a class name and then for
the class name I want to give it a
position which will be absolute and then
top four and left four. If I save this
and again go back, you'll see this
button and it looks beautiful. And if I
click on the button, I will get
redirected to the index page. So we are
finished with the button and the next
step is to render the logo and also the
company name above this card. So right
here. So I want you pretty much create a
header and then also a footer and the
footer will render a text which will say
something like hey if you sign up you
agree to the privacy uh policy and
terms. Therefore, let's again go back uh
let's go to our layout and then right
here I want to go into this div where we
have this maximum width and inside of
here I want to again use the link
component as you all know we already
imported it. Let's give the link also an
href and this will be the index page
meaning an empty slash and then in the
link I want to render the company image
and or in other words the logo and the
company name. So this will be Marshall
LMS dot. If I again go back, you will
see it right here. But you know what? I
want to center it. Therefore, let's give
our link component a class name. And
then this will be flex items which will
be center gap which will be two to have
a bit of spacing self center and font
medium to have a bit of a bigger font
weight. If I again go back, you will see
that the font weight is now a bit bigger
and also the text, the logo, the company
name is centered. And as already
mentioned, I want to also render the
company logo. So right here in front of
our text, I want to get the image
component imported from next/ image. And
this is self-closing. Right here, I have
to provide two properties. And this is
first of all the source of our image and
then also an alt. For the alt, I will
just say logo. So where will we get our
source from? Or in other words, where
will we store our source? Well, in our
explorer, we have this public folder.
And as mentioned in here, we want to
store all of our public assets, images,
videos, fonts, whatever. So, in my
YouTube description, I will have a link.
This will redirect you to a website
where you can download all of the public
assets. And one public asset and maybe
also the only public asset uh will be uh
the logo itself. This is the logo as you
see. So let's again close this and let's
import a logo on the top. So I will say
import logo from at /public/logo.
Then we can use this logo. So if I
scroll to the bottom I can pass the logo
as my source. If I again go back you
will see yeah I mean the logo looks
beautiful but it's way too big.
Therefore we can add a width and a
height. So for the width this will be
32. And then for the height, this will
also be 42. No, I'm joking. It will also
be 32. I want to have this square aspect
ratio. This means if I again go back,
you will see, yeah, it's now way smaller
and the proportions look way better. So,
we are finished with this header. And
the next step is to render this little
footer. So, let's again go back. I want
to go underneath my children, but still
in this div with the maximum width. And
I want to create another div inside of
here. I will render by clicking
continue, you agree agree uh to our then
let's render a span element. This will
be terms of service and then after the
span we can also say and so and then
let's again render a span element and
then in the span I will render privacy
policy and then at the end I can render
a dot. So the complete sentence will be
by clicking continue you agree to our
terms of service and privacy policy.
This means if I again go back yeah
not so nice no let's style this div. So
I will give the div a class name and
this will be text balance text center to
center it in the middle. By the way, I
also misspelled text balance. And text
balance is just text w. So it's kind of
balanced if you understand what I mean.
And then we want to also change the text
size. So text xs and then the color
should be text muted foreground. This
means if I save this and again go back,
you will see yeah this already looks way
better. And also right now we have this
terms of service span element and then
also the privacy policy span element.
The thing is when the user hovers over
these two span elements I want to
showcase a hover state. Therefore uh
let's again go back and for the span
element I want to add a class name and
then this will be hover of text primary
and then we can also say hover which
will be underline. So this means if the
user hovers over our span or over this
text I want to display the primary color
and then also little underline. Let's
copy this class name and then I want to
also paste it for the second span
element. This means if I again go back
and hover over terms of service. You see
we get this uh text color. So the text
color updates and we also get an
underline as you see right here. Then I
can again zoom out and what's the next
step? Well the next step is to finally
implement authentication. And in this
video we will use better off. And what
is better off? Well, better off is the
most comprehensive authentication
framework for Typescript. They support a
lot of frameworks. So, if you go to the
documentation, you can go to the plug-in
section. And here you will see, oh no,
not to the plugins, but to the
integrations. So, right here you will
see they have support for Astro, Remix,
Next. This is the framework that we use.
Next, Sweltkit, even Expo. So, Better
Off is a very nice open-source
authentication solution. Now, you might
ask me, "Hey, Jan, why don't we use
Offjs? In a lot of your previous videos,
you used Offjs." Well, the answer is
quite simple. Better Off is better than
OffJS. Who would have thought? Better
Off has a lot more features. Also,
errors and issues get fixed way faster.
And if you go to the change lock, you
see there are constantly new features.
And that's also the reason why I
personally started using better off and
also why we will use it in this video.
This does not mean that offjs is bad.
No, it's still a great framework and I
also use it right now for my website
marshallcode.com. So it's still fine.
You can still use it but in this video
we will use better off. Also what I'll
quickly mention is or maybe you will ask
me, hey Jan, why don't we use kind in
this video? The answer is simple. Kind
is my favorite of solution. I love it. I
use it pretty much daily. The only thing
is kind makes a lot of sense in a B2B
application. But our application will be
a B2C application. This means pretty
much 90% of our customers won't be
paying customers. This also means I
won't need advanced features. I won't
need multiffactor off. I won't need for
example SSO. I won't need ROS and
permissions. And that's also the reason
why I won't implement kind in this
video. Nevertheless, if this would be
some sort of B2B LMS, then I would
implement kind because implementing
organizations with kind is super easy.
And also I created a very detailed and a
very nice video on organizations. So
right here, if you go to my YouTube
channel, then you will find this video
right here. Multi-tenant SA SAS
architecture in three simple steps. In
this video, I showcase how to build a
nice multi-tenant SAS architecture while
also creating this nice little
organization switcher. So yeah, let's
again close this. Oh, and by the way,
watch this video on file uploads. Super
important and super cool video. So let's
implement better off. So let's head over
to the documentation and then I want to
click on installation. Oh, and by the
way, please also head over to the
website better off. Scroll through the
landing page. It's very detailed. It
will also tell you or it will showcase
all of the features and yeah let's get
started. So I will head over to the
documentation and then to installation.
The first step is to install the package
which is better off. Again I will use
PNPM so I can copy the installation
command and then in my terminal I will
stop my dev server and paste the
installation command inside of here. And
also some people might write in the
comments, hey Jan, you don't have to
stop the dev server every time. You can
also create a second terminal tab. Yes,
I know in theory it works and it
shouldn't create any problems.
Nevertheless, I want to play it safe and
I don't want to create any bundling
issues. Therefore, I will also stop my
dev server every time. But you in theory
can also just create a second terminal
tab and install all of the packages
inside of there without stopping your
dev server. And now I can again restart
my dev server since we installed the
package. And the next step is to update
our environment variables because right
here it says create a ENV file. We
already did that. And then we want to
pretty much create a secret key. This
random value. So this secret key will be
used by the library for encryption and
generating hashes. You can generate one
by using the button below. So let's
generate a secret. And then we can copy
this better off environment variable. Uh
I want to open my env file and as you
see I don't have one. So let's create a
new one in our root directory. I can
create a new file and this will be ourv
file. Inside of here we will store all
of our secrets like for example the
better of secret. Then the next step is
to also set the base URL. This is the
local or not the local this is the URL
of our application. Since we are
currently in development the URL or our
URL is localhost 3000. Therefore, we can
copy this environment variable and again
paste it right here in our env file. The
next step is to create a better off
instance. This means we want to create a
file named off.ts in one of these
locations either in your project root
directory in your lip folder or in a
utils folder. You can also nest any of
these folders. But yeah, let's just
create it in the lip folder. So, I can
create uh open my explorer. Then let's
go right here into the lip folder and
let's create a off.ts file. Then we can
scroll to the bottom and then I will
copy this code and paste it right into
this off.ts file. As mentioned again,
this will just create the server side of
or better off instance. Then we can
scroll to the bottom and the next step
is to configure our database. So better
off requires a database to store user
data. You can easily configure better
off to use SQLite, Postgress or MySQL
with this right here. I cannot pronounce
it. I'm sorry. Handling queries and
migrations for these databases. So,
here's the thing. I don't want to use
this tool. Sorry again. I have no clue
how to pronounce it correctly. Instead,
I want to use an OM. Now, there are a
lot of OM on the market. You have
drizzle, you have type OM and a lot of
other ORMs. But in this video, we will
use Prisma. And the reason is quite
simple. Prisma is a relatively highlevel
ORM. It's very easy to understand and
it's also very easy to write queries and
create mutations and just in general to
work with the OM. Drizzle is also a very
nice OM. So not drizzle.com, but
OM.rizle.te.
This is also a very nice OM. It's also
relatively easy to use, but it's way
more low-level. You have to know a bit
of SQL to use it. And that's not a
problem. The reason why I won't use
Drizzle in this video is because they
are currently doing a huge rewrite for
version one. And since I don't want to
deprecate this tutorial, we will use
Prisma. And also, let me quickly
summarize what Prisma is. So, Prisma, as
mentioned, is an ORM. to be specific,
it's a TypeScript ORM and it's very easy
to use. They also offer a lot of other
products like a database and uh I don't
know Optimize Accelerate. We won't use
these paid products. The OM is
completely free and opensource. So let's
get started. So I want to open my
terminal and then in my terminal I want
to first of all install the OM. So I
want to do a PNPMI at Prisma/client.
This will install the Prisma client. And
then we have to also install a second
package and this will be PNPMI uh-d
uppercase D Prisma. So this will install
Prisma as a development dependency. And
as mentioned, this won't show up in your
production bundle size. Once these two
packages are installed, we can also
initialize Prisma. So let's run PNPM DLX
Prisma in it. So, as you see right here,
hey, your Prisma schema was created. You
can open it in your favorite editor. And
the next steps are first of all to set
the database URL in our env file. Then
we want to also set a provider. And then
we can run a few commands. But let's
first of all look at what Prisma even
created. So first of all, we have a new
Prisma folder. In the Prisma folder, we
have a schema file. And then in the
schema file, we will create our schema.
This means we will create all of the
tables with all of the uh columns and
then we will also create all of the
relations and then also if you open your
env file you will see that Prisma right
here created a dummy database URL. Let's
delete these comments. We don't need
them. And what we want to do is we want
to now create a real database and then
we want to connect Prisma to our real
database. So there are a lot of options
for databases. free ones, paid ones,
good ones, bad ones. But in this video,
we will use Neon. Neon is a Postgress
provider which got recently acquired,
but I guess this has nothing to do with
this video. It's super cool and it has a
lot of fancy features like for example
autoscaling. This means it can scale to
zero and it also offers branching. Now
in this tutorial we won't need scaling,
we won't need branching but still if you
go into production at some point in the
future then it's nice to have these
features. If we also quickly look at the
pricing you will see that they have a
very generous suite here which again
does not require any credit card. So we
can create 10 projects 0.5 GB storage
190 computer hours this is more than
enough. And also if you want to have
some sort of alternative then you can
also use superbase. This is also a
postgress provider. But honestly neon is
just faster and easier to set up.
Therefore I will use neon in this video.
So step number one is to first of all
log in. And once logged in you will see
all of your projects right here. If you
don't have any don't worry. I have quite
a few as you see. And also I am on the
scale plan but this also is not
important for this video. So let's
create a new project. This means let's
create a new database. For the database
name, I will just call it
Marshall-LMS-YouTube-public.
Then for the Postgress version, I will
choose the latest one. In this case,
this is version 17. For the database
name, it will just generate a random
one. Then for the cloud provider, Azure
is fine enough. And for the region, I
will select the default one. Then let's
create our database. And you know what?
Our database has already been created.
So, Neon has a very fancy architecture
in the background which allows it to
spin up databases in milliseconds. So,
let's connect to our database. I will
click on connect. And then right here,
please select Prisma. Um, this is our
ORM. And then here we have a schema
file. We don't need it. We want to click
on env. And here we already get our
database URL. So you want to uncomment
the next line if your Prisma version is
lower than 5.1. So let's quickly check
if I open my package.json what version
of Prisma do we have installed 6.8.
Therefore we can leave it un commented.
And we want to just copy the first
database URL. I will then again open my
env file and I will delete this dummy
database URL and instead paste what I
just copied. So we already set up Neon.
We are already finished which means I
can close the website. So let's head
over back to the better off
documentation and I want to scroll to
the adapters section. So right here it
says if you prefer to use an ORM as we
do or if your database is not supported
by this tool you can use one of the
built-in adapters and Prisma is a
built-in adapter. So we want to pretty
much first of all import this adapter
Prisma adapter. So I will open my off
configuration file and I will paste the
import statement on the top and then we
want to also initialize this Prisma
adapter in the off configuration file.
So I will again just copy the code
example and paste it right here. So
let's quickly analyze the code. So again
right here this first of all creates the
off configuration file for the server
side. Inside of here we have a database
property and we set it equal to the
Prisma adapter. This Prisma adapter
accepts two arguments. First of all, the
Prisma instance itself which we
currently haven't created. We will do
that in a second and also the provider.
So what database do we use? Do we use
MongoDB, MySQL, SQLite? No, we are using
Neon and Neon in the background uses
Postgress. And the next step is to
create a Prisma instance. So please head
over to Chrome and then in Chrome search
for Nex.js JS uh Prisma best practices.
Here you will get a few results but
please click on the first one. This will
give you all of the best practices but
there's only one thing which we need. So
right here at the top they say avoid
multiple Prisma client instances when
developing an X.js application. One
common issue is accidentally creating
multiple instances of the Prisma client.
This often occurs due to Nex.js's hot
module reloading feature in development.
Nex.js's hot module reloading feature
reloads modules frequently to reflect
code changes instantly. However, this
can lead to multiple instances of Prisma
client being created. Which means we
have to somehow fix this problem. So
here's the recommended solution. To
avoid this, create a single Prisma
client instance using a global variable.
And this is exactly what we will do. So
in my codebase uh we can again open the
code structure or the project structure
and then in the lip folder I want to
create a db.ts file. This will be our
Prisma instance or inside of there we
will configure our global variable our
global Prisma variable. We can then copy
this code example. Let's go back and
then I will paste it inside of here. As
you see we get one error and it says
module Prisma client has no exported
member Prisma client. Hm. What's the
problem? We literally just copied the
code example right here from the
official docs as you see. So, sadly,
these docs haven't been updated in quite
some time. And this import statement is
incorrect. So, let's just delete it.
Right now, we still get a few errors.
Don't worry. Let's for now just uh close
this file. We will fix it in a second.
Now if we again go back to the off
configuration file, we can hover over
Prisma and as you see we can add the
import from the DB file. Let's do that.
And I think we now set up our database
provider. So if I go back to the
documentation, the next step is to add
or create the database tables. So better
off includes a CLI tool to help manage
the schema required by the library and
they provide a generate command and this
command generates an RM schema or SQL
migration file. So let's copy this code
example with this generate command and
then I can just copy it or not copy it
but paste it into my terminal. Again
this will generate this schema. As you
see I have to install the package so I
will do that quickly. Oh, and by the
way, friends, don't forget to stay
hydrated. Drink some water or drink a
Pepsi. No, this is not recommended.
Drink some water. Stay hydrated. Uh-huh.
We got an error. Couldn't read your off
config. Reference error. Prisma client
is not defined. So, what's the problem?
Well, again, if we open our off.ts file,
or not our off.ts, but our db.ts file,
we currently don't import Prisma client
because we currently don't have a Prisma
client. To generate a Prisma client, we
have to first of all push our schema.
But to create a schema, we have to
create a Prisma client. I know so
stupid. So let's open our schema. And in
our schema, we will just create a dummy
model. So I will create a model. I will
call it test. And then I will open it.
And then I will create an ID. This will
be of type string at id default UYU ID.
And then I will create a test property
or column which will be of type string.
That's it. Then we can open our terminal
and inside of here I will run pnpm dlx
prisma db push. This will push the
schema to our database or in other words
it will sync our database schema with
this local Prisma schema. So as you see
your database is now in sync with your
Prisma schema. Nice. Let's quickly head
over to the Neon dashboard and let's see
if everything worked. So right here in
the sidebar you will find the tables
tab. Let's click on it and as you see we
should get one table and this is the
test table. So everything worked as
expected. So we can again go back and
then in our DB file we can import our
Prisma client. So I will hover over
Prisma client. Then we can click on
quick fix and I want to add the import
from generated / Prisma. Then I will
click on enter. And as you see
everything now works as expected. So
here's the thing. In version five or
with Yeah, I think with version five, we
got a big update. In previous versions,
all of the client code got abstracted in
the node modules folder. Now in the lip
folder, we have a new generated folder.
This generated folder is pretty much all
of the code which is created by Prisma.
These are all of your types. Again, in
previous versions, this was abstracted
away in the note modules folder. they
now give you access to this generated
folder and that's also why we have to
import Prisma client from this generated
folder. So since this is finished we can
now finally generate also our better off
schema. So I can again copy this uh
command this script and then in my
terminal I will just paste it again. In
theory it should work and as you see it
says the file schema.prisisma already
exists. Do you want to override the
schema to the file? Yes, I want to do
that. So let's click on yes. And as you
see it was successful. And in our schema
we now have a few tables. So I can first
of all delete the test table. I don't
need it anymore. And now we have a user
table. We have a session table, an
account table and then also a
verification table. These are all of the
required tables and also the required
columns for uh better off to work as
expected. So I think we are finished
with the schema. So let's again head
over to the documentation and the next
step is to already configure our
authentication methods. So configure the
authentication methods you want to use.
Better off comes with built-in support
for email password and social login
providers. So we can again open our
off.ts configuration file. And as
mentioned I want to allow the user to
sign in uh either with GitHub or using
the user's email. And then we will send
a magic link to the user. So let's first
of all configure GitHub OF. So
underneath our database property, we can
get the social providers property. This
is an object and inside of here we get
quite a few options. So as mentioned, we
want to use GitHub and this is again an
object. And inside of here we have to
define two key properties. First of all,
the client ID. For now, this will be an
empty string. And then also the client
secret. Again, for now, this will be an
empty string. So, where do we get our
client ID from? And where do we get our
client secret from? Well, who would have
thought? From the GitHub website. So,
let's head over to github.com. I will
blur out a few things. And then I want
to go to the settings. Then we want to
scroll to the bottom. And here you will
find the developer settings. Then I want
to click on OF apps. And we want to
create a new O of app. So first of all,
we have to provide an application name.
This will be Marshall. So I will spell
it correctly. Marshall LMS. Then for the
homepage URL, this will be localhost
3000. So I will copy it and paste it.
And then we want to also add an
authorization callback URL. So let's
head over to the better of
documentation. And then I want to click
on authentication. And then right here I
want to click on GitHub. This is what we
are using right now. And as you see it
says, make sure to set the redirect URL
to localhost 3000/ AI/off/callback/Gitub
for local development. And since we are
in local development, we can copy this
URL. Let's again go back and then I will
paste it right here. So again, localhost
3000/ AI/off/callback/github.
Then I don't want to enable device flow.
And then I can register my application
right here. We will get a client ID. I
will copy it. Go back and instead of
pasting it right here, I will instead
paste it into my env file because this
at the end of the day is a secret. So I
will create a github_client
ID and this will be equal to the value
that I just copied. And then I want to
also generate a client secret. So let's
click on this button. So as you see my
client secret got generated and it's
important that you copy the secret now
because you won't be able to see it
again. So I will copy it then I can go
back and I want to create a new ID or a
new environment variable and this will
be the github
secret and you know what let me uh
rename these environment variables. So
this uh first one will be of
undersc_github_client
id and then the second one will be also
of un_github
secret and then this will be equal to
the value that I just copied. So this is
finished. Let me copy the off github
client ID. Let's go back and then for
the client ID I want to pass my process
uh env
client ID. Then for the client secret I
can also copy the name. I can go back
and again I want to pass it using my
process.env. So I will say
process.env.off
github secret. As you see I get two
errors and it says right here type
string or undefined is not assignable to
type string. So what's the problem?
Well, TypeScript currently does not know
if your secrets are defined or not. So
there are two ways to fix it. We could
either right here just say as string and
then also for the second one I could say
as string. And as you see the error goes
away. So you could say, "Hey Jan, let's
continue." Sure, we could do that. But
still, we don't verify right now that
the environment variable actually
exists. We just say, "Hey, in theory, it
should exist. Don't throw an error." But
honestly, I don't really know if we have
this environment variable. Therefore, in
this video, we will implement T3 env. So
T3 envy here says, "Forgetting
environment variables during build can
be a hassle and difficult to debug if a
buck is caused by a missing environment
varable. This package provides a simple
way to define environment varables
validation for your app. This library
does all the grunt work for you. Simply
define your schema and use your
environment vables safely. So in the
sidebar we can click on next.js because
we use Nex.js JS as our framework and we
have to install two dependencies. First
of all, the T3 package itself, the
dependency and also Zot. So what is
Zord? Well, Zot is a TypeScript first
schema validation library with static
type inference. Zot will help us to
create a Zot schema. So Zot at the end
of the day pretty much allows you to
write rules. So we will say in the Z
schema, hey our env schema will have a
GitHub ID, a GitHub secret, a database
URL, some sort of other secret and then
we will use T3 or T3 will take the Z
schema and then it will compare your Z
schema against your ENV file. So right
here if I open my ENV file, I have all
of these secrets. If I for example
delete the off GitHub secret, it will
throw an error and it will say, "Hey,
when I compare the Z schema against your
env file, I see that there's one
environment variable missing." In this
case, the off GitHub secret. And this is
a huge benefit for us because we will
now know definitively that our
environment variables are defined. So,
let's copy the first installation
command because we are not using JSR. So
I will just copy it and then in our
terminal I will just paste it right
here. And also right here they mention
although we'll use sort as examples
throughout these docs you can use any
validator. Honestly zord is pretty much
the industry standard and that's also
why we will use sort in this video. So
right here they already provide us with
an example schema. So let's just copy
it. Then let's go back and I want to
create in my lip folder. So right here a
new file which will be called env.ts.
Then I will paste what I just copied.
And again what do we do right here?
Well, first of all we create this env
variable. This constant. This is equal
to create env. Create env
schema. Right here we define all of our
variables. And as you see there's a
slight distinction. We can either define
server side variables or client side
variables. If we look at our env file,
you will see that all of these secrets
are server side specific. Therefore, our
client will be empty, which means I can
just delete the client. We won't have
any client secrets right now. This also
means we don't need the object. And
also, here's a very important comment.
If you're using Nex.js which has a
smaller version than 13.4, you will need
to specify the runtime environment
manually. But since we using a Nex.js JS
with a version which is bigger than
13.4. We only need to dstructure the
client variables. So let's delete this
one-time environment object and instead
let's uncomment this experimental
one-time env.
So again inside of here we have to only
destructure the client vables since we
don't have any right now. This will just
be an empty object. So let's also define
all of our server environment viables.
First of all, we have our database URL.
This is already defined right here. The
second secret is our better off secret.
So, I will copy it and paste it right
here. This will be of type Z.string. And
we want to have a minimum length of one.
The next secret is our better off URL.
Let's copy it, paste it, and this will
be equal or this will be of type Z dot
string. And to be specific, this will be
an URL, which means let's append the URL
method at the end. Then we also have the
off GitHub client ID secret. So I will
copy it, paste it and this will be equal
or this will be of type Z.string and
then I can also append dot minimum one.
So at least a minimum character length
of one and the last environment variable
for now is our of GitHub secret. I will
copy it, paste it and this will be of
type Z.string and then of course minimum
one. So this should be already it which
means I can close this env file. I can
close this env file and instead of now
getting our secret through this process
env we can use our env. So let's delete
this. Let's also delete this right here.
And right here I want to import env. ENV
is imported from the env file. Please
don't import it from process because it
won't work. Import it from the env file.
And then we want to get our client ID.
And as you see we also get auto
completion which is huge. I mean I
misspelled already so many environment
variables in my career. So this is a
huge timesaver. So we want to get our
off GitHub client ID. And then for our
client secret I can also say env dot and
again we get autocomp completion. And I
want to get my off GitHub secret. And as
you also see I don't have to mark these
secrets as string and that's because T3
envile
time. So at compile time it goes through
our env file. It see the user defined
all of these environment variables.
Let's check the Z schema. Does it
compare correctly? Yes, it compares
correctly which means all of the all of
the secrets are defined and that's why
also TypeScript and first them as type
string. So we are almost finished with
setting up better off and I want to
finally allow my users even though I
don't have any users to sign up or in
other words sign in with GitHub. So
let's head over back to the
documentation. I will go to the get
started guide and to be specific to the
installation guide. So we are finished
with step number one with step number
two with step number three with step
number four. Oh my god with step number
five with step number six and the next
step is step number seven and this is to
mount a route handler. So to handle API
requests you need to set up a route
handler on your server. This will then
allow the user to finally sign up, sign
in, sign out, uh create organizations,
even though we won't allow it, but just
in general, this is needed for all of
the operations. So right here, they have
a few examples for pretty much all of
the popular frameworks. We use Next.js.
And I want to first of all copy the
route structure. So if I zoom in uh
you'll see that the route structure is
slappi/off
/all/out.ts.
So here's a little trick. We can just
copy everything right here. So API of we
can just copy it. Then I can go back and
then in my explorer instead of creating
a separate folder or and first of all I
want to go into the app folder and then
instead of creating a new folder I want
to create a new file. And then if I
paste this route structure into this
route it or into this file it will
automatically create the correct folder
structure. So we now have an API folder
in all folder then this all folder and
then we have this route.ts. And again
please make sure that you create this
route handler in the app folder. And as
you see I also interchange the term
route handler and API route quite a bit.
So what's the difference? Well, there
literally is no difference. A route
handler is an API route. An API route is
a route handler. In my humble opinion,
route handler is just a term created by
the Nex.js team for marketing purposes
because at the end of the day, it's
literally just an API route. Therefore,
call it however you want to call it. It
does not matter. Then I want to copy
this code example. I then we can go back
and I will paste it inside of here. So
we have finished with our route handler
and let's see what the next step is and
step number eight is to create a client
instance. So the client site library
will help you to interact with the off
server. Better off comes with a client
for all the popular web frameworks
including vanilla JavaScript. So let's
scroll a bit to the bottom and right
here they already have a code example.
So I will just copy it and then we can
go back and then in my lip folder I will
create a new file called off-client.ts
and then I will just paste the code
inside of here. As you see we also have
a comment right here and it says the
base URL of the server optional if
you're using the same domain. As you
know we use Nex.js and the client and
server are both I guess routed to the
same domain. Therefore we can just
delete the space URL. We don't need it.
You can leave it there if you want to.
It does not matter. Then let's go back.
What's the next step? Well, there is no
next step. That's it. You are now ready
to use better off in your application.
Continue to basic usage to learn how to
use the off instance to sign in users.
Yeah, I mean, let's try it out. So,
let's go to basic usage. And if I scroll
a bit to the bottom, it will say right
here that we can use our off client to
sign up our users. So let's sign up our
users with GitHub. Let's go. So I will
go back to my uh page.tsx. So to my sign
in route or lockin route and then as you
all know we already render our button
right here. And when the user clicks on
this button we want to call pretty much
uh better off. And then better off
should sign in the user using GitHub or
it should pretty much manage the whole
authentication flow. So let's scroll a
bit to the top. Let's go above the
return statement and let's create a new
async function. So async function and I
will call it signin with GitHub and then
in the function I want to start the off
or in other words the signin flow using
the off client which we just created. So
inside of here I will say await off
client and off client is imported from
our lip folder and then I want to use
the signin method. But now you might ask
me, hey Jan, wouldn't it be smarter to
use the sign up method? I mean, there's
a quite big probability that the user
pretty much uses our application for the
very first time. Well, this is actually
a very good question and the simple
answer is no. But why is the answer no?
Well, the thing is right here, we want
to allow the user to sign in with
GitHub. GitHub is an ooth off provider.
And when using O of off, there's no such
thing as signing up a user. You can only
sign in a user. And that's also the
reason why we will use the sign-in
method. Because when you use the sign-in
method, you can call the social method.
But if you use the sign up method that
you can't call a social method, there's
only email. And the thing is signing up
a user only works with email and
password. It does not work with O off
and it also does not work with magic
links and that's why I right here use
the sign in method and then we want to
call the social method because I want to
allow the user to sign in using GitHub.
Then we want to invoke it the struct and
inside of here I have to provide a few
properties. First of all the provider I
want to allow the user to sign in with
GitHub. The next step is to provide the
call back URL. This is the URL where we
will redirect the user to after a
successful signin. And I want to
redirect the user to our index page.
This means an empty slash. Then we want
to also provide fetch options. And fetch
options or in the fetch options you can
listen for specific events like for
example the onsuccess event or the onour
event and we want to specifically listen
for these two events. So this is an
object. Let's open it. And I want you
first of all listen uh for the onsuccess
event. And then this will be equal to a
standard error function. And inside of
here if the signin was successful I want
to return a toast. And for our toast
library we installed sona. So let's
import our toast from sona. And then I
want to use the success method because I
want to showcase a success toast. And
then we can invoke it and as an argument
we can provide the message which will be
showcased when rendering the toast. And
I want to say hey signed in with GitHub
uh comma you will be redirected dot dot
dot. Then we can also listen uh for the
on event. This will be also equal to a
standard error function. And then inside
of here again I want to return a toast
dot error this time. And for the
message, you know what? Let's render the
actual error message. So, right here in
our params, we can get the error object
itself. And then uh we can return the
error. Eerror dossage. But here's the
thing. Currently, our toast library
won't work because if you head over to
the SH CN website and type in sona, uh
let me go right here, sona. And if you
scroll a bit to the bottom, you will see
that the first step is to first of all
add the toaster component or in other
words render it in our layout. So uh
let's go back. Uh then I want to open
the root layout and then in the theme
provider but underneath the children I
want to import the toaster component.
Please make sure that you import it from
the components and not from Sona. The
toast itself is imported from Sona but
the toaster is imported from the
components. This is self-closing and
later on we might also configure the
toaster a bit but for now we will just
leave it as is. So I can again close our
layout and you know what in theory this
should already be finished and it should
also work. So we want to now call this
function. So uh right here for the
button I can add a on click handler and
then this will be equal or I want to
then call the sign in with GitHub
function. Also currently there's one
problem. Before I test it out, I want to
pretty much also show a pending state
because currently if a user would click
on this button, there would be zero
pending states. We would just pretty
much wait until the request would be
finished and then we would redirect the
user. But I want to give the user
feedback and also if the submission is
currently pending, I want to make the
button disabled. So this means we want
to somehow uh keep track of the
progress. Now there are two options to
do that. Either the I guess standard way
of using a use state hook and then
having a pending or a getter which will
be pending and the setter set pending.
This works but you know what there's a
even better solution and this is the use
transition hook. Now if you have never
heard about the use transition hook then
let's head over to the React website. So
react.dev and then inside of here I will
search for use transition. Use
transition is a React hook that lets you
render a part of the UI in the
background. Here's the thing. React the
React documentation is sometimes great
and sometimes absolute trash because
this s has a lot of words but it does
not explain anything. So what is meant
by this gibberish? Well, at the end of
the day, the use transition hook will
can be used to show a pending state. So
you start a transition, the code is run
in the transition and while the
transition is pretty much pending, the
is pending boolean is set to true. And
now you might also ask me, hey Jan, why
should we use the use transition hook if
there's also the use state hook? I mean
the end result is pretty much the same,
right? Well, there are a few caveats and
for example, right now we won't use it,
but later on we will use a revalidate
path function. This will revalidate our
cache. And the thing is the normal use
state hook won't take this revalidate
path function into account. So it will
stop the pending state earlier. Our code
will still run but the pending state
won't work anymore. If this currently
sounds confusing, don't worry. I will I
guess show you a live example later on.
Let's copy this code example. Let's go
back and then above our async function
but still in the export default function
I can paste this code. I want to then
import use transition from react. And
then also I want to rename the getter
and setup. So instead of is pending this
will be GitHub uh pending and instead of
start transition this will be start
GitHub transition. And then it pretty
much works exactly the same as a
standard uh use state hook. What we can
do right now is first of all copy all of
the code in this async function sign in
with GitHub. I will delete it for now
but please keep it in your clipboard.
And then inside of here I want to first
of all initialize the start GitHub
transition function. So let's say right
here start GitHub transition. Then I
want to invoke it inside of here. I want
to then create an async arrow function.
So let's say async and as mentioned this
will be an arrow function and then
inside of here I can again paste my
code. And how does this exactly work?
Well, again this start GitHub transition
function will start right now instantly.
It will then wait until this code is
finished and once it's finished it the
start GitHub transition function will
also see hey the transition the
submission is finished. Let's set the
GitHub pending boolean to false. And now
let's use this GitHub uh pending
boolean. So if I scroll to the bottom I
can add a disabled state for our button
and it will be equal to our GitHub
pending boolean. So if it's true our
button will be disabled. And then also
instead of just rendering sign in with
GitHub I want to render or I want to
create a turnary. So I will copy the
code again. Leave it in your clipboard.
And then let's create a turnary. And
let's say hey if GitHub pending is true
then I want to use a question mark and I
want to render the loader to icon. So I
want to get this loader to icon from
lucid react. This is self-closing. And
then I want to also add a class name.
And then this icon will have a size of
four, which means width four and height
four. And then also animate spin. This
means our icon will pretty much animate
and spin. And then underneath the loader
icon, I want to render a span. And then
I will just say loading dot dot dot. And
if GitHub pending is not true, then we
can use a colon. And I want to render
what I just copied. So let's again use
empty tags. And then I will paste this
GitHub icon and sign in with GitHub. So
what did we just do? Well, we set up the
use transition hook for our pending
states. This uh GitHub pending boolean
is used to first of all set our disabled
state, but it's also used for our
turnary. If we are currently submitting,
then we will render loading dot dot dot.
If we are not submitting, then we will
render our initial default state. So
let's test it out. I will save
everything. I will restart my dev server
and I already know that we will get an
error. But don't worry, we will fix it
together. So right here it says you are
importing a component that needs use
transition. This react hook only works
in a client component. To fix it, mark
the file or its parent with the use
client directive. So what's the problem?
Well, right now we use two core things.
So first of all, I implemented the use
transition hook and also right here we
have this async function. So I'm not
sure if you knew it, but Nex.js builds
on top of two key principles, server
components and client components. What's
that? Good question. So if you go to the
documentation and if you search for how
to use server and client components,
then you will find this section. And
right here they say by default layouts
and pages are server components which
lets you fetch data and render parts of
your UI on the server. Optionally cache
the result and stream it to the client.
When you need interactivity or browser
APIs you can use client components to
layer in functionality. So here's the
thing. As a default all pages in XJS are
server components. Server components run
completely on the server side. This
means all of the content is rendered on
the server side with zero JavaScript.
This keeps your bundle size small and it
also makes your application super fast
because again there's no client side
JavaScript involved. The only problem is
you can't create any interactivity. The
use transition hook creates
interactivity. This async function
creates interactivity and this does not
work in a server component because again
these interactive I guess features need
a JavaScript bundle to use or to
implement interactivity you want to
implement client components. So right
here they have a section when to use
server and client components. The client
and server environment have different
capabilities. Server and client
components allow you to run logic in
each environment depending on your use
case. So you want to use client
components when you for example need
state event handler. So for example the
onclick handler life cycle logic browser
only APIs or custom hooks and then you
want to use server components when you
need to fetch data when you want to use
API keys when you want to reduce the
amount of JavaScript in the browser when
you want to imp uh improve FCP. So at
the end of the day, think of everything
like this. You want to use server
components. Whenever you fetch data,
every component, every page as a default
is a server component. If you need
interactivity, then you can either mark
the page itself as a client component or
you can create a separate component and
mark the component itself as a client
component. The thing is when you mark a
component as a client component or a
page then you won't be able to fetch any
data anymore in this page because it's
now a client component and it does not
only run on the server side anymore. So
that's something that you should
remember. So let's mark this whole page
as use client. And then if I again go
back you will see that this error will
go away. And also maybe before I test
out everything um we don't really want
to render this message generated from
better off. Instead let's just say right
here internal server error. This is a
bit better and I guess let's test it
out. So I will click on sign in with
GitHub. We have this nice pending state
and we get an error toast internal
server error. What what's the problem?
So let's go back and if I open my
terminal, it says right here, better off
error model verification does not exist
in the database. If I open my schema, I
literally have right here a verification
model. So what's the problem? Well,
actually the problem is a very simple
one. So let's head over back to the Neon
console to the Neon dashboard and let's
click right here on overview or not on
overview but on tables. If you wait for
the loading spinner, you will see, huh,
we only have one table. What's the
problem? Well, when we generated our
schema, our new tables, we did not sync
with uh our schema with our database.
Therefore, let's open our terminal. And
then inside of here, I will run PNPM DLX
Prisma DB push. This will now take my
local schema and it will sync it with my
database schema or it will pretty much
push these new tables into the uh remote
real database schema. This means if I
again go back and do a hard refresh, you
will see the new tables right here. And
this also means that our authentication
flow should now finally work. So let's
again go back and then in my terminal I
will again restart my dev server. And
then I can also do a hard refresh right
here. So my server has restarted. And if
I click on the button on the magic
button, we have a pending state and we
got redirected. So I will write here
authorize myself. And let's see. I
should get redirected to the index page.
Wow, I got redirected. But was this
successful? Well, I got an email on my
phone, which means I in theory
authenticated. Um maybe we can open our
inspector and then we can go to our
application. Let's see what do we have
right here. Uhhuh. Better off session.
So if you open your inspector and go to
the application and then go to the
cookies, you will find this better off
session cookie. And this means that our
authentication flow was successful. So
let's close this again. And you know
what? I want to kind of render my
session data right here in the index
page. So uh we can go back to our
page.tsx to our root index page. And
right here I want to get my user
session. Now here's the thing. Better
off is a very nice authentication
library because it allows you to get the
user session natively both on the server
side but also on the client side. Let's
for now first of all get the user
session on the server side. So let's
again head over to the documentation.
Then I want to click on integrations and
I want to click on next.js right here.
If you scroll a bit to the bottom, then
you will see right here react server
components and server actions. And to
get the user session, we want to use
this code right here. So we want to call
the API, then this get session method.
And then we want to pass headers. So I
will just copy this code example and
paste it right here above our return
statement. Again, constant session is
equal to await. Aapi get session. And
then we will pass our headers right
here. As you see, we get quite a few
errors. What's the problem? First of
all, we want to uh import off from our
lip folder. The next error is for our
await expression. So, it says right
here, await expressions are only allowed
with an async functions. And at the top
levels of modules and right here, we
also already have a quick fix. And it
says, did you mean to mark this function
as async? And yes, I want to mark this
function as an export default async
function. But now you might ask me, hey
Jan, is this even safe? Should you even
mark a function as asynchronous,
especially an export default function?
And the answer or the simple answer is
yes. This is completely safe to do. The
thing is this is a server component. As
mentioned, every page as a default is a
server component. It only becomes the
client component if you mark it with
this use client directive. But if it's a
server component, everything on the
server side, which also means you can
mark your function as a sync. Let's also
import headers. And headers is imported
from next/ headers and then we can
render our user session. So underneath
the theme toggle I will create a turnary
and I will say hey if we have a session
then let's use the question mark and I
want to render the session do user dot
name and if we don't have a session then
I will just render a button which is
imported from the components and I will
say lock out. If I save this and again
go back and do a hard refresh you will
see on the top left corner my name I
will also create a bit of padding
because right now it's quite hard to see
something. So padding let's say 24. And
if I go back yeah Jan. So this worked
exactly as expected. Let's again head
over back to our login page. And here we
have one problem. So as you see I'm
authenticated right? I render my name
Jan. But if I'm authenticated I don't
want to be able or the user shouldn't be
able to reach the login route. Therefore
we want to also check if the user has a
valid session. But now we have a huge
problem because again if I open this
page.tsx tsx then you will probably
remember that I marked this component as
a client component and also if you
remember I said if we have a client
component then we cannot fetch data on
the server side in this component that's
a huge problem and the thing is I want
to still fetch the ser or the session on
the server side I know I could fetch it
on the client side but I want to do it
on the server side so how can we fix
this problem well the answer or the
solution is quite simple we want to uh
create a separate component for our
login form and then render all of the
code inside of there. We will mark the
component as a client component. But the
page itself, this page.tsx should be a
server component and then we will fetch
the user session in this page. So let's
do that. So in this dockin folder, I
will create another folder and this will
be called underscore components. Why do
I call it underscore components? Good
question. So if you go to the
documentation and search for private
folders, you will find this section. And
right here it says private folders can
be created by prefixing a folder with an
underscore underscore folder name. This
indicates the folder is a private
implementation detail and should not be
considered by the routing system thereby
opting the folder and all its subfolders
out of routing. So this means that this
folder right here is just a private
folder. And to be specific, this folder
will only store very specific
components. So as you see or as you all
know, we have already a components
folder in our root directory. Inside of
here, we store all of our general
components, our card component, the
button component, the checkbox
component. These components are reused
all throughout the application. But all
of the components which are very I guess
feature specific well I want to store
them right alongside the code. So for
example this component which we will
create in a second will only be used in
this login page. It won't be reused and
that's also why I create a components
folder right in this login folder. So
right here let's create a new file and
this will be the lockin form.tsx
file. As mentioned we need a JavaScript
bundle. So let's mark this component as
use client and then I can go back to my
page.tsx and I can literally copy
everything in the return statement. So I
will just copy it, go back and then
right here we can create an export
function. This will be lockin form and
then I can just open this function.
Let's create a return statement and then
I will paste everything that I just
copied. As you see we currently get a
few errors but that's not important.
Let's go back to the login page. I can
delete everything in the return
statement. And then I can instead render
or import the lockin form component.
This is self-closing. And then I want to
also copy this async function and the
use transition hook. I will copy it and
then paste it right here into my lockin
form. And as you see I still get quite a
few errors. And that's because we have
to import all of these I guess
components, features and stuff like
that. So let's go back to the login
page. And then I will just copy all of
these import paths. I will go back and
paste them right here on the top. As you
see, I don't get any errors anymore. And
if I go back to my page.tsx, everything
will still work as expected. And then in
my login page, I can now finally fetch
my user session. So I will create a
constant session and this will be equal
to a of is imported from the lip folder
API and then get session. This is the
method which I want to use. Then let's
invoke it. That's the structure. And
inside of here we have to pass our
headers. So headers will be equal to
await headers. And headers is imported
from next/ headers. I want to also
invoke it. And now we get one error. And
it says hey await expressions are only
allowed with an async functions. So
let's mark this function as
asynchronous. And this error will go
away. But now we have a new error.
What's the problem? Well, prevent client
components from being async functions.
Right now, this page is still marked as
use client. So, let's delete the use
client directive. And this error is also
gone. As mentioned right here, I want to
check if the user has a valid session.
Therefore, let's create an if statement.
And let's say, hey, if we have a
session, then let's open this and I want
to redirect the user to the index page.
So, let's create a return redirect. and
redirect is imported from next
slashnavigation and then as an argument
I have to provide the URL to redirect
to. So in this case this will be the
index page. So an empty slash. If I
again go back and do a hard refresh you
will see that I will get redirected to
the index page. Let's again try to
navigate to /lockin. If I click on enter
I will instantly get redirected back to
the index page. And also what is this
redirect uh function? Good question. If
you hover over it, you will see this
function allows you to redirect the user
to another URL. It can be used in server
components, route handlers, and server
actions. So this only works on the
server side, but since this is a server
component, everything works as expected.
In a client component, you would use the
use router hook, but we will come to
that a bit later on. So I have currently
one problem. If I try to reach the
lockin route, I will get redirected back
to the index page. This is fine. This is
expected. But there's currently no way
for me to lock out. I mean, there's no
button. As you see right here, I render
my name Jan, but I want to render also a
lockout button and then I want to also
be able to lock out. So if we go back to
our codebase right here, we get the user
session on the server side and then we
have this turnary where I say hey if we
have a valid session then let's render
the username and if there's no valid
user session then instead of rendering
lock out I want you of course render
lockin. I mean if there's no session how
could a user lock out? So yeah the thing
is to lock out we have to use the off
client. So again, if I open it quickly,
this is our off client and we want to
use the off client to log out. But the
off client only works in client
components, but currently we get the
user session on the server side and you
can't use a client or something that
needs the client side in a server
environment. So what am I trying to tell
you? Well, we have to mark this page as
a client component and then we want to
get the user session on the client uh on
the client side instead uh instead of on
the server side. So let's go back to the
better off documentation. Then I want to
add over to the docs to basic usage and
then right here they have a section
called client side. So better off
provides a use session hook to easily
access session data on the client side.
This hook is implemented using nano
store and has support for each supported
framework and vanilla client ensuring
that any changes to the session such as
signing out are immediately reflected in
your UI. So right here we can just copy
this code example. I can go back and
then instead of rendering the or instead
of having this constant session I will
delete it and paste what I just copied.
Uh I can also delete this headers import
the off import and I will make or mark
this page as use client. If I again go
back we get one error. That's because we
have to delete this async modifier. And
then I want to also import my off client
from the lip folder. As you see we
structure right here four properties.
First of all the data itself. This means
the session and this could be either
defined or undefined. Then we also have
an error object. This will be again
defined if we have an error. If there's
no error, this will be undefined. And
then we also have this refetch function.
And with that, we can then refetch the
session. But we don't want to refetch
the session. We don't need this error.
And we also don't need the is pending
boolean. And we only need our session.
So since we now get our session on the
client side, it in theory should work.
So if I go back and do a hard refresh,
we see for a split second the login
button. That's because again we fetch on
the client side. This means on the
client side there's a little delay and
since we don't get a session instantly
we have a fall back and the fallback is
at the start false. So as a default the
session is false while our off client
fetches the user session. That's why we
render this lockin button for a split
second. But once we fetched our user
session and once better off sees that
the user has a valid session it renders
the username. So that's why you have the
splitsecond delay. Again, if I go back
and do a hard refresh for a millisecond,
we see this lock in button and then we
see, hey Jan, because I have a valid
session. Okay, I think you all know that
that's nothing groundbreaking. Uh let's
also render our lockout buttons. So I
can wrap this P tag in a div element or
with a div element. And then underneath
the P tag, I will again render a button
component and I will say lockout. This
lockout button should call a function.
So above the return statement, I will
create a function, an async function. It
will be called a sign out. And then I
can just open it inside of here or let's
again head over back to the
documentation. If you scroll a bit to
the top, you will find the section sign
out. So to sign out a user, you can use
the sign out function provided by the
client. So again, I can just copy this
code example. I can go back and paste it
inside of here. So as you see we just
say await offclients sign out. This is
the function and then again this sign
out function exposes fetch options and
fetch options as you know uh pretty much
gives you a few events. So on success,
on error and stuff like that, we want to
listen for the on success event because
if the user signed out successfully, we
want to redirect the user to the login
route or you know what, let me delete
the /loin. I want to redirect the user
to the index page. And also right here
they use router. What is router? So
again, let's head over to the next JS
documentation. And I know I could also
explain it without the documentation,
but I want to teach you that the
documentation is literally your best
friend. You want to always use it. So in
the documentation, we can s we can
search for use router. And then inside
of here, you will see the use router
hook allows you to programmatically
change routes inside client components.
Again, this page.tsx is marked with the
useclient directive. This means this is
a client component. And as you all know
uh for example we have this redirect
function. The redirect function only
works on the server side in the server
component in the server action and stuff
like that. And since this is a client
component we need to use the use router
hook. So let's go back and then above
this constant session I can create a
constant router and then this will be
equal to use router. Use router is
imported from next navigation. Please
make sure that you don't import it from
next slouter. It has to be imported from
next slashnavigation. Then I can invoke
it. And as you see this error is gone. I
want to now call this sign out function.
So right here for the lockout button I
can use an on click handler. And this
will be equal to sign out. So if I again
go back and do a hot uh refresh, I see
this lockout button right here. If I
click on lock out, I get locked out and
I again get my initial state which says
lock in. So I will again navigate to
/lockin and then I can again sign in
with GitHub and I got redirected back to
the index page. Let's also render a
toast for our sign out function. So
underneath the router I will call or I
will use uh my toast. So I will import
it from sona dosuccess and I will say
hey signed out successfully. This means
if I again go back and log out, signed
out successfully and as you see
everything worked as expected. So I can
again navigate to my login route and
then we can finally finish off this
authentication page by implementing
email signin. So, as mentioned already
at the start, when a user inputs his
email right here into the input, I want
to send an OTP, a little six-digit code
that then the user has to again type
into this website to verify that the
email belongs to this user. Also, I just
realized that I made a few spelling
mistakes. So, I will fix this quickly.
So, for the login form, I want to say
login with your GitHub or email account.
And then let's finally implement email
signin. So for that I want to go back to
the better of documentation and then we
can head over to the integrations or not
to the integrations but to the plugins.
So right here they offer a few
authentication plugins to factor
username anonymous magic link but I want
to use email OTP. So, the email OTP
plug-in allows users to sign in, verify
their email, or reset their password
using a one-time password, which is sent
to their email address. So, how can we
start using the email OTP? Well, the
first step is to add the plug-in to our
off config. So, to enable email OTP in
your app, you need to add the email OTP
plugin to your off config. So, let's
copy the import statement for the
plugin. Then I can open my off
configuration file. I will paste it on
top. And then underneath the social
providers, I want to get a plugins
property. And this will be equal to an
array. And then inside of here, I want
to initialize this email OTP. So I want
to invoke it. And then the structure.
And inside of here, we want to now send
a verification email to the user. So we
can right here say async. And then if I
click on control spacebar you will see
that I get the send verification OTP um
function then I can open this function
and inside of here for now I will just
create a comment and I will say hey
implement um I get I don't know sending
the email to the user also I can
destructure my params and I want to get
the email property itself this means the
email of the user and then I want to
also get the OTP which better off
generates. So the email is what the user
provides in our input right here. So
john@acample.com
and then the OTP is what better off
generates and what we will send to the
user itself. So to send emails to the
user we of course have to use some sort
of email service. Now there are a lot of
services on the market again good ones
bad ones very expensive ones very cheap
ones but in this video we will use
resend. So, Recent is an email service
and as they say, email for developers.
They offer both transactional and also
marketing emails. But in this video, we
will of course use transactional emails
because I mean marketing emails. We
don't even have any users right now. So,
let's scroll a bit to the bottom. So,
they have a lot of features and they are
very developer focused. This is by the
way not sponsored. You can also use any
other service. I honestly don't care to
be honest with you. And also it would be
nice if you provide your own email. So
if you have your own domain xyz.com then
please configure it in the dashboard.
But in this video I will use this demo
resent.deaf domain because I ex because
I probably think most people or a few
people won't have domains. Therefore I
will use this default one. But if you
have your own domain then please
configure it in the recent dashboard.
And I think that's already it. Let's
sign in. So I will click on sign in and
then I will continue with Google. Then
once signed in this is the dashboard. As
you see I haven't sent any emails yet.
And I want to first of all create an API
key. So right here I will click on
create API key. For the name this will
be Marshall uh LMS-Y.
Then for the permission this will be
full access. And for the domain I will
select all domains. Then I can click on
add. And right here we get our API key.
Now, please make sure that you copy it
because you can only see this key once.
So, I will copy it. I will go back and
then in our env file, I want to create a
new environment variable. So, this will
be the resend API_key.
And then this will be equal to the value
which I just copied. I can then click on
done. And honestly, we are already
finished with this dashboard. So, I can
head over to the documentation. So, I
will click on next.js quick start. And
the first step is to install the recent
SDK. Uh this is the NodeJS SDK. So it
also works in other NodeJS projects. So
I will copy it. I will go back and then
in my terminal I can paste it. Then once
installed I can again restart my def
server with pnpm rune defaf. And then
let's see what the next step is. The
next step is to already create an email
template. Let's for now skip this step.
And the third step is to send an email
using react. So right here we have to
first of all configure the recent SDK.
So I can copy this code example. Then I
will open my explorer. And then in the
lip folder I want to create a recent.ts
file. Inside of here I will create a
export constant or let me just paste
what I just copied. And as you see we
right here create a new resend instance.
Sadly resent does not import
automatically. So I will do it manually.
import I can then d the structure and
this will be done then from recent and
then where I destructure it I want to
get uppercase to recent so this is now
imported then for our env or for our
environment variable I don't want to use
this process envable
[Music]
from the env file and I want to get my
recent key as you see it's not defined
so we want to open our env file And
inside of here I want to define my
recent key. So I named the environment
variable recent API key. I can paste it
inside of here. And then this will be
equal to Z dot string. And I want to add
further validation meaning dot minimum.
And this will be a character length of
one. So a minimum character length of
one. I can then close this and then in
recent itself in the recent
configuration file I can get the recent
API key. Also I want to export this
constant. And we have now configured
resend. So what's the next step? Well,
the next step is to send an email in the
send verification uh OTP function. So I
can go back and right here they already
have a code example. So I will just copy
it. Go back and paste it inside of here.
As you see, we have to first of all
import. I will import resend from my
recent configuration file. And then we
want to send an email. So resend.s.end.
Then the first property is from and here
we define the sender itself. In this
case we are the sender. So instead of
having a company name or whatever of
ACMA this will be Marshall LMS. Uh for
the email I will leave it as onboarding
at.deaf. But if you configured your own
domain then please also add it right
here. And you can configure your domain
quite easily. Just again head over back
to the dashboard click on domains and
then you can add your domain right here.
But I will again go back. Then right
here we have the two property and I
don't want to send the email to this
domain but instead to the email which
the user provided. So I will just pass
the email right here in the array. And
it's also important that the two
property is an array with the email
added in the array. Now here's one
important thing. If you don't verify
your domain with resend, then you have
to use this onboarding email. This is
not new. You already know that. But the
problem is if you use the onboarding
email, you can only send emails to
yourself. So as an example, if I go
again to the uh recent dashboard, then
you will see that I'm signed in with
this email right here on the top uh
bottom left corner. This means if I use
this on boarding domain, I can only send
emails to this specific email. If you
have verified your domain, then you can
send emails to anyone. But in this case,
I can only send emails to myself. Then
for the subject I don't want to say
hello world. Instead I will say right
here uh Marshall LMS
and then I want to say dash verify your
email. Then right here they have a react
property and that's if you want to send
an email using a react component. But I
don't want to do that. I want to send a
blank HTM or not a blank but a standard
HTML email or an email with HTML
content. So we can use the HTML property
this will be equal to optics and inside
of here I want to get a P tag and I will
say hey your OTP uppercase is and then I
want to use this strong element and then
in this strong element I will render
this OTP. So again P tag your OTP strong
OTP finished. I can also delete this d
the structuring we won't need it. I will
just say hey await we send emails. And
in theory, this should already be
enough. So I can go back to the
dashboard. Let's see what the next step
is. So we added our configuration in the
off.ts file. And the next step is to
also add the plug-in to our off client.
So I can copy the import statement. I
can open the off client itself. So off
client, I will import it on top. And
then inside of here, I will just add the
email OTP. And also we want to get our
plugins right here. This is again equal
to an array. And then in the array, I
want to pass my email OTP client. And I
want to also invoke it. Then what's the
next step? Well, the next step is to
already send an OTP to the user's email.
So let's go back and let's again open
our login form. Inside of here, we have
to first of all keep track of the user's
email. Therefore, I can go a bit to the
top and then underneath this transition,
I will create a constant. Then I want to
get a getter and setter. So this will be
email and set email and then this will
be equal to use state. Use state is
imported from react and the default
state the initial state will be an empty
string. Then I can scroll a bit to the
bottom and right here for my input I
want to add a value and an onchange
handler. So for the value this will be
equal to my email and then we can also
get an onchange handler. Then uh this
will be an inline callback function as a
param I want to get the event and then
we can call or we can use our setter set
email and as an argument I want to
provide the value. So e.target dot
value.
Then for the input I will also add a
required property. Is there anything
else? Uh type is already email.
Everything is added. I think this is it.
And I want to now create an async
function to sign in with email. So I
will go underneath this async function
sign in with GitHub and I will create a
new one. So async signin with email. I
can then again open this function and
inside of here I want to first of all
again start a transition. So this means
I want to create a new transition. I can
copy this GitHub pending transition.
Then for the getter, this will be the
email transition. And for the setter,
this will be the start email transition.
Also, this does not have to be an async
function. This can just be a standard
function sign in with email. And then
inside of here, I can call my start
email transition function. I want to
then invoke it. And inside of here, I
want to create a standard arrow
function. This means async. And then I
can just open it inside of here. And
then in this function start email
transition we can now finally
authenticate the user. So we can say
await of client of client is already
imported dot email OTP dot send
verification OTP I can invoke it the
structured and inside of here we have to
provide a few properties. First of all
the email itself we get our email or we
store our email in the state. So use
state which means I can just pass my
email right here. The next property is
the type and you get two or you get
three properties email verification
forget password and sign in. In this
case we want to sign in and then we also
get our fetch options and I want to
listen for two events. The onsuccess
event and the on event. So let's first
of all get the on success event. This
will be a standard error function. And
if it was successful I want to again
return a toast dosuccess. And for the
message I will say email sent. Then we
want to also redirect the user. So we
can say router.push. And as you see we
currently don't have access to the
router. This means I can scroll again to
the top. And then above this transition
I can create a constant router. And this
will be equal to use router. Use router
is imported from next/navigation.
Please don't import it from next/
routouter. And then again if I scroll to
the bottom I can say router.push
I want to invoke it. And then as an
argument I want to pass uh optics
because I want to pass a dynamic value.
And then as an argument itself I will
say /verify
request.
Later on we will also pass the email of
the user as a param but for now let's
leave it as is. Then I want to also
listen for the on error event. Again
this will be an error function. And
inside of here I want to return a toast
error. And for the message I will say
hey error sending email. So this in
theory should already be finished. So I
can copy the name sign in with email.
And then I can scroll a bit to the
bottom. Right here we have this button
continue with email. And if this is and
for the button I want to add an onclick
handler. And if the user clicks on the
button I want to call the signin with
email function. Also, we get uh access
to the email pending boolean. This means
we can set the uh button to disabled if
email pending is true. So, disabled will
be equal to email pending. As you see, I
don't get an email pending. So, I
probably misspelled something. And yes,
this shouldn't be email transition, but
instead email pending. If I save this
and again go back, you will see that
this error will go away. Also instead of
just rendering uh continue with email, I
want to render the content dynamically.
This means if email pending is true, I
want to render loading dot dot dot. If
email pending is not true, I want to
render continue with email. So I will
just copy this text and then I want to
create a turnary. If email pending is
true, I can use a question mark. Then I
want to return these empty tags. And
inside of here, I want to get a loader
to icon imported from Lucid React. Let's
provide a class name and this will be
size four. Again size four is the short
form of width four and height four and
this means about 16 pixels uh width and
height. Then we want to also say animate
spin and this means this loader will
spin. And then underneath the loader I
want to render a span and I want to say
loading dot dot dot. If email pending is
not true then we can use the colon and I
want to render what I just copied. This
means continue with email. Also I want
to render an icon. So I will again use
empty tags. Then I want to get the send
icon from lucid react. I want to also
add a class name and this will be size
4. And then underneath the icon I can
paste a span or I can pass a span
element and paste continue with email
inside of here. And I guess let's test
it out. And again please remember since
I use the onboarding email I have to
provide the email with which I signed up
to resend itself. If your domain is
verified then you can pass right here
any email. But if you use the onboarding
email then you have to send an email to
yourself. So I will add my email right
here. And then if I click on continue
with email, we have this nice pending
state and in theory I should get
redirected to verify request. And that's
exactly what happened. If I open my
Gmail client, I should also get an
email. And that's exactly what happened.
If I zoom in a bit, it says your OTP is
this number right here. But again, if I
go back to my web application, there's
no way to add this uh digit or this OTP
right here because currently we don't
have a verify request route. This means
we can go back again. Let's open the
explorer and then in the app folder in
the all folder I want to create a new
route. Who would have thought? So I will
create a new folder verify- request and
then in the folder I want to create a
new file page.tsx. tsx. Since this is
the route, I will create an export
default function and I will call it
verify request.
I want to create a return statement.
Inside of here, I want to start with the
cart component. The cart is imported
from the components. And then in the
cart, I want to render a cart header. In
the cart header, I want to render a card
title. And in the cart title, I want to
say uh please check your email. Then
underneath the card title, I want to
render a card description. And then for
the card description, I want to say we
have sent a or a verification email a
code to your email address dot please
open the email and paste the code below.
So this is finished, which means if I go
back and do a hard refresh, we should
see this card right here. And yes, it
says, "Please check your email." And
then we have this nice little text, this
nice little description. Then we can go
back and for the cart, I want to also
add a class name. And then this will be
width of full and MX auto. So if I again
go back, nothing changes. Then I want to
also style my header a bit because I
want to center this text. So for the
cart header, I can give it a class name
and this will be text center to center
everything in the middle. Also the card
title should be a bit bigger. So I can
add a class name and this will be text
XL. So the font size will be bigger.
Then underneath the card header I want
to start by rendering my card content.
So let's go underneath the cart header
and I want to get the card content
component. Inside of here I can first of
all render a div. And then in this div I
want to render an input OTP component.
So I will head over to the shad CN
website and inside of here you can
search for input OTP. This component is
an accessible one-time password
component with copy paste functionality.
So this is already installed which means
I can go back and inside of here we want
to first of all get the input OTP
component from the components. Then in
the input OTP I want to get the input
group or the input OTP group. Then I can
open it and in the input OTP group I
want to render the input OTP slot. This
is imported from the components and this
is self-closing. This input OTP requires
one key property which is the index and
the index defines the position of the
input OTP slot. So JavaScript is zero
indexed which means we start with zero 0
1 2 3 4 and then five. So I can go back
and for the index again this will be
zero. Then I can copy paste this input
OTP slot two more times. The second uh
index will be one and then the third
index will be two. Then we can again
copy this input OTP group. Paste it down
below and this index will be three. This
one will be four and then this one will
be five. So if I again go back and do a
hard refresh you will see that this is
our input OTP. It looks quite nice.
Nevertheless, we still get an error for
our input OTP. That's because we have to
provide a few key properties. First of
all, the maximum length. The maximum
length will be six. We can only pass six
digits. Then we want to also add a class
name. This will be gap 2. Then I want to
also add a value and onchange handler.
This means we want to store the value in
state. So I will scroll to the top and
then above the return statement I will
create a constant again we want to
create a getter and setter. So this will
be OTP and set OTP and this will be
equal to use state. Use state is
imported from react and the initial
state will be an empty string. So again
if I go back to the input OTP for the
value this will be equal to our OTP the
getter and then for the onchange I want
to create an inline call back function
and then as a param I want to get the
value itself and then we can call our
set OTP uh getter or setter I'm sorry
and then as an argument I want to
provide the value which we get from the
input OTP. So in theory we now uh
configured our input OTP which means if
I go back and do a hard refresh we get
an error. Nice. So you're importing a
component that needs use state. That's
because so right here we use this use
state hook. And as you all know if we
want interactivity then we have to mark
the file the component whatever with the
use client directive. So use client. And
if I go back then you will see the input
OTP right here. The only problem is it's
not uh centered right now. So I will go
back again and then for the stiff which
uh wraps my input OTP I will give it a
class name and this will be flex flex of
column items which will be center and
space Y2.
As you see this is now centered and it
already looks way better. Underneath the
input OTP I want to render a little
description text. So I will go back and
then underneath the input OTP but still
in the diff I will render a P tag and I
will say enter the six uh dash digit
code sent to your email. As you see yeah
it looks good but it's too big and it
should also be darker. So I can add a
class name and this will be text SM and
text muted foreground. Again this is a
CSS vable provided by SHA CN UI. So if I
go back, yeah, this looks way better.
You can make it even smaller if you want
to, but honestly, I think this is fine
enough. And then underneath the input
OTP, I want to render a button. So I
will go back underneath the P tag and
underneath the div, but still in the
cart content, I want to render a button
component imported from the components.
And inside of here, I will just say uh
verify request. Then for the button, I
want to also add a class name. And this
will be width or full. And this is our
button. But as you see, yeah, it looks
nice, but we don't have any spacing. I
need some gap. So, we can go back. How
is this route structured? How is the UI
structured? Well, we have our cart
content. And in the cart content, we
have two sections, you could say. First
of all, the OTP and then the button,
which means we can pass a class name for
the card content, which will be spaced
Y6. It already looks way better. Then
let's finish off our button and also
this shouldn't be verify request but
instead verify account. And now I want
to also implement the functionality so
that the user can actually verify uh
their account. So I will go to the top
and then underneath this constant OTP I
will create a new function which I will
name verify OTP and then I can just open
it. Inside of here I want to again start
a transition. So underneath my state I
can create a constant again for the
getter this will be email pending and
then I want to also create a start
transition and then this will be equal
to use transition. I can import it from
react and then inside of here I can
again call or use my start transition. I
want to invoke it and as an argument I
want to create a standard async arrow
function. I can open it and then inside
of here we can use our off client to
verify the OTP. So I will say await of
client which is imported from the lip
folder dot sign in. And again we have
three methods email OTP and social. In
this case we want to use email OTP. Then
I can invoke it and structure it inside
of here. We want to first of all provide
our email. But now here's the question.
Where will we get our email from? I mean
right here. I don't get my email. If I
go back in the URL, I don't store my
email. How can I sign in or how can I
verify the request if I don't have the
email? So, here's the thing. We want to
store the email in the URL itself. This
means I can go back and open the lock in
form component itself. Then I want to
scroll a bit to the top. And here we uh
redirect the user to the verify request
route. And I want pend a query
parameter. And this query parameter will
be the email. So we can add right here a
question mark. And then I want to add an
email. And this will be equal to dynamic
value which will be the email itself.
This means if I again go back and I want
to again sign in. So I will navigate to
/loin and I will again paste my email
inside of here. And if I click on
continue with email, I will get
redirected in my domain or in my URL.
You will now see something interesting.
First of all, the path itself, verify
request. And then we have this query
parameter email which is equal to the
email which I used to sign in. This
means I can go back to my email client.
And as you see, I get a new message. And
my new OTP is this one. So I can just
copy it and paste it inside of here. But
this won't help us right now because we
have to configure or finish off our
function. So I want to get my email from
the URL. So I want to get my params uh
my query param. So underneath this email
pending I can create a constant params
and this will be equal to use search
params and then I can invoke it. Use
search params is imported from
next/navigation
and it allows us or it gives us access
to the query or search parameters and
then underneath the params I can create
a constant email and then this will be
equal to params.get get because I want
to get a param and not set a param we
can then invoke it and as an argument I
have to provide the name itself and
again what is the name well if I go
right here to the URL you will see that
it's email so I can just paste email as
an argument also I will mark this as
string and then I can pass this new
email uh for my email itself so the next
property is the OTP and our OTP is
stored in state so OTP will be equal to
OTP and then I want to again use my
fetch options because I want to listen
for two events the onsuccess event and
the onour event. So this will be equal
to an object inside of here I will get
the onsuccess event this is a standard
error function and then I want to return
a toast dosuccess for the message I will
say email verified and then I want to
also redirect the user which means we
have to again use the use router hook.
So at the top I can create a constant
router and this will be equal to use
router which is imported for
next/navigation.
Then again if I scroll to the bottom I
can say or a bit to the bottom I can say
right here router.push and I want to
redirect the user to the index page.
Then I want to also listen for the onour
event. This is also a standard error
function. And inside of here I want to
return a toast. And I want to say our
verifying email or OTP email OTP
email/OOTTP.
Yeah, this is a diplomatic answer. So
this looks great and we can now use this
verify OTP function uh in our button or
in other words, our button should now
call this function which we just
created. So we can add an on click
handler. This will be equal to verify
OTP. And then I want to also add a
disabled state. And this OTP or this
button should be disabled if we are
submitting. So we can add our email
pending state. If this is true, then
this button will be disabled. But I want
to also disable this button if we
haven't added all of the digits. So as
an example, if the user only fills out
three digits, then this button should be
disabled. So if I again scroll to the
top, we can create a new constant called
is OTP completed. And then here I want
to check that the OTP length is equal to
six. So we can say OTP.length should be
equal to six. So I can now use OTP
completed. This is a boolean. I can
scroll to the bottom and then for the
disabled state I will say this will be
disabled if email pending is true or so
I can use two vertical lines if is
completed is not true and for that we
have to also add this question mark at
the start because we don't want to uh
disable this button if OTP is completed
we want to disable it if is OTP is not
completed so if I again go back and do a
hard refresh you will see that this
button is disabled If I add six digits,
then this button will be again available
because we added all of the digits. So I
think it's time to test out everything
again. I think our OTP won't work
because there's like a 5minut time
window. So I will again log in. So I
will head over to /loin and then inside
of here I will again paste my email
and then I will click on continue with
email and then as you see email sent I
got redirected to the verify request
page and if I open Gmail I also got a
new email. This is my OTP code. I will
copy it and paste it right here. If I
click on verify account I should get a
pending state. I did not get one. That's
because I haven't implemented one. And
we also get a toast which says email
verified. So as you saw right now I
haven't implemented uh any pending
states. That's not quite what I want. So
instead of just rendering verify email,
we can use our email pending boolean. So
if email pending is true, we can add a
question mark. And for now I want to
return empty tags. And inside of here I
want to again render this loader to icon
which is imported from Lucid React. I
want to give it a class name which will
be size 4 and then also animate spin.
Underneath the loader icon I want to
render a span element and I will say
loading dot dot dot and if email pending
is not true then we can render verify
account again. So if I save this and
again go back I will have to again first
of all log out then I can go to /lo or
navigate to /lo then I will again add my
email. If I click on continue with
email, we have this nice pending state.
I got redirected. I have this nice
toast. And then if I again go back to my
email client, I should get a new email.
Let's see. Yes, I got a new one. I can
just copy the code, paste it inside of
here. I get this nice pending state. My
email is verified and I have a valid
session. Let's maybe also quickly go
into the recent dashboard. And if you go
for example to your metrics, uh is this
the correct one? Yes, metrics, you will
see that we delivered four emails
successfully. And if we go to the logs,
you will see them right here. Four
emails with all of the timestamps right
here. So, we are finally finished with
authentication. Users can sign in with
email with GitHub. We sent OTPs. The
login form looks beautiful. It works
great. Everything works exactly as
expected or as I wanted it to. But
here's the thing. Let's look at our
application from a security standpoint.
So right here next to me I have my
friend John. I don't really have a
friend John, but let's just imagine that
right here my friend John sits next to
me and John is a malicious user and he
wants to attack your application and
this login form gives John quite a big
surface for attacking if this makes
sense. So what I mean by that is for
example users right here can sign in
with email. So John for example will see
this and say hey how about I just spam
this application with fake emails some
gibberish atj gibberish.com and if I
click on continue with email it will
work because I don't validate the emails
and also I don't have weight limits set
up. So John could just uh create some
sort of bot which spams our application
with hundreds of requests per minute.
And again, John could also create a bot.
I don't want to allow bots to sign up.
Only real users should be able to sign
up to my application. This means we want
to set up rate limits. A user a real
user will probably only as a maximum
make five requests per minute. This
means everything which is bigger than
that should be blocked. Also I want to
protect this login form and also later
on in general my application against
bots. And then also I want to validate
this email. Currently any email can be
passed right here. But only real emails
should be able to sign up if this makes
sense or users with real emails like
john@gmail.com. This is a real email.
Johnas asdfasdf.com
is not a real email. So in this video we
will set up arc chat. Arcjet is the
sponsor of this video and also a tool
which I have been using in my own
personal web applications but we will
come to that in a second. So as they say
security doesn't have to be a pain.
ARJet allows you to implement bot
detection, rate limiting, email
validation, attack protection, data
reduction, and at the end of the day,
it's a developer first approach to
security. So before we go through the
landing page, let's quickly look at my
personal web application. So this is
marshallcode.com
and if you go to the navbar, you will
find this link, ultimate next.js course.
here. Users, visitors can sign up to the
weight list to get notified once it's
released. And you know what? I
implemented arjhat right here. So if I
add my email right here and then click
on uh reserve my spot, I will get an
error. You have already been added to
the weight list. If I spam my
application, so I will click this button
multiple times as you see right here. I
will get a different error and it says
it seems like you are a bot. If this was
an error, please try again or contact
support. So right here I set up rate
limits with arcjet. So arcjet sees the
weight limit has been hit. This means
probably we want to block the request
and that's why arjet blocks the request
and the user in this case I myself am
not able to reserve my spot and that's
also exactly what we want to do for our
application. So let's quickly go through
the landing page and let's see what ark
chat offers. So here they uh list all of
their primitives, all of their defense
primitives. First of all, arcjet shield
W AF which stands for web application
firewall. So this archet shield protects
your application against the most common
attacks including the OASP top 10. If
you never heard about the OWOSP top 10,
then in short, the OASP top 10 is a
standard awareness document for
developers and web application security.
It represents a broad consensus about
the most critical security risks. And
for example, here you see the evolution
of security risks. So in 2017, the
biggest security risk was injection. In
2021, the biggest security risk was
broken access control. And against what
does a arcjet shield specifically
protect you against? Well, it protects
you against common categories such as
SQL injection, cross-ite scripting,
local file inclusion, PHP code
injection, HTTP proxy, shellshock, and
much more. Then what else do they offer?
They also offer weight limiting. This is
what I have set up for my own web
application. So define rules which limit
the number of requests a client can make
over a period of time. And the nice
thing is these weight limits can also be
set dynamically. So if a user has a
valid session, we can say this user can
create 10 requests per minute. If the
user does not have a valid session, then
a user can only create uh five requests
per minute or something like that. This
is very very powerful. Then archet also
offers bot detection. This means we can
detect and manage traffic by automated
clients and bots. So for example, for
our sign up form, I don't want to allow
bots to uh sign up right here or sign
in. Then Arkjet also offers email
validation. So we can validate and
verify email addresses to reduce spam
and target fraudulent accounts. We will
also set up email validation later on.
And then they also offer protect a
signup form. And this is like a
consolidation of email validation, bot
protection and weight limiting. So you
can protect your signup form from abuse
by combining rate limiting, bot
detection and email validation. And this
is exactly what we will do because what
is this right here? Well, this is a
signup form. And they have already a
rule, a primitive which exactly targets
what we need. And then they also offer
PII detection. What's that? Well, you
can protect against clients sending
personal information such as credit card
numbers or email addresses that you do
not wish to handle. So, let's imagine
the following. You have some sort of um
contact us form and you don't want to
allow a user to send you private info
like credit card data. You don't want to
store it because for example, you maybe
have some sort of company internal
policies or data retention or whatever.
I'm not sure what rules you have, but
you don't want to store or you don't
want to handle this private data. Using
PII detection, you can filter it out and
then block it. We won't implement PII
detection in this video because a user
can't really add any fake or sensitive
data in our application. Nevertheless,
this is a very very powerful primitive.
And you know what? Before we implement
Arkjet, I want to look at the
architecture of Arkjet because this is a
huge differentiator to its competitors
because it allows you to do things that
the competitors don't. So, Arcjet has
been architected around a few key
principles. First of all, proper
security protection needs the full
context of the application, which is why
security rules and protections should be
located alongside the code they are
protecting. Most security solutions live
in some sort of cloud and they don't
live in your code. Arcjet directly lives
in your code and you define arcjet in
your code which means it also gets the
full context of your code. Also security
rules should be easy to test. You should
be able to run them in development as
well as in production and arcjet should
not interfere with the rest of the
application. It should be easy to
install, must not add significant
latency to requests, and it also does
not add any latency or very minimal
latency because it's built on top of
Rust and it should not require changes
to the application's architecture. So
quickly uh regarding performance, ArcJet
is super fast. It's built on top of
Rust. It it makes its decision in
milliseconds. So how does exactly Arkjet
analyze your request? Well, right here
they have an example. In this example
flow, a client makes an HTTP request to
your application. Now, our application
or our platform will apply standard DOS
protection through our network firewall.
So if you for example later on and we
will also do that if we later on deploy
our application to Versel we will
automatically already have a network
firewall configured and this network
firewall will already apply standard DOS
protection and most platforms provide
DOS uh protection transparently and out
of the box for no extra cost. Then our
server receives the request and then the
arcjet SDK is configured as middleware.
Now this is an example. We won't
configure Arcjet right now in our
middleware. Maybe later on, but for now
it will live in our route handler. So it
intercepts the request before it reaches
your application code. Arjet analyzes
the request locally based on the rules
you configured. For example, weight
limiting or bot detection and then it
decides to allow the request or deny it.
Arcjet returns the result and your
application code continues to execute as
normally. You can inspect the decision
to understand why arjet came to that
conclusion. An asynchronous report is
made to the arcjet API for post request
analysis. So right here they have a
little diagram. So here we have a
client. Let's say I'm the client and I
make a request to Marshall LMS. The
client makes a request. The network
firewall. So for example the one which
provides will already analyze the
request. It applies very very standard
DOS protection. If this passes, our
request hits our server. Our server will
now get a request and arcjet will
evaluate the request. It will check is
the user a bot. Uh is the user still in
the weight limit which we have defined.
Is the or has the user provided a real
email address. It will validate
everything and then it will come to a
decision. This decision will either be
allow or deny. If the decision is
allowed, then the request hits our
application, our code. If the decision
is denied, then we will deny the request
and we won't even continue analyzing
anything. So that's how arcjet works and
it's super super powerful. And let's
also quickly look at this one more
section and then we will finally
implement arcad. So traditional CDN
security services are typically
implemented as a reverse proxy in front
of your application. The security
service is a separate entity from your
application. Rules can't be adjusted
dynamically because it does not have
access to the full context of the
request and it can't be tested locally.
And this is exactly where archet comes
into play. Arcjet is not a reverse
proxy. No, it lives in your code. It
gets the full context of your code which
also means it has way or it creates way
better decisions. It has way less false
positives and false negatives. So since
we now know what arcjet is, I think we
can get started by implementing arcjet.
Nevertheless, I would recommend you to
read through this architecture page.
It's very in-depth and it's also super
helpful to understand arcjet even
better. But for now, let's go to the get
started guide. And the first step is to
create a next.js project. We already did
that. And the next step is to install
Arkjet. So I will copy this installation
command and we will install the arcjet
SDK and arcjet inspect. What is arcjet
inspect? Well in the sidebar if you
click on archet inspect it will say the
arcjet decision inspection library
provides a set of utilities to more
easily interact with the decision
returned from the arcjet SDK. Then let's
continue with the get started guide.
What's the next step? We install we did
not install anything. Uh let's head over
to our application. I will open my
terminal. I will stop the dev server and
I will paste the installation command
right here into our terminal. The next
step is to then set our key. So I will
copy this environment vable. I will go
back and then I will paste it into my
env file. And then the next step is to
get our key. So please head over to my
YouTube description and click on the
first link. This will show arcad that
you came for my video and this would
help me to create more of these super
cool videos. So please, it would mean a
lot to me. But now let's head over first
of all again to the Arcjet landing page
and then I will sign in. I will sign in
with Google. And as you see I'm in the
dashboard and I want to first of all
create a new site. A new site is like a
new project. So I will click on new
site. We want to give it a name. This
will be Marshall LMS YouTube. And then I
can create this new site. As you see we
got redirected into this project. And
here we already have the arcad key. I
can just click on it. This will copy the
key and then I will paste it for the
environment variable. So for the arcjet
key itself. Then we can again close the
CNV file. And then I want to head over
back to the documentation. And then
what's the next step? Well, the next
step is to add all of the rules, all of
the primitives. But we don't we won't
follow this guide. Instead, let's go to
the sidebar. Let's scroll a bit to the
bottom. And here you will find the SDK
reference section. Let's click on it.
And I want to click on next.js. Here it
will again give you a little quick start
guide. But if I scroll a bit to the
bottom, you will find the single
instance section. So we arcjet recommend
creating a single instance of the arcjet
object and reusing it throughout your
application. This is because the SDK
caches decisions and configuration to
improve performance. The pattern we use
is to create a utility file that exports
the arcjet object and then we import it
wherever we need to. So let's again head
over back to our application. I will
open the explorer. I want to go into the
lip folder and I want to create a new
arcad.ts file and again this will be the
configuration file for arcjet. Inside of
here we can first of all create an
import statement and I want you also the
structured this will be imported from at
archet / next and then where I
structured I want to get a few rules a
few primitives I want to get the detect
bot rule I want to get the fixed window
then also protect signup uh sensitive
info we won't use it but let's still uh
import it then I want to also get shield
and also the sliding window algorithm
and then Uh underneath this import we
want to reexport these rules. Uh so
let's create an export. I will open an
object and I want to reexport my detect
bot then fixed window protect signup and
then sensitive info shield and also
sliding window. So now I just reexport
everything to simplify the imports later
on. And then as the next step I want to
create a base arc chat instance which we
will reuse throughout our application
because again it will then cache
everything. So let's create an export
default this will be called arcjet and
then I want to also import arcjet. So
arcjet is imported from at archet / next
and then I can invoke it and the
structure inside of here I have to
provide a few key properties. First of
all the key the secret this will be
equal to our env. So we want to import
our env variable from the env file
arcjet key. As you see I don't get it.
So I want to open my env.ts file and I
want to add this environment variable
into my server object. So I will open
the standard env file. I will copy the
name arcjet key and then I can paste it
right here and it will be equal to
z.string string minimum one because I
want to have a minimum character length
of one. And then for our key, I can now
get the arcjet key as you see. And then
as a next property, I want to add
characteristics and this will be equal
to an array. And then in the array, I
will pass a string and I will just say
fingerprint. You can also call it some
other name. Uh it does not matter but I
will say fingerprint. But now you might
ask me, hey Jan, what is this
characteristics property? What is this
array fingerprint? What does this
characteristics thing do? Well, here's
the thing. Arcjet has to somehow track
and identify the requests and as a
default, it uses the IP address. The
thing is an IP address is easily
spoofable. Therefore, in most cases, you
don't really want to use an IP. Instead,
you want to use something which is
identifiable. As an example, the user
ID. So, if I don't add this
characteristics property, everything
will still work. and it will identify
and track the request using the user's
IP. But if I add the characteristics
property right here, I can define my own
characteristics like for example the
user ID. If I don't pass anything again,
it will use the user's IP as a default.
But if I then later on want to use
something to track the request, I can
then add for example a user ID. And then
the next property is rules. And this is
interesting because this is an array and
inside of here I can define base rules.
This means whenever I use this archet
instance all of the rules which are
defined in this rules array will also
run as a default. This means if I leave
this rules array empty then there will
be nothing run as a default. If I for
example add shield as an example then
this shield will run every time we use
archet. So inside of here we can create
a comment. Um define base rules here can
also be empty if you don't want to have
any base rules. So if we think through
our application what would uh what would
make sense to have as a base rule rate
limiting? Not really because every you
could say instance or every feature of
our application will have a different
rate limit. For example, our sign-in
form could have a weight limit of five,
but then some sort of let's say for now
a course creation route could have a
weight limit of 10. Therefore, it does
not really make sense to add a base rate
limit. So, what could make sense? Well,
for example, shield. So, in the rules
array, I will uh get shield. I want to
invoke it the structure and inside of
here, I have to provide one key property
and that's the mode. And if I click on
control spacebar, I get two options
either dry one or live. Dry one will
only console lock the decision. Live
will also block the request. So it makes
a lot of sense to set the mode to dry
one in development. But since I want to
really test out everything, I will set
it to live. And now we already
implemented shield. And again, what is
shield? Well, if you hover over it, you
will find nice comments. And right here
it says the ArcJet shield analyzes every
request to your application to detect
suspicious activity. Once a certain
suspicion threshold is reached,
subsequent requests from that client are
blocked for a period of time. And again,
this is a base rule which means it will
run everywhere where we use the arcjet
instance. So I can close this arc file.
We don't need it anymore. And we want to
combine or connect uh better off to
arcad because we want to use the sign up
form protection. We want to implement
weight limiting. We want to implement
bot detection and email validation. So
where would it make sense to track this
request to analyze it? Well, our route
handler as mentioned all of the better
off requests are funneled through this
route handler. This route handler allows
the user to sign in, sign out, create
ors and stuff like that. This means we
want you also get a request right here,
analyze it with arcjet and then either
allow it or deny it. So if you go to the
arcjet documentation and scroll a bit to
the bottom, then you will find this
section called better off. So
integrations better off. And here they
say arcjet can protect your better off
routes from brute force attacks, signup
spam and other abuse. You can also use
the authenticated user ID to implement
user specific rate limits because as
mentioned again arjet can be used to
create dynamic rate limits. If a user is
signed up we can give the user a rate
limit of 10. If we don't have a valid
user session we will give the user a
rate limit of four as an example. And
right here they already have an example
application. So let's open it. And also
right here they have a nice little
section and they say we recommend
integrating arcjet in the off route
handler rather than in a better off hook
because hooks do not provide sufficient
request context in server only
environments. So we will use the route
handler to analyze the request because
it gives us all of the info. This
request gives us everything and that's
what arcjet needs. It needs the full
context of the request. So let's again
go back to this GitHub repo and we want
to go into the app directory into this
API folder and then into this route.ts.
And here we already have a demo code
example. And you know what I will just
copy this file and paste it right here
for my route.ts. Don't worry I will
explain everything. As you see we have
two errors. So first of all we import
all from the wrong location. So I can
delete it. And also we want to import IP
from archet IP. But this package does
not exist. So here's the thing. As
mentioned, if I again open my arcjet
base instance, we added characteristics.
We can add our own custom
characteristics, but as a default, it
will use the user's IP. Next.js does not
give you access to the user's IP
natively. This means we have to use a
separate function. And thankfully, Arjet
created the Archet IP detection library
and it provides a utility to find the
public IP of a request. So we want to
install it. I can scroll to the bottom.
I will copy the installation command and
then paste it into my terminal.
And also they say the IP should not be
trusted as it can be spoofed in most
cases, especially when loaded via the
headers object. We apply additional
platform guards. If a platform is
supplied in the options argument, then
we can continue. So right here they set
up an arc chat instance. But as you all
know, we already created our own base
instance. This means I can just delete
this constant AJ equals to arjet. We
don't need it. Then what else do we have
right here? Well, we create a few
objects. First of all, the email
options. So as mentioned, if we again
head over back to the documentation, I
want to set up this rule which is called
signup form protection. And this signup
form protection is a combination of rate
limiting, bot protection, and email
validation. This means I want to also
create these objects. First of all,
email options. The mode will be set to
live. This means we will block all
requests. And then we can also add a
block property. And this is an array.
And inside of here, we can define the
types of emails which we want to block.
So for example, I want to block
disposable emails, invalid emails, and
emails which don't have any valid MX
records. Then we want to also use bots.
So we create a constant bot options
object. The mode is set to live. I want
to block requests. And then we also have
an allow property which is an array.
Inside of here I could say I want to
allow search engines for example to make
a request or I want to allow for example
open AI to make a request the open AI
crawler or open host or whatever. So we
can define right here bots which are uh
allowed to interact with our signup
form. But I don't want to allow any bots
to interact with our signup form.
Therefore, this allow property will just
be an empty array. No bots will be
allowed to submit the form. Then we also
have this weight limit options object.
And again, the mode is set to life. And
then we have an interval and a maximum
property. And as you see, this is a
sliding window weight limit option. What
does this mean? Well, there are three
key algorithms which you can use for
weight limiting. So if you go back to
the documentation and go to the sidebar,
you can click on algorithms. And right
here they say arcat weight limiting
allows you to define rules which limit
the number of requests a client can make
over a period of time. It supports three
different weight limit algorithms. Fixed
window, sliding window, and token
bucket. Currently we set up sliding
window. So let's go through them
quickly. Let's start with the fixed
window. This is the simplest algorithm.
It tracks the number of requests made by
a client over a fixed time window. As an
example, 60 seconds. If the client
exceeds the limit, all requests are
blocked until the window expires. So, if
we have a 1 minute time window and I
make 50 requests and also the maximum
limit is 50 requests. Then I will be
blocked for this 1 minute. After this 1
minute passes, I can again create 50 or
100 or whatever the limit is uh
requests. Then we also have the sliding
window and that's what we implemented.
This algorithm tracks the number of
requests uh made by a client over a
sliding window so that the window moves
with time. So this is a very interesting
algorithm and it's also a more advanced
algorithm. It's a bit more complicated.
So what's the problem with a with the
fixed window algorithm? So let's say you
allow 100 requests per minute. With the
fixed window algorithm, a user could
send 100 requests at 120059
and then another 100 at 1201. That means
a user can send 200 requests in 1
second. And right here, I meant 59
seconds. A sliding window is the better
solution because the sliding window
algorithm smooths this out by tracking
request timestamps more precisely,
sliding across time rather than jumping
in fixed chunks. So, how does it work?
Well, imagine you want to allow 100
requests per 60 seconds. For each user,
IP or token, whatever, whatever you use
for your characteristics, you store a
list of timestamps for their recent
requests. On each new request, you
remove all timestamps older than 60
seconds from the list. If the remaining
list has fewer than 100 entries, allow
the request. Otherwise, reject or delay
it. I know this sounds super confusing
and at first it's also I will be honest
with you uh quite confusing. So let's
look at this uh diagram. So as you see
the time is 12:00 and a user sends a
request one request and this is allowed
and right here we have a limit of 100 in
a 1 minute window. Then after 10 seconds
the user sends 50 more requests. So in
total we now send 51 requests. Then at
uh 59 seconds, so 59 seconds have now
passed, a user sends 49 requests, which
means we now hit the limit of uh 100
requests. Then at 12:01 and 1 second,
one request is now older than 60
seconds. So the list now has 99 entries
because after 1 minute, I deleted this
entry and this entry only had one
request, which means we can also now
make another request. And then let's say
1 second after that a user tries to
again make a request. This is now
denied. We will only be allowed to
create again a request at 1201 and 10
seconds because then we will again free
up 50 requests. So right here they say
this algorithm is useful to avoid the
stampage problem because a user can't
really now spam your application. We
have a sliding window. And then there's
also the token bucket algorithm. And
this is honestly my favorite algorithm.
This algorithm is based on a bucket
filled with a specific number of tokens.
Each request withdraws a token from the
bucket and the bucket is refilled at a
fixed rate. Once the bucket is empty,
the client is blocked until the bucket
refills. So this means as an example
right here, we have a capacity of 100.
So our bucket can have a maximum of 100
tokens. Every 60 seconds we will refill
this bucket with 10 tokens and then
after some time our capacity will be hit
100 which means we won't create any new
tokens. If we then again use up a bit of
our already uh created tokens then we
will again refill them every uh 60
seconds. So 10 tokens per interval. It's
a very interesting algorithm but I know
most people will probably use the fixed
window or the sliding window. But now
let's again continue. So we implemented
already the sliding window. The mode is
set to live and a user can make five
submissions in a twominut sliding
window. Then we also right here create
our signup options object which means we
combine our email rule, our bots rule
and our rate limit rule. And then the
next step is to create a protect
function as they did right here. And
then inside of here they first of all
fetch the user session. So we can import
off from our lip from our off file. Uh
so from the lip folder and here we have
an if statement. So if the user is
locked in we will use their ID as the
identifier. This allows limits to be
applied across all devices and sessions.
Otherwise we will fall back to the
user's IP. So if we have a valid user
session then we will use the user ID as
a characteristic. If there's no user, if
we don't have a valid user session, then
we will just use the IP using the IP
package which we just installed. And
then we have an if statement. And this
checks if the request is a signup. If
so, then we will use the protect signup
rule. And the signup rule is a
combination of email validation, bot
protection, and weight limiting. Then we
get our body. Then as a next step, we
check that we also get an email. If so,
we want to then use our protect signup
rule. So, let's import arcjet from our
lip folder. So, we want to get our base
instance. Then we can use this with rule
method and we want to use protect
signup. As you see, we get one error for
the user ID and that's because we want
to get our fingerprint and this will be
equal to the user ID. Then if this is
not true, this means if we don't get an
email, then we want to also validate the
request, but we don't want to use the
protect signup method because there's no
email to validate. This means we will
now chain two rules. First of all, the
detect bot rule and then also the
sliding window algorithm rule. So let's
again import arcad from our lip folder
or it's already imported. And then right
here for our user ID, I want to get my
fingerprint and this will be equal to
the user ID. And then we also have an
else statement and this is for all other
of requests. Let's again get arcjet. We
want to use the with rule method and we
will use the detect bot rule also. Again
I want to get my fingerprint and this
will be equal to the user ID. And that's
already it. Then the next step is to
wrap the post handler with the arcjet
protections. So we get our decision. So
we call this protect function. This gen
uh generates a decision. we console lock
the decision and then we create an if
statement. If the decision is denied
then we can check what the reason was.
So if it was weight limit then we just
return a new error. If the decision was
an invalid email then we return a
message. If it's invalid then we return
this error message. If it's disposable
we return this error message. If there
are no MX records then we return this
error message. And if nothing works then
we just return this default error
message. And that's it. So to summarize
it, we have a protect function. In the
protect function, we implemented arcjet.
And then this protect function is called
in our post request. This gets us a
decision. And then we check if the
decision is denied. If so, we throw a
new error. If the decision is allowed,
then we just return a new response or in
other words, we let off or better off
handle the request and authenticate the
user. So this in theory should work. So
I will go back do a hard refresh and I
will hope for the best. So I will sign
in with GitHub. We have a pending state
du signed in redirecting. Okay. Okay.
Okay. We got redirected. So in theory
everything worked. And then if we open
our terminal you will also see a console
lock right here. And the arcjet decision
was allow. This means everything worked
as expected. Let's also quickly head
over to the arcjet dashboard. And in the
arcad dashboard you will see this is our
request with the time the host the path
and the reason is allow. So if I go
right here conclusion allow reason there
is no reason everything was allowed and
that's great. You can also for example
go to the analytics and again no denies
no errors only requests which got
allowed very cool. So since we are
finally finished with authentication and
also with arcjet I want to continue with
a few other interesting things. So
here's a little road map of what we will
do in the very near future. Uh which
means in the next couple of hours. So I
want to start with a landing page. Right
now this is my index page and as you see
it does not look very nice. I want to
make it beautiful. After that we will
create an admin dashboard. Inside of the
admin dashboard we will be able to
create courses. After that I will finish
off our public facing page. This means
we will create a course ID page and we
will allow customers to buy the course.
After that we will create a customerf
facing dashboard uh to view the course
and I think we will then be finished. I
hope so. But for now I want to start
with my landing page. So my landing page
is my index page. So if I go back to my
codebase right here we have our
page.tsx. Here's the thing. As
mentioned, we will have like you could
say three separate spheres if this makes
sense. We will have the public facing
pages. This means the index page, the
courses um overview page and then the
courses lock page which is then the
overview page for the individual course.
Then we we will have the admin section
and then we will have the public facing
dashboard for customers. This means I
want to create another route group and
this will be a public route group. This
means inside of there I will store all
of the routes which will be public
facing which don't require any
authorization. So in the app folder I
can create a new folder. Then I want to
use parentheses and I will call it
public. I will be honest with you. I
think public is not a great name because
it kind of has a conflict with our
normal public folder. But since this is
a route group, it does not create any
errors. Nevertheless, if you have a
better naming convention, then please
name it differently. If I would sit here
for a few hours, I would probably rename
it, but honestly, who cares? We will
leave it as is. Then inside of here, I
want to create a page.tsx. And I want to
delete this page.tsx. we don't need it
anymore since we have this new public
route. So what I will do is just copy
all of the code, paste it inside of here
and delete this index page which we have
in our root app directory. This page.tsx
in the public route group will now be
our new index page. This means if I go
back and do a hard refresh, everything
still works. Then we can go back and I
want to update my code a bit. So I want
to delete everything in the return
statement and I want to start with empty
tags. Inside of here I want to create a
section element and I will also give it
a class name which will be relative. So
the position and padding Y20. This means
padding on the top and bottom and this
corresponds to about 80 pixels. Then in
this section I want to render a div
element and in the div I want to get my
batch component which I import from my
components. Please make sure that you
don't import it from Lucid React. Lucid
React will render an icon, but we want
to render a component. So, I will import
it from the components. And inside of
here, I want to say the future of
online. You could learning education.
Yeah, education.
If I save this and again go back, you
will see right here this batch. It looks
good. But you know what? I want you
centered. So I will again go back and I
will first of all update this div. So I
will give it a class name and this will
be flex flex of column items which will
be center text which will be center and
then space Y of eight because here's the
thing we will render a badge as we do
right now. Then we will render a nice
big title, a little description and then
two links. That's why we created this
flex column layout because we want to
have a column if this makes sense. Then
I want to also update my batch. So I
want to give it a variant and this will
be outline. So as you see this is
already a bit better. Then underneath
the batch I want to render an H1. And
for the H1 I want to say elevate your
learning experience.
As you see this is not centered. This is
not quite what I want. So this means I
can give the H1 a class name and this
will be text for Excel. Then on MD or
bigger, this will be text 6 XL. And MD
or bigger means that the screen size has
to have a minimum width of what do we
have right here? 768 pixels. If it's
smaller, so if the width is smaller than
768 pixels, then we render text for
Excel. Then I want to also say a font
which will be bold, so a bigger font
weight. And then also tracking which
will be tight. So as you see this is our
title but I don't know it's not
centered. It does not look good. So we
want to again go back and then let's see
it's not centered. What's the problem?
We have our section relative. Then we
have our div. Ah that's the here's the
problem. The H1 is not rendered in the
div. But of course we want to rendered
in the div because this div is a flex
column or has a flex column layout with
gap and also text center. So let's again
paste it inside of here. And now it's
centered. And we also have the gap to
the top. Then underneath the H1 I want
to render a P tag. And inside of here I
will say discover. So discover
a new way to learn with our modern comma
interactive learning management system
dot and then access high-quality
courses anytime, anywhere. So the full
sentence will be discover a new way to
learn with our modern interactive
learning management system. Access
highquality courses anytime anywhere. If
I go back, you will see the description
right here. But there are two key
problems. It's a too big, so it takes
too much width. And secondly, the color
is too light. It should be like a
grayish color. This means I can give
this P tag a class name. And this will
have a maximum width. And here's the
thing. I want to add a custom width. So
right here, we already have like these
predefined tin CSS classes, 2.5, 2XL,
and stuff like that. And they have their
own maximum width. Uh but what I will do
is add a custom width. So for that you
can use these array brackets and inside
of here I will say 700 pixels. Then I
want to also update the text color and
this will be text muted foreground. And
then on MD or bigger this will be text
XL. If I again go back you will see that
this has a grayish color. And then I
want to also render two buttons
underneath this content. A button to
explore courses and then a button to
sign in. So we can go back. We want to
go underneath this P tag and then inside
of here or underneath the P tag I want
to create a new div. Then for the div I
will give it also a class name and this
will be flex flex of column. And then if
the device is bigger than this SM break
point I want to say flex row. So on a
mobile screen we will stack the buttons
vertically. On a desktop screen we will
align them horizontally. Then I want to
also say gap four and margin top of
eight. Inside of here I want to render a
link component imported from next/link.
And inside of here I will say explore
courses. Uh as you see the link
component currently complains and that's
because I'm missing one key property and
that's the href. So I will provide an
href and this should navigate or for the
href I will provide slashcourses.
If I save this and again go back, you
will see the link right here. But this
is not styled nicely. The link does not
look nice. So we want to add a class
name. And then of course again we could
style this link by ourselves. We could
add padding. We could add a background
color rounding stuff like that. But I
want to use the button variance
function. I want to make my life a bit
easier. So I can import it from the
components. I can invoke it. I can
destructure it. And then I want to also
provide a size which will be LG. So this
button will be a bit bigger than the
default shad CN button. And then I want
to also create a second link to sign in.
So I will go underneath this link. And
to be honest I can just copy paste the
link. We don't have to write it again.
Uh for the size this will be LG. I want
to update the variant. This will be
outline. And then for the href this will
be /lock in. And instead of saying
explore courses, I will say sign in. If
I save this and again go back, you'll
see two buttons. And if I click on sign
in, I will get redirected to our login
page. Then underneath this landing page,
if you want to call it like that, I want
to render like a feature section. So I
want to say something like comprehensive
courses, interactive learning, progress
tracking, something like that, you know.
So we can go back and I want to go
underneath our div. So under which div?
Well, I want to actually go underneath
the section. So I want to use again my
section element. We can open it and I
want to also give it a class name. So if
this currently confuses you, if you
don't really understand what I'm trying
to do right here, then let me uh show it
to you with a little diagram. So this is
our page right now. As you know, right
here we have a little batch. Then we
have a huge title. So let me just for
example use a text and this is a huge
title. Then underneath this big title we
have a small description. So this is
this right here. Oh of course we also
have two buttons. But yeah this is our
hero. But underneath my hero I want to
render three or four cards. So one then
also two three and four. In these four
cards I want to render like fe core
features like comprehensive courses
again interactive learning and stuff
like that. So this will be our landing
page. It will consist of this hero and
then these feature cards. So we can
again go back and then for the section I
want to create a grid layout because
again we will have four cards which
means we want to create a grid layout
with four columns. So I can go back I
can add a class name and then this will
be grid grid columns of one for the
mobile screen because on a mobile screen
we want to stack them vertically. Then
on MD or bigger, this will be grid
columns of two. And on LG or bigger,
this means on a desktop device, this
will be grid columns four. I want to
also add a gap, which will be six. And
inside of here, I want to map over my
features. Currently, I don't have any.
So, let's create a new array. I want to
go above my return statement, above this
export default function, and then inside
of here, I want to create a constant
features. And this will be equal to an
empty array. In this array, I want to
create an object. And this object will
have uh three properties, a title,
description, and icon. So, let's start
with the title. And for the title, I
will say comprehensive courses. Then I
want to also add a description. And for
the description, I want to say access a
wide range of carefully curated courses
designed by industry experts. This means
by me since I'm an expert. Then
underneath the description, I want to
also provide an icon property. And the
icon will be equal to this Mac OS icon.
So if you use Windows, I'm not sure how
you use the icons, but with Mac OS, you
want to click on command and then also
Fn or whatever it is and spacebar. And I
want to get the books icon right here.
Then I want to create another object
again with a title. For the title, I
will say interactive learning. Then I
want you also provide a description and
for the description I want to say engage
with interactive content quizzes and
assignments to enhance your learning
experience. Then I want to also provide
an icon and for the icon I will use this
game play gamepad I don't know
PlayStation controller. Then we can
create another object and you know what
currently we have a big problem. There's
no type safety. What I mean by that is
if I misspel title I don't get any
errors. So let's create a little
interface on the top. So interface I
will call it a feature props and then
this will be an object and inside of
here we will have a title which will be
of type string. We will have a
description which will be of type string
and then we will also have an icon which
will be of type string. Then I can use
this feature props for my constant
features. This means I can add a type
with this colon and this will be equal
to feature props. But feature props is
an object which means we want to append
this array symbol. So if I again go back
and now click on control spacebar I get
all of my types right here. So I want to
get my title and the third title will be
progress tracking. Then I want to also
add a description and for the
description I want to say monitor your
progress and achievements with detailed
analytics and personalized dashboards.
Then I want to also add an icon which
will be of type string. And for the icon
I want to provide this icon right here.
So the statistics icon. And then I want
to create one more object a fourth
feature. And again we want to provide a
title which will say community support.
Then I want to also provide a
description. For the description I will
say join a vibrant community of learners
and instructors to collaborate and share
knowledge. And then we are also missing
the icon. And for the icon I want to
just render a user icon. So right here
you can just say users and then you
should find this icon. So we now created
our features array which means I can
scroll again to the bottom and I can map
over my features in this section. So I
will get my features. Then I want to use
the map method as a param. I will get
the feature and also an index. And then
I can just return this. Then inside of
here, I want to use the cart component.
And as you all know, whenever you map
over items in React, you have to provide
a key. And what is unique right here?
Well, the index is unique. And also,
some people might say, "Hey, Jan, you
shouldn't use an index. You should use
an unique ID. You should go back to your
array, add ID, stuff like that." Yes, in
theory, you want to always use custom
IDs or unique IDs. An index is unique,
but whenever you start reordering items,
the index will break a lot of things.
But if your items are statically
rendered, this means if you don't have
drag and drop and no interactivity with
this features map or with this mapping
itself, then you don't need custom ids.
Then an index is fine enough. Then for
our cart, we can also provide a class
name. And I want to say on hover the uh
we I want to showcase a shadow which
will be LG and then also transition
which will be shadow. Then in the cart I
want to render a card header which is
imported from the components. And inside
of here I want to first of all render
the icon. So I will create a div and
inside of here I want to get my feature
dot icon. I want to also give the div a
class name which will be text for Excel
and then also margin bottom four. If I
save this and again go back, you will
see these cards on the bottom. They look
quite nice. But we are missing the title
and the description. So I can go back
and then underneath this div but still
in the cart header I want to get my card
title and I will render my feature.
Then underneath my cart header I want to
also render card content and in the card
content component I will create a P tag.
In the PTA tag, I will render my feature
dot description. We have an icon, then
we have the title, and then the
description. The only problem is this
description has a color which is white
and it should be a bit darker. So, I can
go back and then for the P tag, I will
provide a class name which will be text
muted foreground. And as you see, this
already looks way better. But if we look
at this page, you will see it's kind of
broken. If I zoom out, these cards go to
the end of the screen. This shouldn't
happen. I want to have something like a
container. This here should be the end
of my screen and the cards should align
all right here and they shouldn't
overflow. So this means we want to
create a layout. So I can again open my
explorer and then in the public folder I
will create a layout.tsx
because here's the thing on the top. So
if I go back and do okay, now it does
not work. So let's again go back for the
layout. I will create an export default
function layout public. I will also
create a return statement and I will
return a diff just so that this error
goes away. If I go back you won't see
anything. That's fine. But what I want
to do is render a navbar right here on
the top. Then I want to render my main
content which we just created. And then
this will be already it. Also this
layout will define our layout which
means it will create a container so that
this content or this outside space will
just be empty because on large devices
we don't want to take the whole width.
So we can again go back and then I want
to add a class name or in the return
statement I want to start off fresh. I
want to first of all again return a div
element. Then in the div I want to
render a navbar. For now, I will create
an H1 and say navbar. And underneath the
H1, I want to render my children. Where
do we get our children from? Well, we
will get them through uh from our
params. So, I can destructure the
params. And I want to get my children.
As you see, we get an error and it says
children is declared, but its value is
never used. And also, binding element
children implicitly has an any type. So,
we want to give it a type. And children
will be of type react note.
Then underneath my uh H1 I want to
create a main element and in the main
element I will render my children. This
means if I go back you will now see on
the top left corner I render this navbar
H1 and then I render my children. But we
still haven't fixed our container or our
width issue is this if this makes sense.
So for the main element I will provide a
class name and then this will be
container. This will create a maximum
width. But we with that also create a
problem because if I go back and zoom
out, you see it's aligned to the left
side but it should be centered. This
means we want to also give this main
element a class name which is MX auto.
This means it will center it in the
middle the content. And this already
looks way better. Then we can also
continue and I want to give it a padding
X4 on MD or bigger padding X6 and on LG
or bigger padding X8. Then as a next
step I want to create my navbar. So I
can open the explorer and then in the
public folder I want to create another
folder which will be underscore
components. So I know a few people
probably already forgot the reason on
why I create this underscore components
folder. So here's the thing. I'm a big
fan of vertical slice architecture. What
does this mean? Vertical slice
architecture essentially means that you
want to store your code based on the
feature. That's how I explain it in most
cases. So for example, my navbar is
public facing related. This means this
navbar will only be used in this layout.
It won't be rendered in my dashboard. It
won't be rendered in my admin dashboard.
It won't be rendered anywhere else. It
will only be rendered in this one
layout. Therefore, I create a components
folder right in this public folder. For
example, later on we will create a rich
text editor. This rich text editor will
be reused in multiple routes. That's
also the reason why I will later on
create a witch text editor or I will
store it in this components folder. If I
would only use it in one application
level itself, then I would also store it
in this specific route level. But since
I will later on reuse it, I will store
it in the components folder. The navbar
won't be reused. And that's the reason
why I created this underscore components
folder. Again, you can read more about
this if you go to Google and search
vertical slice architecture or
featurebased uh folder structure. You
will find enough info. I also created a
video on that on my YouTube channel.
It's called stop structuring your
project like a junior deaf. And there I
talk about how I structure my projects.
And then in this components folder, I
want to create a navbar.tsx
file. And inside of here we can first of
all create an export function navbar.
And then I want to also open this
function inside of here. For now I will
create a return statement and I will
return an H1 which says hey this is the
navbar. Then in my layout instead of
rendering this H1 I will render the
navbar component which is imported from
the components. If I again go back and
do a hard refresh, I will see the navbar
right here on the top left corner. But
of course, this is not quite what I want
to render. So let's create a beautiful
navbar. So I will go back and I will
create a new return statement, a fresh
return statement. I want to start off
with a header element and I will also
give it a class name. First of all, the
position will be sticky. This means once
we scroll later on, the navbar will
always be visible. Then for the position
I want to also say top zero. Um then we
want to say Z 50. So it should always
overlay our content. Then with full
border bottom I want to render a border
at the bottom. BG background and then /
95. This means I want to take the whole
background color and give it an opacity
of 95%.
Then we can also say backdrop blur. And
then I want to provide a custom filter.
So this means we can use array symbols
right here and I want to say
backdrop-filter
and then this will be equal to bg
background/60.
I can delete this h1 and I want to
create a div element. In this div I want
to render a link component which is
imported from next /link. I have to
provide an href. This will be the index
page. This means an empty slash and
inside of here I want to render the logo
and then also the company name. So first
of all we can get the image component
from next / image and we have to provide
a source and then also an alt. For the
alt I will just say logo and for the
source I can import it on the top. So I
will say import logo from at
/public/logo.png.
I can then pass it as a source and I
want to also provide a class name and
the class name will be size 9. This
means width 9 and height 9. And then
underneath the image I want to render a
span element and I want to say Marshall
LMS dot. I can also give it a class name
and this will be font bold. This means
if I again go back you will see right
here that we have a logo and then my
name right here or the company name. But
the thing is this should be aligned
horizontally. Currently it's aligned as
a column. This means we can go back and
for the link I can give it a class name
and then this will be flex. We want to
say item center and then also space X2
and margin um right four. So margin to
the right side. If I again go back,
you'll see that it's aligned
horizontally and it looks quite nice.
But we still have one problem. You see
this is my navbar, but my navbar has
zero padding. So this touches the
border. It does not look good. So I can
go back and then I can give this div
which wraps our link a class name. This
will also be container then flex height
which will be 16 and we can also say
minimum height 16. This is always better
then just to give an absolute value.
Then this will be items center MX auto
to center it in the middle. And then we
want to also add our padding on the
horizontal side. So this means padding
X4 MD or bigger padding X6 and LG or
bigger padding X8. And if I scroll a bit
to the bottom, you see that my navbar
overlays my content. Then I want to
continue with my desktop navigation.
This means I want to render my links. So
we can go back. We can go underneath
this link and I want to still stay in
this main div. And inside of here I want
to create a nav element. And again this
will be our desktop navigation which
means I can also create a comment which
will say desktop navigation. inside of
the nav element uh I want to create a
div element and then in this div element
I want to map over my navigation items.
So I will create an array above my
export function. This will be a constant
navigation items and this will be equal
to an empty array. Inside of here I want
to create three objects three links. The
first object will have a name. For the
name I will say home.
Then I want to also provide an href and
this will be an empty slash. Then for
the second link the name will be courses
and for the href this will be
slashcourses.
And then I want to also create a third
link and for the name this will be
dashboard and for the href this will be
/ dashboard. So we have finished with
the navigation items which means I can
map over them in my div. So I will get
my navigation items. I want to use the
map method. I will invoke it as a param.
I want to get an item and then I will
return it. Inside of here I want to
render a link component and for the link
we have to provide two key properties.
First of all the key which has to be a
unique identifier. In this case our name
is unique. So for the key I will pass
our item dot name. Then I want to also
provide an href and this will be the
item href and I want to also provide a
class name and this will be text sm font
medium transition which will be colors
and then on hover I want to render text
primary so my primary color and then in
the link I will render my item name.
This means if I again go back you will
see in the navbar three links home
courses and dashboard but there's no
spacing between these links. So I want
to go back then right here we have this
wrapping div and I can give this div a
class name which will be flex items
center and space x which will be two. As
you see this already looks way better.
And we are finished with the left side
but on the right side there are a few
things which I want to render. First of
all, I want to render a theme toggle and
then I want to create a turnary. If we
have a valid user session, I want to
create a user dropdown. If we don't have
a valid user session, I want to render a
lock in button. So, we can go back and I
want to go underneath this div, but I
want to stay in the snaf element. Inside
of here, I will create a div element.
And in this div, I want to get my theme
toggle, which is imported from the
components. This is self-closing. And if
I go back h yeah this is not what I
wanted. This uh theme toggle should be
on the right side. What wraps our
children? So we have this div and this
div. Our nav element wraps these two
divs. This means we can give our nav a
class name and then this will be flex.
And you know what on mobile this should
be hidden. This means the initial state
will be hidden and then on MD or bigger
it will be flex because again on a
mobile screen we don't want to render
these nav items. We want to only render
them on a desktop screen. Therefore this
will be hidden at the start and then
once we hit this MD break point we will
display it using this flex element. Then
on MD or bigger this will be flex one.
On MD or bigger this will be item
center. And then on MD or bigger, this
will be justified between because I want
to align the children to the mo most
outer corner. This means the left side
and also the right side. The next step
is to get our user session and then
either display a user dropdown or a lock
in button. So the first step is to first
of all get the user session and we will
do that on the client side. So above the
return statement I will create a
constant then I can structure it and
this will be equal to of client. I want
to import it from my lip folder and then
I want to call this use session
function. I can invoke it and then where
I structure it I can get my data and I
can also get the is pending boolean is
pending will be true whenever we fetch
the user session on the client side. Uh
I can then scroll a bit to the bottom
and right here I have my theme toggle.
Underneath my theme toggle I want to
create a turnary and if is pending is
true so um I can use a question mark
then I will return null. If it's not
true then we can create a colon and I
want to create another turnary. So
eternary in a turnary and I want to
check if we have a session. As you see I
don't get a session and that's because
we don't call it session but data. But I
can rename it with a colon and instead
of calling it session uh data we will
call it session. My god. Then I can copy
the name and if session is true then I
want to use a question mark and I want
to render my user dropdown. For now I
will just say locked in because this
means that we are locked in. If this is
not true then I want to use a colon and
I want to return empty tags. Inside of
here I want to render two buttons. First
of all a lockin button and then a get
started button. Both of these buttons
will redirect the user to the login
page. But it's just nicer to have two
buttons. So instead of rendering a
button, I will render a link component
which is imported from next /link. And
then for the link, I want to provide an
href and this will be /lockin. Then I
want to also provide a class name and I
want to style the link exactly the same
as a shad CN button. Therefore, I will
use the button variance function. And
then I want to also give it a variant
which will be secondary.
For the link, I want to say lock in. And
then I can copy paste the link one more
time. And this will be also HF login for
the class name button. Variance is fine.
I will delete the variant. So this will
be the default variant. And then instead
of saying login, I will say get started.
This means if I save this and again go
back and do a hard refresh, we will get
an error and that's because I use the
off client and the off client only works
in client components. Therefore, I want
to mark this navbar with the use client
directive. With that, this error will go
away. And now you see on the top right
corner the theme toggle, a login button,
and a get started button. That's because
I don't have a valid user session. But
here's the thing. It does not look nice.
I need some gap. So I can go back and
then again if I scroll a bit to the
bottom, we have this div. This div wraps
my theme toggle and then my user uh
session display. So I can give this div
a class name and this will be flex item
center because I want to center my items
vertically. Just if I center would
center them horizontally. And then I
want to also say space X4 to have some
spacing in between the items. So as you
see this already looks way better. As a
next step, I want to also create a theme
toggle or user dropdown. Uh I'm sorry.
Uh let me show it to you. I will log in.
You will see I will get redirected. I
want to sign in with GitHub. Then I will
get redirected back to the index page.
And then on the top right corner, you
now see logged in. But instead of
rendering locked in, I want to render a
drop-down. And then in the drop-down
menu, we will render three links. So
here's the thing. We could create our
own user dropdown, but this would be
annoying. So I will show you a nice
little component library called Origin
UI. And of course, I will link it down
below in the YouTube description. And
origin UI is relatively interesting
because this is a component library
which is built on top of SHA CN UI. Shad
CN UI is built on top of radics UI.
Origin UI is built on top of um SHAT CN
UI. This means it uses the same
components but it already creates
pre-built components. And I want to use
a user dropdown. So we can search for I
don't know drop-down. Yeah, drop-down.
Let's click on that. And then if you
scroll a bit to the bottom, you will
find this user dropdown. And if I click
on this user, we display the name, then
an email, and then a few options. And
that's exactly what I want to do. So I
can click on this view code toggle, and
then you can either install it or you
can just copy the code and then create
the component yourself. And that's what
we will do. So I will again go back. I
will open my explorer. I want to go into
the app folder uh public folder,
components folder components. And inside
of here, I will create a user
drop-down.tsx
file. For the content, I can just copy
this code and paste it inside of here.
And if you analyze the code, you will
see that these are just chat and UI
components. We import a few icons from
Lucid React. We get the avatar
component, the button component, and
then the drop-down component. And then
Origin UI just combines all of them and
styles them nicely. This means I can go
back to my navbar and instead of
rendering locked in I can get this user
dropdown and it's not called user
dropdown. How is it called component? Uh
I want to rename it. So this will be the
user dropdown and instead of doing an
export default function I want to export
this function normally. So just export
function and then in my navbar again I
can get this user dropdown which is
imported from my components. This means
if I again go back and do a hard
refresh, I get an error. I will have to
restart my dev server again, don't worry
about these uh things right here. That's
nothing which is related to our code.
And if I go back and do a hard refresh,
you'll see on the top right corner this
user dropdown. If I click on it, we get
all of these options and it looks quite
nice. Nevertheless, there are still a
few things that I don't like. So, for
example, if I click on this user
dropdown, this content, that's what you
see right here, is aligned in the
center. That's not quite what I want.
So, we can go back to this user
dropdown. And here we have this drop-own
menu content. There we can add an align
property. And we get three options,
center, end, and start. Currently, it's
aligned to the center. That's the
default. But I want to align it to the
end. This means to the right side. So
now it already looks way better. Then
what else can we do? Well, we have our
drop-down menu content, but you know, I
don't want to render Keith Kennedy. I
don't want to render this fake email. I
don't want to render option one, two,
and stuff like that. So, let's update
everything. Uh, I want to start off with
my drop-own menu items. So, instead of
saying option one, I want to render
home. Then, instead of using the bolt
icon, I want to use the home icon
imported from Lucid React. And if I go
back and again click on this user
dropdown, you will see if I click on
home, nothing happens. But I want to get
redirected to the index page. This means
I can go back and then for the drop-own
menu item, I can provide an as child
property. And this means that we render
a component or yeah a component, a
function, whatever in this drop-down
menu item because I want to use the link
component. So I will copy this code, the
span and the icon. And then I want to
get the link component from next /link.
I will again paste my code. And then for
the link component I want to provide an
href and this will be an empty uh slash.
Then we can continue with the next
drop-own menu item. And this will be for
my courses. So instead of saying option
two, I will say courses. And for the
icon instead of using layers 2, I want
to use the book open icon which is also
imported from Lucid React. Then I want
to also wrap this code in a link
component. We already imported it. And
for the link I want to provide an href
which will be /courses. Also don't
forget for the drop-own menu item we
want to provide an as child because
right here this is a child. If I again
click on this drop-own menu we get home
and courses. If I click on uh courses, I
will get redirected but we will get an
error and that's because I haven't
created this route yet. We will do that
a bit later on. And then there's one
more link which I want to render and
that's for our dashboard. So instead of
saying option three, I will say
dashboard. Instead of using the book
open icon, I want to use the layout
dashboard icon imported from Lucid
React. Then for the drop-own menu item,
I want to provide an as child property
and I want to wrap this code in a link
component. For the link, I will provide
an href and this will be / dashboard. If
I then again click on my dropdown, you
will see that we have three items right
here. Currently, we also render in
option four and five. I don't need that.
This means I can delete this drop-down
menu group which renders these two
items. I will just delete it. And now we
have first of all these three items. And
then we render this lock out drop-down
menu item. I can also delete one
drop-own menu separator. One is enough.
We don't need two. And if I again go
back, you will see that this already
looks way better. This lockout button
also currently does not work. This means
we have to create a separate function.
As you know, implementing the lockout
functionality is quite easy. So we can
go to our page.tsx and we wrote the code
already right here. So I can copy this
async function sign out and I will paste
it inside of here. Then we use this off
client. I want to import it from the lip
folder. I want to call the sign out
function. Then we have our fetch
options. I listen for the onsuccess
event. If it's successful, I want to
redirect the user to the index page. For
that, we have to initialize the router
hook. So I can go above this async
function and I want to create a constant
router which will be equal to use
router. I want to import it from
next/navigation
and then this error will go away. Then
we have to also import toast from sonar.
And then I want to also listen for the
onour event. So underneath on success I
will also get on error. This will be
equal to a standard error function. And
inside of here I want to return a toast.
And for the message I will just say
failed to sign out.
Then I can copy the name sign out.
Scroll to the bottom. And then for the
button we don't have a button. So I can
just use this drop-own menu item. I can
use an on click handler and this will be
equal to sign out. That's it. There's
nothing else that we have to add. This
means if I again go back and then click
on lock out, I should get locked out.
And as you see signed out successfully.
Then I can again log in, I will continue
or sign in with GitHub. I will get
redirected and then I will again see the
user drop down on the top. Currently I
render Keith Kennedy and this fake
email. So let's also update that and I
want to render a real email and real
name and also I want to render the user
image right here. So I can go back
scroll to the top right here I get a few
import errors. So I will just delete
these imports which are not needed
anymore. This means all of these icons
and I want to first of all create an
interface. So I will create an interface
called I props and I want to get a name
which will be of type string. I want to
get an email which will be of type
string and I want to get an image which
will be of type string. Then in my user
drop-down function in the params I can
structure them and this will be of type
I props. This means if I click on
control spacebar I get three properties.
First of all the email then the name and
then also the image and then I can use
these three properties to render real
data. So instead of rendering this
avatar.jpeg JPEG which does not exist.
We can render or we can pass our image
which we will pass through the params.
Then for the alt currently we say
profile image. This is fine enough. Then
for the avatar fallback instead of
rendering kk I want to instead get my
name. So name and then we can get the
first character. This means I can just
pass an array symbol and get the first
value. This means a zero. This is the
first um letter in the name. And then I
want to also use the two uppercase
method and I can invoke it because I
want to um uppercase the first letter.
And if I go back right now, you will see
nothing. And that's because we don't
have a name. This means I can go back to
my navbar. And here I already get an
error. And the error is that I'm missing
three properties. The email, image, and
name. So let's pass our email. And this
will be equal to session
user. L then we also have our image and
this will be equal to session do user
dot image and then we also have the name
and this will be equal to our session do
user dot name and as you see we get an
error right here and it says type string
or null or undefined is not assignable
to type string what's the problem well
the thing is when we sign in with GitHub
GitHub will automatically give us an
image of the user an avatar but when the
user signs in with the user's email.
Then we don't generate an image. We
don't get one. Therefore, for now to
just prevent this error, I will create
an or sign and render or pass an empty
string. This means if I again go back,
you will see my user image. Then instead
of rendering Kenneth Kennedy and this
email, I can also go back, scroll a bit
to the bottom, and then instead of
saying Kenneth Kennedy, I will get my
name. So this will be name. And then I
want to also update the email. And we
get our email through the params. But
here's the thing. I don't want to render
this email because it will display my
real email. So I will just hardcode
john@joh.com.
But you of course should render the
email which you pass or which you get
through the params. This means if I save
this and again go back then you will see
Jan then probably your email and then
home courses dashboard and then this
lockout button. Uh for my user dropdown
I currently got get one error that's
because I don't use the email. That's
fine. I will just um disable the CSLint
rule. Who cares? And then we are
finished with the user dropdown. So
let's analyze this page. Is there
anything missing? We have a nav but it
looks great. If I click on courses, I
get redirected. Our user dropdown looks
great. Then in light mode, this page
also looks great. In dark mode, it looks
great. Just in general, it looks
beautiful. Also, I just realized that
Origin UI, the component library,
released its own navbar um collection,
if you want to call it like that. So,
they released their own con collection
of 20 navbar components. So, I guess we
could have just copied it. But hey, uh
when I started creating this video, this
wasn't released yet. So, we can close
Origin UI. I don't need it anymore. And
we finished with our index page. But
here's the thing. In the demo, I showed
you a different UI, a different design.
This is just the default SHA CN UI uh
design which they provide us with.
Because if I head over to the SHT CN
website, I can customize the theme. So
here they have a themes button and here
I can for example use the default theme.
That's what we currently have. But they
also offer a green theme, blue theme, uh
theme, yellow theme, violet theme. They
look quite good. But the thing is the
only thing that changes is the color.
But the border is the same, the rounding
is the same, the text is the same, the
button looks the same. At the end of the
day, it just looks the same. But I want
you have a custom website. The design
should be completely custom. I want you
to have a custom width, a custom border
radius, a custom shadow. Everything
should be custom. I don't want to use
these predefined labels provided by SH
CN UI. That's why we can head over to a
website called tweakcn.com
and using this website we can customize
our chat cn UI theme because again if we
open our globals.css file we currently
define our theme or we customize it
using the CSS variables. This means if I
update for example this OKLCH color then
I update all of the components where I
use the second secondary foreground
color and with tweak CN I can customize
my colors, typography and layouts with
realtime preview. No signup required.
Nice. So I will click on try it out now.
And here they already provide us with a
lot of predefined themes. Amber,
minimal, bold, tag, bubblegum. You see
the rounding changes, the shadow
changes, the text or typography changes.
And here they provide us with a few nice
themes, a few themes which I find a bit
ugly, but honestly, whom who am I to
make or say what is nice and not nice?
So, you can choose your own right here.
For example, Superbase or T3 chat. These
are all nice themes, but I'm a big fan
of the claw theme. So right here I can
select cloth and that's the theme which
I want to use for this video. We can
also see how it looks like in light
theme. Yeah, it looks beautiful. Uh the
primary colors are fine. The secondary
colors are fine. Um we can maybe
customize the typography. So we could
for example select um this mono font. So
guys mono if you want to but for now I
will just leave it as system. Maybe
later on at the end I will customize it
and make it guys mono. I'm not sure, but
for now it's fine enough. Then we can
also update or customize the letter
spacing. Then we can also click on
other. Here you can update the hue
shift. We don't want to do that, but we
want to update the radius. So this is
currently the default radius, but I want
to have a smaller radius. So for
example, maybe 0.15.
Is this nice? Yeah, I think 0.15
looks quite good. Then for the spacing,
this is fine enough. For the shadow,
this is also fine enough. And I think I
can copy this theme preset.
And then I can just copy this. So this
is our globals.css file. It again
defines a root. Then it defines right
here the star class. And then this theme
inline uh creates all of the CSS
variables. So I can copy this. I can go
back and then I can uh collapse this
theme inline this root and then also
dark. I can then delete these three
objects and paste what I just copied.
Don't delete this at layer base. Don't
delete this at custom variant. We need
that. We want to just delete these three
objects. And if I again go back to my
index page, you will see, wow, this is
literally a completely new page.
Everything updated and that's what I
wanted. So we have a new background
color. We have this new border radius.
We have literally everything is
different. And again if you want to you
can also update the typography. But this
is a very big change. And that's why I
won't do it right now. Maybe later on
again as mentioned. Then also one
problem which I currently have is that
we don't have any margin to the bottom.
So I can go back to the page.tsx tsx to
our index page and then inside of here
we can first of all delete this async
function sign out then I can delete this
off client code I can delete this router
I don't need it anymore then I can
delete these unused imports I don't need
them anymore and also this can be a
server component which means I can
delete this use client uh directive then
as mentioned I want to create a bit of
margin to the bottom so I can go to the
second section and then I can add a
margin bottom which will be 32. So if I
again go back then you'll see that we
have some spacing to the bottom also.
Maybe later on I will add the margin to
the layout but for now it's fine enough.
So what's the next thing? We are
finished with the landing page. We are
finished with customizing the UI and the
next step is to create the dashboard
layout for the admin section uh for the
admin section because as mentioned we
will have two dashboards a publicf
facing dashboard for our customers to
view the courses but also an admin
dashboard so that admins can then log in
and create courses manage them this
means edit them delete them and stuff
like that. So we could create our own
dashboard, but this would literally take
days to perfect it. So we can head over
to Shhatzy and UI and then you will find
this block section and here they already
provide us with a beautiful dashboard.
So I can zoom out a bit. As you see this
will be the index page. They already
display a few nice cards, this analytics
chart and yeah, in general this is a
great uh dashboard layout which is also
responsive and that's why we will use it
in this video. So what you can do is
just copy this installation command on
top right here npx shad cn add-1.
I will copy it and then I want to paste
it into my terminal. Also instead of
using npx I want to instead say pnpm dlx
shad cn at latest and then this command.
Then I can click on enter. As you see it
asks me a few questions. So the file
button already exists. Would you like to
overwrite it? Yes, I would want to do
that. The same thing for the drop-own
menu for the drawer avatar and all of
that. And then if I open my explorer,
you will see that chat and UI generated
a few new folders and files. So we first
of all have a hooks folder with a use
mobile file. Then in the components
folder, we now have a few new files. The
app sidebar file, nav main, data table
and stuff like that. And also in the app
folder, we have a new folder, a
dashboard folder, a dashboard route with
a page.tsx. And then in the dashboard I
render the sidebar. So let's uh restart
the defaf server. So I will run pnpm
rundef. And then I can go back and do a
hard refresh. So this has refreshed
which means I can navigate to slash
dashboard. And as you see this is the
our dashboard. So right on the left side
we have a sidebar and then on the right
side this is the main content. And again
this is also mobile responsive. This
means if I collapse it, it's completely
responsive. I can click on this button
and then we have this navigation or
mobile navigation. Uh let me again
maximize this and I want to customize it
a bit. So currently this is / dashboard
or the route is uh a dashboard route.
Instead of calling it dashboard, I want
to call it admin. So I can uh rename
this dashboard folder and it should be
called admin. This means if I go back
and navigate to /admin, we again see
this dashboard which looks great. So if
we analyze this dashboard, how does it
work? How is it structured? Well, we
have a sidebar on the left side which is
mobile responsive which we can also
collapse. This is very important. And
then on the right side we have our main
content. Now here's the funny thing.
Creating sidebars, collapsible sidebars,
a mobile responsive sidebars is
literally one of the hardest things that
you can do as a developer. That's why
Shati and UI created a sidebar
component. This is a composable feeable
and customizable sidebar component. So
that's what we have set up because if
you head over back to our page, you will
see that we use right here for example
the sidebar provider and the sidebar
provider is imported from the components
and to be specific from the sidebar
component. So to create this dashboard
layout, we right now use the sidebar
component. And the sidebar component is
quite interesting because it's not a
singular component, but it's rather a
combination or it's a component which is
composed of multiple parts. So first of
all, we have a sidebar provider. So in
the page.tsx, you will see right here
everything is wrapped by a sidebar
provider and this handles the
collapsible state. So the collapsible
state is this right here. If I click on
the button, my sidebar collapses and I
don't see it anymore. Then we have the
sidebar component itself. And this is
the sidebar container. So they have a
very nice diagram right here. So right
here they don't showcase the sidebar
provider, but the sidebar provider
pretty much wraps everything. Then in
the sidebar provider, we have the
sidebar component itself. This, as you
see, also wraps everything. In the
sidebar, we then get a sidebar header
and sidebar footer. These are sticky at
the top and bottom of the sidebar. In
this case, this is our sidebar header.
And then on the bottom, this is like a
navigation user drop-down thingy. This
is the footer. And let's quickly check
it out. So, we have a sidebar provider.
And in the sidebar provider, we have an
app sidebar. In the app sidebar, we have
the sidebar header. And in the sidebar
header, I render this acme in logo. So
this is the header and then at the
bottom I also have a sidebar footer and
I render the nav user in the sidebar
footer. This means this right here this
dropdown is the footer. Then we also
have the sidebar content. The sidebar or
the sidebar content is this right here.
So this is our header and then this is
our footer and this here is our main
content. Then let's continue. What else
do we have right here? The sidebar group
and this is the section within the
sidebar content. So in theory for
example we can again create a line this
is one sidebar group this right here and
then this is another sidebar group and
in theory this is also a sidebar group.
So in this case we have one sidebar
content but this sidebar content
consists of three sidebar groups with
individual items. Then what else do we
have? We have a sidebar trigger. This is
this button which collapses our sidebar.
So this is how this whole structure is
created. And the main part is literally
this app sidebar because inside of here
we use the sidebar, the sidebar header,
the sidebar content with the sidebar uh
groups and then also the sidebar footer.
So if you want to customize the sidebar,
then you will do it in this app sidebar.
And then if we now analyze the sidebar,
what do we want to change? Well, right
here it says Acme Inc. H I don't want
that. So we can go back to the app
sidebar component and then right here
you will find the name Acme Inc. And
then also this icon. Currently they
provide us with the normal a tag but I
want to instead use the link component
provided by next slashlink. And for the
href this will be an empty slash. Then
instead of rendering this icon I can
delete it and instead I want to get the
image component from next/ image. For
the image component we have to pass two
properties. First of all the source and
then also an alt. For the alt I will say
logo and for the source we want to
import our logo. So on the top I can
delete this unused import and then I can
create an import and this will be logo
from at /public/logo.png.
I can then copy the logo name. Again
scroll to the bottom. My god that's so
much code. And then I can paste it right
here. Also I want to give the image a
class name. And this will be size five.
This means width five and height five.
And then instead of saying acme inc I
want to say marshall lms dot. This means
if I save this and again go back, you
will see right here that this is our new
logo and it looks absolutely beautiful.
Then we also have this quick create
button and then this mail icon. I want
to leave this quick create button, but I
don't need this mail icon. So I can go
back. Then we have the side by header.
We are finished with it. And then we
have this nav main. This means I want to
open the nav main component. And then
inside of here, if I scroll a bit to the
bottom, you will find the sidebar menu
button. Inside of here, we have the
quick create button and then also the
icon button or this inbox uh button. I
will delete the button. I don't need it.
I only need the sidebar menu button.
This means if I go back, we only have
this button. And this already looks way
better. The only problem is if I click
on quickre, nothing happens. But if the
user clicks on the button, I want to
redirect the user. This means I can go
back and then for the sidebar menu
button I want to add an as child
property because I want to wrap the icon
and the span text in a link component.
So I will import link from next /link.
Then I can again paste the content and
for the link I want to provide an href
and this will be slashadmin/courses
slashcreate because if the user clicks
on this link or on this button I want to
then redirect the user to create a new
course to quick create a new course.
This means if I click on this button I
will get redirected and we get a four
not found and that's because I haven't
created the route yet. We will do that a
bit later on. Then I have a new problem
and this is my sidebar content. My na
main content in general. These are links
which I don't want to render. I mean
dashboard life cycle analytics. This
does not make sense. I want to render a
dashboard link and then a courses link.
This means we can again go back. I want
to go to the app sidebar and if I scroll
to the top you will find all of the
links right here. So we have a constant
data and in there they have a nav main
then also the nav clouds array the nav
secondary array the documents array and
just in general in this object chats and
ui configured all of the routes so I
want to specifically update the nav
main. So the title dashboard, this is
our first link. That's fine enough. For
the URL, this will be /admin. And then
right here, we have a second link. This
currently has a title, which is life
cycle. This should be courses. And the
URL should be /admin. And then /courses.
If I go back and hover over dashboard,
you will see or in other words, if I
click for example on courses, nothing
happens. That's not quite what I want.
And where is this data rendered? Well,
if I again scroll to the bottom, we
right here have this nav main component.
I pass a prop which is items. And to be
specific, I pass my data.nav main. This
means I want to update the nav main
component. And again, right here, I get
a few errors. So, I don't need the
button import. I don't need this icon.
And if I again scroll a bit to the
bottom, we map over the items and then I
display them. But as you see, I don't
render a link. And that's why the user
also does not get redirected. So for the
sidebar menu button, I want to add an
ask child property. And then I want to
wrap the content in a link component.
It's already imported. I can again paste
the content. And for the link, I want to
provide an href which will be equal to
the item. Href or to the item URL
because in the app sidebar again we
provide a title and also the URL. So I
can go back. This is added. And this
means if I save this and go back and
click on courses, I will get redirected.
Of course, I get a 44 not found. But
that's because I haven't created the
route yet. Then let's analyze it. So we
have a dashboard route, a courses route,
an analytics route, projects route, team
route. At the end of the day, I will
only create two routes. A dashboard
route, this is the index page, and a
courses route. I won't create an
analytics route. I won't create a
projects route, a team route. There's
not enough time in this video.
Nevertheless, I don't want to delete
these items because then our sidebar
will be quite empty and we don't want
that. So, I will leave the links right
here. They will be not working links,
but it will just look nicer. Then I can
also go back and I want to configure a
bit my links. So, this sidebar is a bit
too full. So, for example, I don't want
to render documents, which means I can
go back and I want to delete this
documents away. I don't need it. I don't
want to render it. So, I can just delete
it from this constant data. And if I
scroll a bit to the bottom, we get an
error. And it says right here, documents
does not exist. And that's because I
don't want to render the snav documents
anymore. So, I can just delete it. I can
also delete the import at the top. And
then also from the components, I can
delete the uh the nav documents
component. I don't need it. So, I will
move it to the trash. I will also delete
unused imports. I don't need them
anymore. I don't want to get any errors.
And if I again go back, this will
already look way better. So again, the
dashboard link works, the courses link
works, but the analytics, projects, team
settings, uh, get help and search links,
they won't work. These are just there so
that the sidebar does not look so empty.
And then what else? Is there anything
else I want to update? Yes, I want to uh
update the nav user. This means I can go
back and if I go back to the page.tsx,
we have our app sidebar. In the app
sidebar, I render my nav footer or
sidebar footer and then I render the
snaf user component. This means I want
to update the nav user component. And
then in our params we get an object user
and in the object we have a name, an
email and an avatar. And where do we
pass this object? Well, this nav user is
rendered in the app sidebar. We pass a
prop which is this user. Our user is
defined in the constant data user with a
name, email, and avatar. So here's what
we will do. We will delete this user
from our constant data. We won't need it
anymore. Then in the nav user, I can
delete this destructuring. I won't
destructure my nav user anymore. And
then for the nav user component, which
we render in the app sidebar, I can
delete this prop. I won't pass anything
right anymore. Then in the nav user
component, I want to get the user
session. And here's the thing. There are
two ways to get a user session. Either
on the server side or on the client
side. We already know that. But here's
my question to you. How should we get
the user session on the server side or
client side? You might say the server
side is fine. Or you might say the
client side is fine. Well, there's only
one right answer. And the right answer
is to get the user session on the client
side. Why is that? Well, here's the
thing. In a second, we will convert this
page.tsx into a layout.ts. tsx and then
the page or the index page will be a
child and then we will have a courses
route and an edit route and stuff like
that. But at the end of the day we will
have a layout which is the sidebar where
we render this user nav and then on the
right side we will have all of the
children. If I get the user session on
the server side all of the children will
be converted or will be opted into
dynamic rendering. This means every
request will be rendered the page will
be rendered dynamically. My god. So,
Nex.js has the ability to render pages
two ways. Either on the server side or
on demand or it can be statically
rendered a page. And if I fetch the user
session right here on the server side,
every child will be automatically opted
into dynamic rendering. If Nex.js gives
you the ability to render a route
statically, then you don't want to take
this ability away or give this ability
away. So that's why we want to get the
session on the client side and also if
you head over to my YouTube channel
again don't forget you subscribe please
do that then you will find this video
stop fetching data in nextJS the wrong
way uh here's how to do it the right way
or something like that I'm not sure why
this is translated into German but yeah
in this video I also talk about data
fetching so I can again close this then
we can go back I want to go underneath
this use sidebar hook and I want to
create a constant we can destruct
And this will be equal to off client. Of
client is imported from the lip folder.
And then we want to use the use session
hook or the use session function. I want
to call it and then where I structured I
will get the data. This means the
session and also the is pending boolean.
Then I can go underneath this constant
and I want to create an if statement. If
is pending. So if we are currently
fetching the user session uh then I want
to return null. This means I won't
return anything. And once we get our
session, we will then return this user
dropdown. Then I can scroll a bit to the
bottom and I can update my source and my
name and stuff like that. So for the
avatar source, I want to use the session
do user dot image. And here's the thing,
we will get an error. What's the
problem? Well, it says type string or
null or undefined is not assignable to
type string blob or undefined. What's
the problem? Well, again, a user can
sign in either with GitHub or with
email. If a user signs in with his
email, then we won't generate a avatar
or an avatar URL, an avatar image,
whatever. That's why we want to render
something else. This means if we don't
get an image URL, then we can use
nullish coist. This says, hey, if this
value is not defined or null or
something like that, then let's render
whatever we pass here. And we want to
use a little micros service. So if you
go to Google you can search for avatar
versell API and then you will find this
link. This is a GitHub repo and here
they say beautiful avatars as a micros
service and this URL will just generate
a new image. So we can copy it. I can go
back and then I want to use optics and
paste it. This means again if we don't
get an image URL from our provider then
we will just generate one by ourselves.
So this is avatar.cell.sh. SH and then
we can pass a name and this name will
then dynamically generate the image. So
currently it's hardcoded as RA g the
name of the founder. So let's use a
dynamic value and I want to pass the
session user email. This means this API
will generate an image using the user's
email and then the image will be
relatively unique for every user. Then
for the alt I want to pass the user or
not user but session do user.name name
and then I want to continue with the
avatar fallback and this avatar fallback
will be rendered if the avatar image is
not accessible for some weird reason if
the URL is broken or something like that
and then instead of rendering the image
this fallback will be rendered for now
for example CN is hardcoded but in most
cases you want to use the initials of
the user's name this means we can for
example get the session dot user name
dot name and then I can use array
brackets and get the first character uh
from this username. But this is actually
kind of a mistake. Why is this a
mistake? Well, here's the thing. If a
user signs in with GitHub, then GitHub
will provide us with the user's name.
Great. That's what we want. But if the
or if a user signs in with his email,
then we won't get a name. And this is a
huge problem. So the weird thing is
better off handles the username and it
says that it's strictly defined but it
isn't because if I hover over the name
it says it's of type string but in
reality yes the name is of type string
but it could be not defined. Better off
in the back and converts this null to an
empty string. What what do you mean by
that? Well if a user signs in with his
email then better off just creates a
empty string for the name. But we don't
want that because again if we have an
empty string then I can't render
anything right here. This means we have
to now check if we get a username with a
few characters. If not then we want to
use the user's email and then use the
first character. Honestly I think this
is a very bad design from the better off
team. If there's no username then this
should be null, not just an empty
string. This is a huge mistake.
Honestly, I'm not sure how they could
ship something like that to production.
But hey, I'm not a maintainer, so who
knows? Maybe there's a good reason for
that. So, we will create a turnary. We
will check if the session uh username is
defined. If so, we will then also check
if we have at least one character. If
so, then we will render the first
character of the username and if not, we
will render the first character of the
user's email. So, I will create a
turnary or I will check the following.
Hey, if the session do user.name is
defined, then we can use this double and
sign and then I want to check if the
session username has at least one
character. So I want to get the session
do user.name. We now know that it's 100%
defined. And we want to check if the
length is bigger than zero. So at least
a character length of one. If the
character length is bigger than zero,
then this means that we have a real
username. If so, we can use a question
mark eternally and I want to render the
session do user.name and then I can use
the char at. So uh again let me get the
name right here and I can use the char
at or car at no char at so character at
method and I want to get the first
character. So as an argument I want to
provide zero so the first character and
then I want to also use the two
uppercase method because I want to
uppercase the first character. If this
is not true, if the character length or
if the length of the name is not bigger
than zero, this means if we don't have a
username, then I want to use the email.
So we can use the colon and I want to
get the session do user do email and uh
again we want to use the character at
method. I want to get the first uh
character and then I can use the two
uppercase method and I want to invoke
it. So again, if we don't have a
username, then or if we have a username,
then we will render the first character
of the username and we will uppercase
it. If there's no username defined, then
we will use the user's email. We will
also use the first character and we will
uppercase the first character. It's
quite simple as you see. Um then I want
to continue right here with the
username. And here we again have the
same problem. We render the username,
but if we don't have a username, this
will be an empty string. This means we
want to literally again create the same
if check the same turnary. So I will
delete this user.name and I will check
if we get the session do user.name then
let's use this double and sign and then
I want to also check that the session do
username has a bigger character length
than zero. So we can again get our
session do user.name.length
and if this is bigger than zero then I
want to create a turnary. So I will use
a question mark and then I want to
render the session do user.name and if
the username is not defined then I want
to render the email. So I will use a
colon and I will get the session do
user.mmail.
But if I will leave it like that then we
will just render the user email as a
name. We don't want that. I don't want
to render this atgmail.com only the
start of an email. So what do I mean by
that? For example this is an email as
you see d.com.
I want to just render this first section
uh which is in front of this at. This
means we can again go back to the top.
Then where do I have my email or my
name? It's right here. And then for the
session user email, we can use the split
method. So dotsplit, I can invoke it.
And I want to split this at. And then I
want to also append this array bracket
zero at the end which means I want to
get the start of this uh email. What
does this mean? Well, again this is a
email as you see and with the zero I
will get this uh start because it splits
everything from this ad. It splits this
section and this section and I want to
get the first section which means I use
array brackets with the zero. Then this
is finished right here instead of
getting the user email. I want to get
the session do user email. Then we have
our avatar image again. As you all know
we already fixed the problem with the
avatar image. So I can scroll to the
top. Here we have our avatar image. I
will just copy the source and the alt.
Then I can go back and also paste it. So
I can delete this old source and alt and
paste what I just copied. Then for the
avatar fallback again I just I can just
copy my old avatar fallback and paste it
right here. So I will delete this one
and paste what I just copied. And then
we can also update the username and
email. We already did that. So I can
just copy this turnary. Then I will
paste it for the username and for the
email I will just render my session do
user do email. So this should fix all of
the problems. Yes, this looks good. Uh
whatever do we have this unused import
statement I can delete it. And if I
again go back you'll now see that I
render my name, my email and if I click
on this user dropdown I again render my
name, my email and my avatar also. Let
me uh remove this uh thingy. I don't
need it. So uh bottom right. This will
be better. Yeah. And one problem which I
currently have is that this avatar has
like this gray scale. I don't really
like that. So I can again go back scroll
a bit to the top and then for this
avatar image you see we have a class
name with grayscale. I can delete this
grayscale and then my image will have
the full you could say opacity I guess.
So yeah our sidebar looks finished. Um
the only problem is these links don't
work. If I click on account nothing
happens. If I click on billing, nothing
happens. If I click on notifications,
nothing happens. So, we can go back. We
can scroll a bit to the bottom. And
instead of rendering this drop-down menu
content with account, billing, and
notifications, I want to instead render
a dashboard link, a homepage link, and a
courses link. And of course, I want to
leave this lockout button right here.
So, for the first drop-down menu item,
instead of saying account, I want to say
homepage. Then I want to also redirect
the user which means I want to render
the link component. So for the drop-down
menu item I want to pass an as child
property and then I will copy the
content in the drop-down menu item. I
want to get the link component from next
/link. Then for the link I want to
provide an href and this will be an
empty slash because I want to redirect
the user to the homepage. Then also I
want to update the icon. I want to use
the home icon imported from Lucid React
and then we can continue with the second
link. So instead of redirecting the user
or instead of saying billing I want to
say dashboard. Then for the icon uh I
want to change it. I want to use the
icon dashboard. This is imported from
Tableau icons. So here's the thing. When
we created this admin dashboard so when
we use this command it also installed a
new icon library. So if I open my
package.json you will find right here
Tableau. So if I search for it, Tablea
icons react. So this was installed when
we created our dashboard. In theory,
it's not great to have two icon
libraries, but honestly, this is also a
good icon library. So I will use it. So
we can again go back. I will close the
package.json. And this has been uh
imported. Then I want to also wrap the
content in a link component. And for the
link, I want to provide an href. This
will be /admin. Also, we want to give
the drop-own menu item an as child
property. And then the third link, this
should be courses. Then I don't want to
use this icon. Instead, I will use the
TV2 icon imported from Lucid React. Then
I can give this drop-down menu item an
ask child property. And also I want to
wrap the content in a link component.
This has already been imported. Let's
give the link an href. And this will be
slashadmin and then slashcourses.
I think this should be already it. This
means if I again go back and click on my
user dropdown, I get three items or
three links. If I click on dashboard,
nothing happens. If I click on homepage,
I will get redirected to the homepage.
And if I click on courses, I will get
redirected. But since we don't have a
route yet, it throws a 44 error. Then we
can go back. This lockout button
currently does not work. If I click on
it, I don't get locked out. And this is
a huge problem. So, we can go back and
then for the drop-own menu item, I want
to pass an on click handler. And if the
user clicks on this item on this button,
I want to lock out the user. Who would
have thought? Groundbreaking. No. And as
you already know, we created a function
in our user dropdown. And this user
dropdown is rendered in our navbar. So,
right here, async function sign out. And
then we use the off client to sign the
user out. But here's the thing. I don't
want to rewrite this function 10 times.
I think you all know this one saying,
don't repeat yourself. Keep everything
dry. This means we want to create one
file, one for example hook, and then
reuse it in multiple places. So I want
to open my explorer. Then I want to go
into the hooks folder. So in the root
directory, we have a hooks folder. And
inside of here I will create a use dash
sign out.ts
file. And inside of here I will create a
hook. And if I call this hook we will
sign out the user. So first of all we
want to mark this hook as or we want to
mark this file with the use client
directive. Then we can create an export
function which I will call use sign out
and then I can just open it. Then inside
of here I want to create a function to
sign the user out. So I can go to the
user dropdown and I can literally just
copy this uh async function sign out. I
will copy it and then paste it into my
use sign out function. Then I want to
update this async sign out function. So
this should be a constant and I will
call it handle sign out and then this
will be equal to async function sign
out. I want to import the off client
from the lip folder. Then I want to also
initialize my use router hook. So above
this constant handle sign out we can
create a constant router and this will
be equal to use router. Please make sure
that you import it from next/navigation.
I want to then invoke it and now I get
access to the router. Also I want to
import the toast from sona the toast
library. And now we are already
finished. We want to also return handle
sign out. So I can go underneath the
constant but still in the function use
sign out and I want to just return
handle sign out. So right here we just
created a custom hook. So again let me
go through this function through this
code. So first of all we create an
export function use sign out. Inside of
here we initialize our use router hook
and then in this use sign out function
we sign out the user. So we create a
handle sign out function. Then we for
example or not for example we use the
off client to sign the user out. We have
our on success our on events and then we
return toasts and we also redirect the
user if everything was successful. This
means I can use this use sign out
function in my nav user. I can scroll to
the top and this is a client component
which means I can go underneath this
constant data uh with the offclient uh
use session and then I want to create a
constant. This will be called handle
sign out and this will be equal to use
sign out. Use sign out is imported from
our hooks folder. I can invoke it and
then this handle sign out function will
allow us to sign out. So I will copy the
name. I will scroll to the bottom and
then this onclick handler will be equal
to handle sign out and then we will sign
the user out. Then we still get three
errors right here and that's because of
unused imports. So I will scroll to the
top. I will delete this unused import
and also this one. And as you see, we
don't get any errors anymore, which
means everything should work. So I will
go back. I will do a hard refresh. And
if I click on log out, let's see. Yes, I
got signed out successfully. And also I
got redirected to the index page. Right
here on the top in the nav by you see
display two buttons, login and get
started. And if I click on login, I will
again get redirected to the login page.
I will sign in with GitHub. As you see
signed in with GitHub, you will be
redirected and I got redirected. Then if
I again go /admin then you will again
see the usern at the bottom with all of
my links. Wow, this was so cool. So we
have finished with the nav user. I can
close it. Then also for our navbar or
for the user dropdown, uh I don't have
to use this code anymore. async function
sign out. Instead, we can just use the
use sign out hook. So, I will just
delete it. I will also delete the use
router hook. And then right here, I can
say constant handle sign out. And this
will be equal to use sign out which is
imported from the hooks folder. If I uh
then I can copy this function. I can
scroll to the bottom and for the onclick
handler, I will pass handle sign out. As
you see, I still have a few unused
imports. So I will just delete them and
we are already finished which is great.
So I can close this. I can close the app
sidebar, the nav main and the page. If
we look at this page, everything looks
great. The sidebar is finished. The user
nav is finished. Everything is
collapsible. But if I look at the code
structure, it isn't great. So for
example, our components folder has an UI
folder. And then we also have all of
these files which are related to the
sidebar which means it would make a lot
of sense to just group them in a
separate folder. So in the components
folder I will create a new sidebar
folder and then I want to move all of
these files into the sidebar folder. So
I will just select all of them. This
means I can click on shift and then
select them and then I will move all of
these files into the sidebar folder. I
will move them. I will get a warning
probably. No, it looks good to me. Yes,
right here. This is the warning. I want
to update the imports. So, I will click
on yes. And in theory, this should work.
This means if I go to the app sidebar,
yeah, the imports look correct to me. No
errors. Chart area. Yep, this looks all
good. And if I go back and do a hard
refresh, yes, everything works nice. So,
this was a little cleanup. So, this
components folder looks a bit cleaner.
Also the site header should be moved
into the sidebar. So uh yes I want to
update everything. And again if I go
back let me save this. If I go back and
do a hard refresh everything works
great. So this is finished. Then right
here I have one problem. This is our
header. I display this button. This
looks nice but I don't want to render
documents and also GitHub. No I don't
want that. So we can again analyze our
page.tsx. So sidebar provider app
sidebar site header. Yes, we want to
open the site header. This means I can
again open the components folder. I want
to go into the sidebar folder and then I
want to open the side header component.
Inside of here we have a header. Okay,
this is not interesting. Sidebite
trigger. This is nice separator
documents. I don't want to render
documents. Instead, I want to render
Marshall LMS dot. Then we have a div
margin left auto and then a button which
renders GitHub. That's not what I want.
What should we render here? Hm, let me
think about that. How about we render
the theme toggle? I think this will make
a lot of sense. So I can delete the
button, but I want to still leave the
div right here with margin left auto.
And then I will get my theme toggle
which is stored in our components. This
is self-closing. Then I want to delete
this unused import which and if I again
go back then you will see here Marshall
LMS and then on the top right corner a
nice looking theme toggle. We can also
select light theme. Yes, this looks all
great. If I click on the nav user yes it
also looks great in light mode. And then
I will again select dark mode so that
you can see something. I know a lot of
people hate light mode. I personally
love it but who cares? So I would say
that we have finished with the admin
site or with the admin dashboard. And
what's the next thing which I want to
do? Well, I want to create the courses
world because if I click on courses, we
get a four for not found error. This
means I can go back. I can open the
explorer. I want to go into the app
folder into the admin folder and I want
to create a new route. This means a new
folder. I will name it courses. And in
the courses folder I want to create a
page.tsx.
Since this is a route, I want to create
an export default function. Then I will
call it courses page. And then I can
just open this function. Inside of here,
I will create a return statement with a
diff and then an H1 where I say, hey,
how are you? If I save this and again go
back and do a hard refresh, you will
see, hey, how are you? This is great. We
don't get any errors anymore. But where
is my layout? Where is my sidebar?
Where's my theme toggle? everything is
gone. I mean, I don't want to render my
dashboard again inside of here. I want
to have a layout. This means if I open
my explorer, you will see that our
sidebar is currently rendered in a
page.x. But as I already mentioned at
the start, instead of having a index
page or instead of rendering the sidebar
in an index page, I want to render it in
a layout. This means in the admin
folder, I want to create a layout.tsx
file. Again we want to create an export
default function. This will be the admin
layout. I can then also open this
function and create a return statement.
For the return statement I want to
return my admin layout my sidebar. This
means I can again open the explorer go
into the page.tsx and I will copy
everything in the return statement. I
can then paste it inside of here. And as
you see we get a few import errors. This
means I can go to the top and just copy
all of the import statements. I will
then paste it on the top and this should
be already it. Then I want to update my
page.tsx and I want to delete
everything. So I will just delete
everything and I will create a new
export default function. This will be
the admin index page. And then I will
open the function. Create a return
statement. Create a diff h1. And I want
to say hello from the admin index page.
If I save this and again go back and do
a hard refresh, you will see my admin
dashboard, my admin layout again. But
where is my courses H1? Well, here's the
thing. We want to render the children.
So, what I will do is copy the section
cards, this diff with the chart area
interactive and this data table. I will
copy all of that and instead I will
render the children right here. Then for
the page.tsx, TSX. Instead of rendering
this boring H1, I will paste what I just
copied. And also, I want to wrap
everything in empty tags. So, I will
create them quickly and paste what I
just copied. I will import the section
cards from the components. I will import
the chart area interactive from the
components and also the data table from
the components. Then I want to also get
my data. So, I can just copy this import
data statement or import path and I will
paste it right here. Then for my layout
as you see I get an error for my
children and it says cannot find named
children. That's because we want to get
our children through the params. So I
can destructure the params I want to get
children and I have to also pass a type
and children will be of type react note.
I can import react note from react and I
will also delete all of the unused
import statements. If I save this and
again go back then you will see hey how
are you? And if I go to the dashboard
itself, then you will see this index
page. All of the children again. This is
what we wanted. But if I go to the
courses, this H1 touches the sidebar
border. This is not quite what I want.
This means I can go back to the layout
and then this div wraps our children.
Currently, we give it a padding on the
yaxis. But we can also give it padding
on the xaxis. So after this padding y, I
want to say padding x of four. And on LG
devices or bigger, I want to give it
padding X of six. This means if I again
go back, this will already look way
better. We now have some spacing. And
that's exactly what I wanted. So as a
next step, I want to continue with the
courses route, which means we want to
display all of the courses. Then we want
to create courses, edit them, and do all
of the fancy stuff. So let's start with
the courses overview page. So as
mentioned this will be an overview page.
This means right here I will display all
of the created courses and then also on
the top left corner I want to render a
title and then on the right side a
button. Here I have created a little
diagram to showcase everything. As you
see I love diagrams. So this is our
sidebar. Then this is our main content.
Again here we have a title. then this
button and then I will create a grid
layout with two columns to then display
all of the created courses. This means
we can go back to our application to our
code not to our application and then I
want to first of all create this header
you could say. So um I want to delete
everything in the return statement and
let's start with empty tags inside of
here. We can create a div element and
then let's give it a class name. This
will be flex items center justify
between to align the children to the
most outer corner. This means the left
side and then the right side. And then
inside of here we want to display again
two things. First of all a title and
then a creation link or in other words
button. So let's create an H1. And
inside of here I will say your courses
and then I want to also style this H1
because as you see it's too small. So we
can give it a class name. And this will
be text to Excel. This means the text uh
the text size will be bigger. And then
font bold to give it a bigger font
weight. Then underneath the H1 I want to
get the link component from next /link.
And then inside of here uh we will say
create course create course. Then this
link also currently complains. That's
because it's missing an href. And the
href will be equal to slashadmin/courses
slashcreate. As you all know, I want to
style the link component exactly the
same as a shhat CN button. This means we
can give it a class name which will be
equal to button variance which is
imported from the components. This
already looks way better. And then
underneath this header, I want to
display all of the courses. This means
we can go underneath this div, but I
want to stay in these empty tags. And
then I will create a div h1. And inside
of here we can say uh here you will see
all of the courses. Yeah, this looks
quite good. So before I can even display
any courses, we have to first of all
create them. And to create courses, we
have to store them in our database. So
here's the thing. If I currently open my
schema, I only have models tables for
the user itself or for the offend for
better off. But there's no model.
There's no table for our course. This
means we want to create a new one. And I
want to give you a little introduction
to Prisma itself because I haven't
really explained things yet. So Prisma
is an ORM as we all know a TypeScript
ORM and we define tables in the schema
file. Prisma calls them models, but in
database terms, it would be called a
table. Here's the thing. Prisma has its
own language, its own DSL, domain
specific language. This means this code
isn't TypeScript. It isn't Rust or PHP
or anything like that. It's its own
programming language. Again, its own
DSL. This means, yeah, you have to learn
a new language, but as you see, it's
very simple. Model verification. This is
our table. And then we define all of our
columns and we append all of the types
string daytime for example int and stuff
like that. So it's very easy to
understand. Also you see I have syntax
highlighting right here and I have also
autocomp completion. To get the same
thing you want to go to your extensions
and in the extensions you want to search
for Prisma. Please check that you have
Prisma installed the extension because
it will add syntax highlighting,
formatting, autocomp completion and much
more. So it's definitely a must-have if
you work with Prisma and that's exactly
what we do. So I want to create a new
model, a new table and from now on I
will just say model but again the real
database term is table. So I will scroll
underneath this model verification and
then we will create a new model course.
Then we can open it and inside of here
we will define all of the columns. So
first of all since we work with a
relational database it we have to also
provide a unique identifier. This means
a primary key. So in this case an ID is
what we want to create. This will be of
type string at id default uyu ID. This
means whenever a new row is generated
Prisma will also generate a new unique
ID and then this will be our primary
key. Then what will our courses have?
Well, they will for example have a
title, a description, an image, a price,
a duration and stuff like that. So,
first of all, I want to provide a title.
This will be of type string. Then a
description which will be also of type
string. Then a file key which will be of
type string. What is the file key? So
here's the thing. Later on we will
upload files to S3. S3 will return the
key and we will store the key in our
file key later on. Then when uh once we
want to render the image, we will just
construct a new URL using this key which
we store in our table or yeah in the row
itself. Then I want to also get a price.
This will be an integer, a number. Then
also a duration. This will be also an
integer. Then a level. And here's the
thing. We will only have three levels.
Beginner, intermediate, advanced. This
means what type would work right here?
Well, we could just say type string.
That's fine. But this is not type safe.
I want to have type safety also on the
type uh database level. This means we
can create an enum and this will be
called course level. I can open it and
our three states will be beginner then
or I don't have to add a comma. Then
intermediate and also at advanced and
yes I misspelled this. Don't worry I
will fix it in a second. But these are
our three states. And then level will be
equal to course level. So I can only
provide these or one of these three
values for the level. And we could also
for example add a default and that's
what I will do. So what could a default
be? Well, let's say a beginner. So add
default beginner. You don't have to do
that. We can also leave it without a
default. That's fine. So the level is
finished. What else will our course
have? Well, for example, a category.
This will be of type swing. This means
for example development or cooking or
stuff like that. Then also a small
description because here's the thing we
will later on create two descriptions. A
small description which will be rendered
for the course card. So if I go back to
the diagram for example here we have
here we will have a small description
which will be rendered in this overview
course card. But then I want to also
create a big description and this big
description will be created with a rich
text editor. And since we will then
later on store it in JSON transform it
into a string. Yeah, complicated. Who
cares? It will just be easier to have
two descriptions. One small description
which is easily rendered here and then
one big description which we will have
to transform into JSON and then do a lot
of fancy stuff. So small description
this will be of type string. Then I want
to also get a slug because I want to
then later on display the course using
the sluck and not an ID. This is always
better for SEO. This will be of type
string and add unique because you don't
want to have duplicates uh slugs. They
have to be unique pretty much like ids.
Then I want to also create timestamps.
This means first of all a created at
time stamp. This will be of type date
time and then at default now. So
whenever we generate a new row a new
timestamp will be generated. And then
also I want to get the updated at time
stamp. This will be of type date time.
and then add updated at. This means
whenever the row is updated, the updated
at time stamp will be also updated. Then
I want you also create a status. I will
create it above the created at and
updated at. And we will have three
statuses and this will be draft,
published and archived. This means we
can again create a new enum. So enum
this will be course status and I will
have three states. First of all draft
then published and then also archived.
Then for the status this will be equal
to the course status enum. And I can
again add a at default and this will be
draft because a course as a default will
always be a draft. Uh a user will have
to first of all publish it to uh for it
to be published. Then is there anything
else? Well, we can also create a
relation. So here's the thing. We have a
user table right here. model user and
then we have a course table right here.
I want to create a relationship. So what
relationship do we want to create?
Either a onetoone relationship or a one
to many relationship or maybe a many to
many relationship. What would make sense
right here? Well, a one to many
relationship would make a lot of sense.
One user can create multiple courses.
Each course is related to one user, to
one creator in this case. Creating
relations with Prisma is super easy. You
want to go to the user model. Then we
can go underneath this accounts and here
I want to get my courses and this will
be equal to the type course and I want
to append an array symbol. This means we
will create a one to many relationship
one user many courses and if I click on
command save it will also autogenerate
this relationship. So in the model
course we now have a user and also a
user id which is of type string and here
we have the relation to the user. So
this worked exactly as expected and
wanted also for the user I can add an
ondee property and this will be equal to
cascade. This means if I for example
delete a user then this course will also
be automatically deleted. Of course, I
won't delete a user, but just in
general, this is a good best practice or
a good practice to add these ondelete
properties. So, I think this is already
it. Is there anything that I would want
to update? Maybe. Yeah, I want to a
lower case user user ID is fine. And
currently, these fields are optional
where uh as you see question marks, I
will delete this question mark. It won't
be optional. And yeah, our relation is
finished. Our course is finished. And
then we can sync our database with this
Prisma schema. So I will open my
terminal and inside of here I can run
PNPM dlx Prisma DB push. This will sync
our local Prisma schema with our remote
database. In this case Neon. I can also
head over to the Neon console. So
neon.te. And as you see if I go to the
tables we should have a new course
table. And this is empty but that's
fine. And then we can continue. I can
close the terminal. I don't need it
anymore. And then I want to allow users
in this case myself to create courses.
This means we want to open the explorer.
Then we want to go to the app folder to
the um admin folder to the courses uh
folder. And inside of here I want to
create a new route a create route. This
means a child folder. That's what we
want to create. And it will be called
create. Wow. Create create. Then in the
create folder let's create a page.tsx.
And inside of here, I want to create an
export default function. This will be
called course creation route or course
creation page.
And then we can just open it. Inside of
here, we can create a return statement
with a diff h1 and then hey, how are
you? If I save this and again go back,
then uh you will see that nothing
changes. But as you see, my site does
not work. That's because I want to
restart my deaf server with PNPM rundev.
And if we again go back and do a hard
refresh and click on create course, I
will get redirected and it says hey how
are you? But instead of rendering hey
how are you? I want to create a real
form a nice looking form so that the
user again in this case myself can
create a new course. So let's again go
back and let's start off fresh. I will
delete everything in the return
statement and I want to get started with
a cart or first of all on the top left
corner I want to render a link which
will say go back and then underneath
this link I will create my card and then
my form so um let's get started with
empty tags inside of here I want to uh
return a div then in the div I want to
get a link or the link component from
next/link as you all know the link needs
one property which is the href and this
will be equal equal to /admin/courses
because if the user clicks on this link
I will redirect the user back to the
admin courses page. Then inside of here
I want to just render an icon which will
be the arrow left icon imported from
lucid react. Also we can give it a class
name which will be size four width four
and height four. Of course this link
should be styled exactly the same as a
sh CN button. This means we can give it
a class name which will be equal to
button variance. Button variance is
imported from the components. We can
invoke it and I want to also give it two
properties. This means I can structured
and for the variant this will be equal
to outline. And then for the size this
will be equal to icon because this is
the size of icon. And if you for example
open the button component itself then
you will find the size object default SM
LG and icon. These are all of the
varants and in this case we are using
the icon size which means it's very
simple. It's just size 9 width 9 and
height 9 nothing else. So I can again
close this we are finished I think
because if I again go back yeah this
looks beautiful. Next to the link I want
to render an H1. So I will go underneath
the link and inside of here I want to
say create courses. Of course we want to
style this H1. So let's give it a class
name and this will be text to Excel and
then font bold. As you see this looks
quite nice but this is not aligned
correctly. Currently this is aligned as
flex column but this should be aligned
as flex row. This means horizontally. So
for this div which wraps the link and H1
we can give it a class name and this
will be flex items which will be center
and gap four. As you see this already
looks way better. Then underneath this
header, if you want to call it like
that, I want to get started with the
form. This means I want to stay in the
empty tags, but I want to go underneath
the div and then I want to get the card
component from the components. Then
let's also get the card header from the
components and in the cart header I will
get the card title. In the card title,
uh we will render basic information. H
very nice. And as you see, yeah, this
looks quite good. If I zoom out a bit,
nothing changes. And that's great. Then
underneath the card title, let's also
get the card description. And for the
card description, I will say provide
basic information about the course. Then
underneath the card header, I want to
get started with the card content. And
in the cart content, we will render our
big nice form. So here's the thing. I
want to implement client side
validation. Client side validation means
if a user clicks on submit without
filling out all of the info, we will
throw errors and it will say uh this
input is not filled out or it's not
filled out correctly. This is client
side validation. Now there are a lot of
ways to implement client side
validation. Again there are easy ways,
good ways, bad ways, hard ways, a lot of
ways to implement client side validation
or others in other words form
validation. So I created a very nice
video on form validation. So I have to
find it myself right here. The best way
to handle form validation in X.js. And
this is literally the best way. And the
best way is to use React Hook Form. And
React Hook Form allows you to create
performant, flexible and extensible
forms with easy to use validation. And
since it uses sort in the background or
since we will use sort in the
background, it will also allow us to
implement serverside validation. And
here's the thing, implementing react
hook form is quite easy, but we want to
combine it with shad and UI. And doing
it natively is quite annoying, but
thankfully shadi has our back since it
has a react hook form component. So it
allows us to build forms with react hook
form and sort. So what exactly is this
form component? Or in other words, why
do we need it? Well, forms are tricky.
Yes, they are really tricky and they are
also one of the most common things you
will build in a web application. And
well-designed forms are well structured,
easy to use and navigate, accessible,
and they have support for client and
serverside validation. And what exactly
does the form component give us? Well,
the form component is a wrapper around
the React hook form library. And it
provides a few things. First of all,
composible components for building
forms. A form field component for
building controlled form fields. It uses
sort for form validation. It handles
accessibility and error messages. This
means we don't have to create this
turnary to render the error messages. No
shy and UI does everything for us. It
uses React use ID for generating unique
IDs. It applies the correct area
attributes and a lot of other cool
stuff. So in general, it's just a easy
to use wrapper around Zot and React took
form and it's great for form validation.
So the first step is to create a form
schema with Zord. Again you can also use
a different validation library but Z is
in most cases or pretty much a industry
standard. So again with Zord we will
create rules. Then we will take our form
data and validate it with the sort
schema. If the validation is okay, if
everything works out, then we won't
throw any errors. But if for example,
right here we have a username. If the
username or if the form data which we
provide does not have a username, then
we will throw an error. If the username
has length which is bigger than 50, we
will throw an error. So we want to first
of all create a z schema. This means I
want to open my codebase and I want to
go into the lip folder and here I will
create the zot schema itself. So we want
to create a zot schemas.ts file because
we will create multiple z schemas. So
let's start with the course schema
itself. So I want to create an export
constant. This will be called course
schema and this will be equal to
z.object.
As you see z is not imported. So on top
I want to say import. Then we can
destructure it and this will be from
zot. Then where I destruct I want to get
z or not z but z itself. So z do.object
and then I can destructure and inside of
here I want to provide all of my fields.
So what we can do is open our schema
again and we can put it right here to
the left side. Then what fields do we
have? We have an ID but I don't need it
for my form. Then we have a title. I
will copy the title and paste it right
here. This title will be equal to Z dot
string. I can invoke it and I want to
also implement further validation. This
means dot minimum will be three a
minimum three characters and then also
dot maximum and in this case a maximum
of 100 characters. So the title has to
be defined. It has to be a string and it
has to have a few characters but it
shouldn't be too big. That's why we have
this maximum. Then we also have a
description. I can copy it, paste it and
this will be equal to Z dot string and
then again further validation with dot
min and this will be three. So a minimum
character length of three. I won't give
it a maximum. I don't need it. But if
you want to you could for example add a
maximum of 2,500 characters. I think
this is a good maximum. Then we have a
file key. I will copy it, paste it and
this will be equal to Z.string. And then
also again further validation dot
minimum one. Then after the file key we
have a price. So I will copy it and
paste it. And this will be equal to Z
dot number. I can invoke it. And then I
want to add further validation in this
case minimum one because I don't want to
add or allow the user to create free
courses only paid courses. And that's
why I need a minimum of $1. And here's a
very interesting thing. So once we
create our form we will um create all of
the inputs. So for the price we will
create an input and we will give it a
type which will be number. So a user
will for example add a number which will
be $500 $500. And in most cases you
would probably think that this will be
of type number. But here's the thing
form inputs always return strings. But
my price has to be a number. So we will
get errors and I don't want to get
errors. This means we have to coers the
number. So in front of this Z dot number
or in front of this number method I can
get the coers method. I don't have to
invoke it or anything like that. So this
price will be Z. Coerc number dot
minimum one. So it will take the string
which the form data gives us and it will
convert it into a number. Then we have
our duration. I will copy it paste it
and again Z.co because I want to convert
the string into a number dot number. I
can invoke it. And then also I want to
add further validation. This means dot
minimum one and then also dot maximum
and for the maximum I will say 500. So a
maximum of 500 hours. Then we also have
a level which I can copy and paste right
here. And the level is interesting
because this level isn't a string. The
level is an enum. This means we only
have three options. So I can go above
this export constant course schema. And
I want to create a new export constant.
This will be called course levels and
this will be equal tune array and inside
of here I can just copy first of all
beginner paste it then a comma then I
can copy intermediate again a string
paste it and then I can copy advanced
add a string and paste it so this is our
new array course levels then for this
level itself this will be equal to zen
enum because we have an enum and as an
argument I want to provide the course
levels itself so this array which I just
created. As you see, I get an error and
this error is quite big. What we have to
do is just mark this as constant and
this will fix this error and we are
finished. Then what else do we have? We
have our level. The next thing is our D
category. I can copy it, paste it and
this will be equal to Z dot string. I
want to invoke it. Then we also have a
small description. I will copy it, paste
it. This will be also equal to Z dot
string. I can invoke it for the small
description. I want to also add further
validation. This means dot minimum. This
will be three and then dot maximum which
will be 100. So a maximum of 100
characters maybe 200. Yeah, I think 200
will be even better. So a maximum of 200
characters. Then I also have a slug. I
will copy paste it. And this will be of
type Z. And also further validation this
means dot minimum three. And then what
else do we have? We also have a status.
So I will copy it, paste it. And again
this isn't a string. This is an enum.
This means above the core schema we can
create a new array. So export constant
this will be course status. And then
this will be equal to an array. Again we
have three different statuses. So first
of all draft I will copy it. I will add
a string and paste it. Then published I
can copy it again create a string and
paste it. and then archived which means
I can copy it. Create a string and don't
paste it. No, I'm joking. Paste it. Of
course. So, we have our core status. We
can also mark it as constant again to
not get any errors. And then for the
status, this will be equal to Z. ENAM. I
want to invoke it. And as an argument, I
will pass the core status. So, is there
anything else missing? If I again go
back, status is finished. User relation,
we don't need that. Yeah, I think that's
already it. Now we will use the default
errors but they aren't that nice. So for
example for the minimum I can add a
comma open an object and then give it a
message and this is what will be
rendered if we have an error. This means
if the user creates a input which is
smaller than three characters and for
the message I want to say title must be
at least three characters long. We can
do the same thing for the maximum. So
again a comma an object we can get the
message and this will be equal to title
must be at most 100 characters long dot
dot dot. So as you see adding your own
error messages is very easy and to not
bore you I will just copy paste these
error messages. You can just use AI to
create your own ones. So for the
description I want to also use this dot
minimum three and for the message
description must be at least three
characters long. Then I want to do the
same thing for my file key. So minimum
one. And then for the message file is
required. Then we also have the price as
mentioned the price will be at least
minimum one. And then for the error
message I want to say price must be a
positive number. Then for the duration
again we have a minimum and maximum. So
for the minimum I want to render an
error message which will say duration
must be at least 1 hour and then for the
maximum I will paste it and this will be
500 and duration must be at most 500
hours. Then we also have our level and
adding error messages here is also very
simple. Again add a comma open an object
and then you have access to the message
property and for the value this will be
level is required. Then for the category
I will skip it for now. I want to update
it later on because I want to create an
enum later on. And then for the small
description for the minimum three the
error message will be small description
must be at least three characters long.
And for the maximum this will be 200
again. So small description must be at
most 200 characters long. Then for the
slug this will be slug must be at least
three characters long. And for the
status again we can add a comma. open an
object get the message property and then
this will be equal to um I don't know
status is required yeah I think this is
fine enough so we created our own custom
error messages we created these two
arrays which means I can use the sort
schema to create the form itself so we
can go back to the creation route and we
want to first of all set up react hook
form so what we can do is head over to
the documentation we are finished with
step number one. This means to create a
Z schema. The next step is to define a
form. Use the use form hook from React
hook form to create a form. So form
schema, this is finished. And here they
have comments. Step one and step number
two. I will copy the step number one. I
will go back and then I want to paste it
above the return statement. So constant
form is equal to use form. Use form is
imported from react to form. And this
here is relatively interesting code.
Z.infer type of form schema. So what
they are trying to do right here is get
the types from the Z schema. That's why
they infer this form schema. But instead
of writing this annoying code, we can
infer it right in our Z schemas file. So
I want to go underneath the course
schema. And then we will create an
export type. This will be called course
schema type. And this will be equal to
Z.infer. infer then we want to add a
generic and inside of here type of um
what was it course schema so we just
created the same code right here z.infer
which means I can use this new type
course schema type and then I can delete
this set.infer infer and we will just
have a simple generic with the score uh
course schema type because if I hover
over course schema I get all of the
properties title description file key
and stuff like that. Then we also have a
resolver and this will be equal to z
resolver. Sadly it does not import for
me automatically. So I can create an
import statement and I will just copy
the import statement from the example
from the code uh from the documentation.
So I will paste it right here. And as
you see Zot resolver is imported from
hook form resolvers zot. Then as an
argument they provide the form schema
but we don't have a form schema but a
course schema. So I will copy it paste
it and we want to also import it. So
course schema and this is imported from
the z schemas file. And then if we
continue, we also have a default values
object. And this object sets the initial
state of our form fields when the
component first mounts. Each key then
corresponds to a form fields name and
its value is the default content for
that field. So since we currently don't
have any inputs, our default value will
be either an empty string or null. So I
can delete this username. We don't have
a username. And if I click on control
spacebar, I get all of my fields right
here. That's because we added this
course schema type generic. So I want
you first of all, for example, get my
title. This will be equal to an empty
string because we don't have a title. In
this case, it's pretty much undefined.
Then for the description, this will be
also an empty string. Then for the file
key, this will be an empty string. Then
for the price, since this is of type
number, this will be just zero. Then
also for the duration this will be zero.
Then for the level this will be equal to
beginner because we have to provide an
initial state. Then for the category
this will be for now an empty string.
Then I want to also provide the status
and this is an enum and the initial
state will be draft. And then we also
have a slug. This will be an empty
string. And also the small description
will be an empty string as a default
value. So what exactly is this code or
what do we do right here? This is a good
question. So first of all we have the
use form hook and this is provided by
react hook form. This is used to first
of all set it up. We need this use form
for the whole state management. Then we
pass a generic course schema type. This
provides the TypeScript typing for our
values as you see here and this also
ensures that our data is consistent. And
then we have this resolver which is
equal to zot resolver and as an argument
we provide the core schema. So this
connects react hook form to uh zot
itself and we pass the core schema
because we want to specifically validate
this one schema. So zot resolver says
hey we use zot and then the core schema
just says hey this is the schema itself.
You want to validate the form data
against the schema. That's it. As you
see it's quite simple. Then what's the
second step? The second step is to
define the onsubmit handler or the
submit handler itself. This means I can
copy this function and I want to paste
it underneath this constant form. And as
you see do something with the form
values inside of here. And this will be
type safe and validated. So if this
console locks then this means that
everything was successful. If this does
not console lock then this means we had
some sort of error and it will render a
client side validation error for the
input itself. So if code runs inside of
here, then this means that client side
validation was successful. And since we
already set up React took form, we can
get started with the form. Also, I
currently get one error here for
Z.infer. As you all know, instead of
using Z.infer, we can use our course
schema type which is already imported.
So I want to scroll a bit to the bottom
and I want to go into the card content
and create the form. So we want to get
started with the form component itself.
This is imported from the components and
in the form we want to also spread our
form itself. So this constant which we
just created we want to spread it. So in
the form itself as you see the form
still complains and that's because it's
missing children. So in the form I want
to then render a standard form element.
We can delete the action. We don't have
one right now. And for the form, I will
also give it a class name which will be
space Y6. This means I want to give the
children a bit of spacing. Also, since
we already have an onsubmit function, I
can give the form also an onsubmit
handler. And this will be equal to
form.andsubmit.
And as an argument, I want to provide
the onsubmit function.
We use this form.andsubmit to validate
the data. And then this onsubmit. This
means if everything was successful then
we will call the onsubmit function and
that's why it will only run if
everything has been validated because if
our form values uh haven't been
validated correctly on the client side
then this onsubmit function won't be
called. It will first of all validate
everything and then the function will be
called and then as a next step I want to
create the form itself. This means all
of the inputs. So if you go back to the
documentation, you will see that they
provide us with a form field component
and this will allow us to then create
the input. So we can go back. I want to
go uh inside of here and I want to get
the form field component from the
components. This is self-closing and
then for the form field we have to
provide three properties. First of all
control and this will be equal to
form.cont control. Then we have to also
provide a name. In this case, this will
be our title. And then the third
property is the render property. And
this will define the UI for the field.
This means inside of here, we want to
create an inline callback function and
then just return it. And then in the
params, I can also the structure and get
the field itself. I will explain
everything in a second. Let's first of
all create the code. Then inside of here
in this render prop function, I want to
get the form item component from the
components. And in the form item we will
get the form label. This is imported
from the components. And here I can say
title because this will be our title. I
also misspelled it. So title. And then
underneath the form label I want to get
the form control component from the
components. Then in the form control I
want to get the input component which is
imported from the components. This is
self-closing. And for the input I want
to provide a placeholder. Inside of here
we can say title. This is the
placeholder itself. And then also I have
to pass my field right here. This means
I can just spread my field with these
three dots. So dot dot dot field. And
then underneath the form control, I want
to also get the form message component.
If there's a client side validation
error, then this form message will be
rendered. So an error message. So how
exactly does this code work? Well, we
first of all have a form field
component. This is a controller
component from react hook form. It
orchestrates yeah fancy word it creates
orchestrates whatever um the state
management for our input. So for this
title input then as you see we have a
control property and this is equal to
form control. This connects the field to
the main form instance which we just
created with this use form hook. So it's
the connector. We have to connect our
state to our UI itself. Then we have a
name property and this assigns the name
title to the field because again as you
know we have a few fields title
description file key whatever and we
have to directly connect our form our UI
to the state management and the unique
value is our title which means I have to
also provide for the name our title.
Then we also have a render prop function
and inside of here this renders the UI
as you see. Then in this render prop
function we render the form item. The
only interesting thing is this for
message component. So this will be
rendered automatically or it will
automatically display validation error
messages specifically for the title. If
there's no validation error then nothing
will be rendered. If there is a
validation error then this component
will be rendered with the custom error
message which we defined here and also
as you see we structure this field
property here. This is an object and
this object contains everything that we
need to make this input controlled
because sh or not shnui react to form
works with controlled inputs. This means
you have a default value and then a
value itself. you control the input and
this field has all of the data which we
need. So it includes for example a value
on change on blur and the ref and stuff
like that. So it's required to pass it
here in the input. You could also for
example instead of spreading it give the
input a value and then this would be
equal to field do value. This works but
it's just easier to spread the field so
that we don't have to write everything
by ourselves. Then if I go back and do a
hard refresh, we should also see our
form here. But we get an error. The
export use form was not found in module.
Did you mean to import set? What? What's
the problem? Well, we use React hook
form. React hook form creates
interactivity. It uses the use state
hook, the use ref hook. And what do we
do if we need interactivity? Well, we
mark the component with the use client
directive. This means if I mark this
page with use client and go back and as
you see we have a nice label title and
then this input with a placeholder I can
write something inside of here create an
input and as you see currently there's
no validation but that's because there's
no onsubmit button currently we will
render it later on and then validation
will also work. So as a next step I want
to continue with this sluck generation
thingy. So we will render an input and
next to the input we will have a button.
If the user clicks on the generate
button we will take the title input and
we will generate the slug from this
title input. This means we want to
create a flex layout. So underneath the
form item we can create first of all a
div. This will be the wrapper between
our input and then the button. And this
will have a class name which will be
flex and then gap 4. And inside of this
div, I want to first of all again get my
form field. So to save a bit of time, I
can just copy the old form field and
paste it inside of here. So for the
name, this won't be title anymore, but
instead slug. Then for the form label,
this will be slug. And for the input
placeholder, this will be sluck. Who
would have thought? Then we can
continue. And underneath this form
field, I want to render a button. So
this generate button. So what component
do we want to use? We want to get the
button component from the components.
And then for the value, how about we say
generate sluck. And then maybe also a
nice looking icon. So after this text, I
will get the sparkles icon from Lucid
React. This is self-closing. And then
for the class name, this will be margin
left one. And also I will give it a size
property and this will be 16. So you can
either give it a class name with a size
or you can give the icon natively a
size. It does not really matter. The end
result is exactly the same. This means
if I again go back.
Yeah, this is quite ugly. The sluck
should or this input should take almost
the whole width. I mean the button
should take the width that it needs but
the input should take the rest of the
width. And also this alignment is not
correct. Currently it's aligned like
flex start but I want to align it flex
end because this should be aligned to
the bottom. This means we can go back.
Then we want to go first of all to the
div. This will be items and to align it
to the bottom. Then for the form itself
I can give the form item a class name
and this will be with full. This should
already fix a lot of things. Yes, that's
already way better. But currently this
generate sluck button does not work.
This means we can go back and then for
the button I can first of all give it a
type. This will be button and this is
super important because if I don't give
it the type button it will try to submit
the form. It will function like type
submit. Therefore please mark it as type
button. Then I want to also give it a
class name width fit. So it will only
take the width that it needs to take.
And then we want to use the on click
handler because we want to take the
title and convert it into a slug. This
means this will be an inline callback
function or an arrow function. And
inside of here we want to first of all
get the title value. This means constant
title value. And this will be equal to
form.get
values and I want to get the title
value. We can click on control spacear
as you see type safety and I want to get
the title. This means if I type or if I
say hello for the title then this is now
our title value and I want to take this
title value and convert it into a slug.
Now we could do it natively. It would
work and that's also something which I
would recommend. The only reason why we
won't do it natively is because you have
to create a lot of waxes. So that's why
we will use in this video the slugify
package. So the slugify package just uh
is just a function which you can invoke
and then as an argument you pass some
string and this slugify function then
creates a slug uh from this provided
string. So we can copy the name slugify
and then I will open my terminal. I will
stop the dev server and I will paste it
inside of here. This means pnpmi
slugify. Once installed I can restart my
def server with pnpm rune defaf and then
on the top I can import sllugify. This
means uh underneath this input for
example I will create an import
statement. Then this will be slugify
from slugify. Then I can again scroll to
the bottom. I want to copy the name
slugify. And then for the on click
handler we can create a constant. This
will be slug and this will be equal to
slugify. I want to invoke it. And as an
argument I will provide the title value.
Since we now get our slug, we can also
set our form value. This means I can go
underneath the slug and I want to get my
form dot set value and I want to set the
value for my slug. Then as a second
argument I want to pass slug and then I
want to also add a comma open an object
and we can get the should validate
property. Here we can set hey should the
form should react hook form validate
this input or not. We want to validate
it. So I will set this to true and this
should already work. So I can go back
and I can do a hard refresh. And if I
say for the title, for example, hello,
how are you? 1 2 3 and click on generate
slug, it will generate a nice looking
slug right here as you see. So this
works exactly as wanted, which means we
can continue with the small description.
So we can scroll to the bottom. We want
to go underneath the button, underneath
the div, but we want to stay in the
form. Then we want to again use the form
field component which means I can just
copy it and again paste it right here.
Then we want to update the name instead
of slug this will be small description.
Then form item this is fine. For the
form label I want to say small
description. Then for the form control
instead of rendering an input I want to
get the text area component. For the
placeholder I will say small
description. then spreading the field
that's fine but we can also add a class
name and this will be minimum height of
custom value 120 pixels and as you see
this is our small description I can also
input something for the description and
it looks beautiful what's the next value
or what's the next input well the next
input will be our rich text area this
means the big description so we can
again go back I can copy this form field
paste it down below one more time. Then
for the value or for the name this will
be big description. So standard
description. For the form label I will
just say description. Then we will for
now leave this text area component here.
But later on I will create a real rich
text editor. And then for the class name
and stuff like that. This is fine. Then
we can continue with the image uploader
itself. So we can go underneath this
form item again copy paste it. Then for
the name this will be file key. For the
form item this is fine. For the form
label I will render thumbnail image. And
then instead of rendering a text area I
want to render an input which is already
imported. We can delete the class name.
We won't need it. And this is fine
enough. H the description. This should
be thumbnail URL. Again I will update it
later on but for now this is fine
enough. we want to later on create a
real drag and drop zone. Then the next
section is a selector for my category,
for the level, for the status, duration,
stuff like that. This means we want to
go underneath this form item or form uh
field. And I want to create a grid
layout. This means let's get a div
element and let's give it a class name.
This will be grid grid columns of one
for a mobile screen. And then on MD or
bigger, this will be grid columns two.
and gap four to have some spacing inside
of here. I want to again render a form
field. So I can just copy this and paste
it inside of here. And this form field
will be for the category. This means for
the name I want to get the category for
the form label instead of saying
thumbnail image this will be a category.
And then for the value itself or for the
form control I want to create a select
element. But here's the thing to create
a select element we want to also map
over items. This means over our
categories. And what I will do is go to
the Z schemas and create a new array.
And we will then map over this array. So
we can create an export constant. This
will be course categories. And this will
be equal to an array. Inside of here I
will just create a lot of strings. This
means the first category could be
development. Then a second one could be
for example business. Then how about
finance? Yeah, finance courses are
always great. You know, buy some stons.
Then what else? How about IT and
software? That's what we do. Then how
about office productivity? Then I want
to also have personal development. Then
also design. We all love design.
Marketing is also a great category. So I
want to create about 10 categories. Then
maybe health and fitness. They always
make money, so why not? then also music
because we all love music and then also
teaching and academics. So now I've
created all of these categories here. As
you all know we want to also mark this
as const so as a constant and then I
want to also update my course schema
because currently the category is set to
z.string but this should now be an enum.
This means what I can do is delete this
um zstring. I don't need it anymore and
instead this will be a Zen enum as an
argument. I want to provide the course
categories and then I want to also
display an error message. This means we
can add a comma an object. Then we can
get the message property and this will
be equal to um category is required. So
this is already enough which means I can
go back to the creation route. I want to
first of all again update my default
values. This means for the category
instead of passing an empty string this
will be equal to damn what's a good
category how about health and fitness
why not and then we can again scroll to
the bottom and I want to map over my
items so I can delete the input since we
won't render the input anymore and
instead I want to create a select
element or I want to use the select
component we can also delete the form
control and we will just have a form the
form item component then this form label
And then underneath the form label I
want to get the select component from
the components folder. For the select we
have to provide two key properties.
First of all on value change which will
be equal to field do onvalue or dot
onchange and then also default value
which will be equal to field dot value.
So here's the thing in for our input we
just spread our field. But this does not
work for the select and that's why we
have to specifically define the on value
change and default value. Then in the
select I want to get the form control
component which is already imported. And
inside of here we can get the select
trigger from the components. The select
trigger is what the user will click.
Then for the select trigger I want to
provide a class name which will be width
of full. And then inside of here we want
to get a select value which is imported
from the components. This is
self-closing and inside of here we have
to give it a placeholder and the
placeholder will just be select
category. So this is what the user will
see. Then we also need the select
content. This means we can go underneath
the select trigger underneath the form
control but still in the select itself
and I want to get the select content
again from the components and inside of
here I can map over my categories. This
means I can get the course categories
from the Zot schemas file dot map. We
want to use the map method as a param.
We can get the category itself. And then
we can just return it. Inside of here,
we need the select item which is
imported from the components. And this
select item needs two properties. First
of all, we map over an array. What does
this mean? Well, the child needs a
unique key. A unique key could be the
category itself because each value is
unique. And then we have to also provide
a value itself. And the value will be
equal to category. And then in the
select item itself, I can just render
the category. This means if we again go
back, you will see the title, the slug,
the small description, the big
description, the thumbnail URL, and then
the selector where the user can then
select a category. And as a default if I
do a hard refresh health and fitness is
selected. So the next form field will be
rendered on the right side. And this
will be for the level. This means we can
go back. We can again copy this form
item. So I will draw form field I will
copy it. Then I will paste it down below
but still in this div. Then for the name
instead of category this will be level.
Then for the form label this will be
uppercase level. For the onv value
change and default value, we don't have
to update anything. For the select
value, instead of instead of saying
select category, I want to say select
value. And then instead of mapping over
the categories, I want to map over the
course levels. This is imported from the
Z schemas file. And this should already
be it. This means if I again go back and
do a hard refresh, right here we have
our category. And here we have our
level. And as a default, beginner is
selected. But if I select intermediate,
it of course updates. Then what's the
next input? Well, the next input will be
the duration. This means I want to again
just copy not this form uh field, but
instead a form field with a standard
input. I will copy this one with the
thumbnail URL. And then I want to go
underneath our last form field and paste
it right here. For the name, this won't
be file key, but instead duration. Then
for the form label instead of thumbnail
image this will be duration and then in
parentheses hours. Then for the
placeholder instead of thumbnail URL
this will be duration uppercased. And
then I want to also give it a type and
the type will be number. So this should
already be it. This means if I go back
yes this looks nice and I can also up
right here add a number. Then the next
input will be for the price. This means
we can go back. I will copy this form
field and paste it down below one more
time. So we want to update the name.
Instead of duration, this will be price.
For the form label, instead of saying
duration, I want to say price. And
again, I want to get my parentheses and
render a dollar symbol because the user
should uh input a price in dollars. Then
for the input, the placeholder should
say price for the type number is fine.
And this means if I again go back, yeah,
this looks beautiful. And then we are
almost finished and there's only one
more input or you could say select which
is missing and that's the status
selector. This means I can go back and I
want to copy a form field with the
select already implemented. So I will
copy this level form field. I want to
again scroll to the bottom and we want
to go underneath this div. Still we want
to stay in the form but underneath this
grid div. I can then again paste what I
just copied and we have to update the
properties. So instead of saying level
this will be status. This means for the
name. Then for the form label instead of
level this will be status. The on value
change and default value is fine. We
don't have to update anything. Then for
the select value in the trigger this
will be yeah select status I think uh
will be a bit better. And then for the
select content, I don't want to map over
the levels, but instead over the course
status, which is imported from the Zot
schemas file. This means if we go back,
we now have a status selector right
here. And the default selection is draft
as you see here. Then the last thing
which we need is a submit button. This
means we can go back. We can go
underneath this form field and I want to
get the button component from the
components and as a value I will just
say create course and also maybe an icon
could look quite nice. So let's get the
plus icon from lucid react this is
self-closing and for the class name this
will be margin left one also I want to
give it a size and this will be 16. And
if I again go back yeah this looks
absolutely beautiful. So I will zoom out
a bit because I'm very zoomed in. We
have a nice sidebar and then this is the
main content. I can go back to the admin
courses page with this button. Then this
is the form in a cart. We have a title
input. We have a slug input. I can
generate a slug as you see here. We have
a small description, a big description,
a thumbnail image, category level,
duration, price, and status. And of
course this nice looking button. But
currently nothing really works. We don't
have any mutation layer. And also I
don't want to render a text area for the
description. No, this should be a real
rich text editor. And instead of
rendering this uh thumbnail URL input,
we want to render a real drag and drop
zone. So I want to start with the rich
text editor. Then we will continue with
the uh drag and drop zone. Then we will
implement the mutation slayer. And then
I think we will be finished. So let's
start with the rich text editor. Yes. So
to create the rich text editor, we will
use tiptap in this video. And tip tap is
a headless and open-source editor
framework. So most solutions which you
will find on the internet will just be
pre-built components which are already
styled and stuff like that. That's
great. But I want to have a custom rich
text editor. And tip tap gives me the
ability to create my own custom rich
text editor because tip tap is
completely headless. It's not styled.
You style it yourself. It's also
completely open source and also free. I
know they have a paid tier that's if you
want to use some AI stuff and stuff like
that. But we don't need that. We will
just use the opensource editor which is
completely free to use. And again, it's
headless and it's super powerful. It's
in my opinion the best solution out on
the market to create a simple or not
even a simple an advanced rich text
editor. So what we can do is head over
to the documentation. And here they have
a little I guess getting started guide
where they explain what tip tap is and
how it works and stuff like that. We
don't need that. We want to get started
right away. So I want to click in the
navbar on all docs and then on editor
and then we can click on install and
then next.js. Also here's one thing
which I want to quickly mention as they
say on the top tip editor 3.0 beta is
out. Start here. When I'm recording this
video edit or tiptap 3.0 is still in
beta. It's not released. I tried out 3.0
but it still has a lot of bugs. That's
why I will use the stable version which
is right now 2 something. When you start
watching this video, it could be that
3.0 is already released to the public.
That's fine. I tested it out. The whole
integration is literally the same. They
just you could say they just updated
their back end to make everything
faster. But the integration is the same.
Everything one to one. This means we can
head over right here to this quick start
guide. The first step is to create a
project. We already did that a few hours
ago. And the next step is to install the
uh necessary dependencies. And here they
say, now that we have a standard boiler
plate setup, we can get Tiptap up and
running. For this, we will need to
install three packages. Tiptap React,
Tiptap PM, and Tiptap Starter Kit, which
includes all the extensions you need to
get started quickly. So, I can copy all
of these packages. the names. Then I
will go back. We can open the terminal
and then we can just run PNPMI and then
all of these packages again. Tiptap
React, Tiptap PM and Tiptap starter kit.
And then the next step is to integrate
Tiptap. So to start using Tiptap, you
will need to add a new component to your
app. So let's do that. We can open our
explorer. Then if I scroll to the
bottom, I have my components here. And I
want to create a new subfolder. This
will be the rich-ext-editor
folder. Then in the witch text editor
folder, I want to create a new file and
this will be editor.tsx.
And then in this editor.tsx, we will
integrate tip tap. So first of all, this
component uh has to be marked with the
use client directive because tip tap
needs a javascript bundle to function.
Then we want to export function. So
export function. This will be called
rich text editor and then I can just
open this function. So inside of here I
want to set up tip tap and to be
specific I want to create an editor
instance. This means we can create a
constant called editor and this will be
equal to use editor. As you see it does
not import for me automatically sadly.
This means I will have to do it
manually. On top I can create an import
statement. I can destructure it and this
will be from at tipt tab/react
then where I structure it I can get the
use editor hook and then I can invoke it
and the structured inside of here we
have to provide one key property and
that's the extensions array inside of
here I can define extensions so for
example if I head over back to the
documentation we installed a tip tap
starter kit this is one key extension
which um allows ows us or which includes
all the extensions you need to get
started quickly. So this extension is
like the base layer. It gives us
everything we need to get started to
create a simple rich text editor.
Nevertheless, we will configure tip tab
later on even further. We will add more
extensions. But for now, the starter kit
is already enough. This means on top I
can create an import. Uh I want to
import the starter kit and this will be
from at tiptap/starter
kit. Then I can just paste it into this
array and then we are already finished.
So right here we created an editor
instance and it's now time to also
create the UI. So here's the thing. Um I
want to create a little diagram. How
will our rich text editor look like?
Well, we will have this box, I guess,
and this box will consist of two parts.
First of all, something which you call a
menu bar. In the menu bar, we will
render multiple buttons. A button, for
example, to toggle an H1, then a button
to toggle an H2, a button to toggle the
alignment, so left or the center or to
the right, then a button to create an
underline and stuff like that. That's
what you call a menu bar. And then
underneath the menu bar, we will create
the editor content. And this is like
this big text editor where the user will
create his content. So, hey yo, what's
up? Welcome to my course. Buy it now.
Super cool content. So, as you see two
parts, a menu bar and then the editor
itself. So, I want to start with the
menu bar which means we can create a
return statement. I want to return a div
and then in the div, I want to first of
all render the menu bar. So I will
create a separate component for that. So
in the rich text editor I want to create
a new file and this will be the menu
bar.tsx file. Since this is a component
we can create an export function and
this will be menu bar. I can then open
it and inside of here I want to create a
return statement. And for now I can
return an H1 which says hello um from
the menu bar. If I save this and again
go back, I can just get the menu bar in
this editor component. So menu bar, my
god, menu bar. This is self-closing and
this is finished. So if I save this and
again go back and do a hard refresh, we
won't see this rich text editor. That's
because this editor is not rendered in
our creation route. Currently, we render
this uh big text area. I want to change
that. So uh we have to again scroll to
the top. Here I have my description. I
can comment out this text area for now.
And instead I want to get my editor from
uh my components or how did I call it?
Which text editor? Not editor but which
text editor. And this is imported from
the components and this is self-closing.
If I again go back. Yeah, this is very
beautiful. No, it's not. So we can start
h get started first of all with our menu
bar. And here's the thing. The menu bar
needs the editor instance to function.
This means I can create an interface on
the top and so interface and I will call
it I props because I love the name. I
don't know why. And inside of here I
want to get an editor and this editor
will have a type. The type will be
editor and this type is imported from
tip tap react. I can import it. Uh it
does not do it automatically. So quick
fix import. And I want you also say
import type. I don't want to import the
editor itself but just the type. And the
thing is this editor could be defined or
it could be null. That's why I want to
use this or sign. So either we have an
editor or we don't pass anything which
means null. Then I can get this editor
through my params. So I can destructure
it. This will be of type I props. And
then where I destructure it I can get my
editor. Then above this return statement
I want to create an if statement. And I
want to check if we get an editor. This
means if we don't have an editor, you
can do that with this exclamation mark.
Then we will just return null. This
means we won't return anything. But if
we have an editor, well then we can
create this main uh return. So I will
start off with a new fresh return.
Inside of here, I want to return a div.
And then in this div, as mentioned, I
want to create many buttons to be
specific many toggles. So inside of here
I want to first of all get the tool tip
provider. So it's imported from the
components. Then I can open it. And what
exactly is this tool tip provider? So we
can head over back to the shad CN UI
website. And if I search for tool tip
then you will find this section. So tool
tip a pop-up that displays information
related to an element when the element
receives keyboard focus or the mouse
hovers over it. So later on as mentioned
we will display multiple buttons. H1,
H2, H3, uh center, alignment, stuff like
that. But these are just icons. They
won't have any text. So the button won't
display any text. It will only display
icons. And to give the user more
information, I want to render a tool tip
so that if the user hovers over this
button, there will be a text which will
say H1 or text center or text left and
stuff like that. That's why we have to
or I want to use the tool tip. This
means I can go back and then in the tool
tip provider I want to create a diff and
in this div I want to get my tool tip.
This tool tip is imported from the
components and then in the tool tip I
want to get a tool tip trigger. So this
is what the user will click tool tip
trigger. This is imported from the
components and then in the tool tip
trigger I want to create a toggle or
render a toggle. So again we can head
over to SH CN UI and if you search for
toggle then you will find this. So a
toggle is a two-state button that can be
the uh can be either on or off. So if I
click on this button then the toggle is
on. If I again click on it then it's
off. So the reason why we will use this
toggle is because if a user for example
selects H1 so this button then I want to
show this active state and a toggle
works great for that. A button could
also do the same thing. We could also
showcase an active state, but it's just
easier to create with this toggle and
that's why I will use it. So I can go
back and then in the tool tip trigger I
want to get the toggle component from
the components. Also since this is a
component in the tool uh tool tip
trigger I have to also give it an as
child property. So an as child property
for the tool tip trigger and then I in
the toggle itself I want to render the
bolt icon. The bolt icon is imported
from Lucid React and it's self-closing.
And then we can also test it out. So if
I go back, huh, where's my toggle? I
don't see anything. There's just this
label. What's the problem? Well, again,
right here, we created an if statement.
If we don't get an editor, then we don't
return anything. And if I go to my
editor, I have to pass this editor
instance for my or to my menu bar. This
means in my menu bar, I can click on
control spacebar. I get the editor prop
and this will be equal to the editor.
This means if I go back to the menu bar,
there's no error here. And if I go back,
you will see this toggle. And if I click
on the toggle, nothing happens. But
that's because we have to control it. So
I can go back and I want to update this
toggle. First of all, I want to give it
a size property. I want this toggle to
be small. So the size will be SM. Then I
have to use two properties again. I want
to control it. This means this will be
the pressed property. And then also the
unpressed change. For the pressed this
will be equal to editor do is active and
this is active is a function which we
have to invoke and I want to check for
the bold state. So pressed will be true
if bold is active. So at the end of the
day again this editor is our editor
instance and we check if bold is active.
If so this will return as true which
means pressed will be true. And then of
course since this is a controlled input
we have to also listen for the on press
change because we want to then update
our state our editor instance. So this
is an inline callback function and then
I want to get my editor. I want to call
the chain method. I can invoke it. Then
I want to get the focus method. I want
to invoke it. And then I want to call
the toggle bolt method because we want
to toggle bolt. Again, we can invoke it.
And then it's very important that you
call the run method at the end because
without the run method, this won't run.
Who would have thought? So if I save
this and go back, you will see for now
nothing really changes. So I can go back
and then I want to also add a class
name. So for the toggle I can create a
class name and then uh I want to get the
CN helper function because I want to
create dynamic styles and we can invoke
it and inside of here I want to create a
turnary pretty much. So if this editor
is active is true then I want to change
the background color and the text color.
So we can say if or I can just copy it.
this editor is active bold. I will copy
it, paste it inside of here. And if it's
true, then we can use this double and
sign. And I want to render BG muted for
the background color and text muted
foreground so that the text color is a
bit more grayish. This means if we again
go back, you will now see this toggle is
active. We have a background color and
the icon is also muted. If I again click
on the toggle, this active state is
removed. So this works exactly as
expected. But as mentioned, I want to
also implement this tool tip. Currently,
if I hover over this uh button, nothing
happens. This means we can go back and
we want to go underneath the tool tip
trigger because we defined the tool tip
trigger and we want to get the tool tip
content. So underneath the tool tip
trigger, I want to get the tool tip
content component which is imported from
the components. And inside of here, I
want to say bold because if the user
clicks on the button, I will showcase a
bold state. So if I go back and hover
over it, you see on the top corner bold.
In theory, you could also add a delay
and stuff like that. You can configure
this tool tip, but honestly, I think it
looks beautiful and I will leave it as
is. So what's the next toggle which I
want to render? Well, this will be
itallic. This means we can go back and
what we can do is just copy this tool
tip which we just created and I will
paste it down below. Please make sure
that it's pasted in the div. So we have
a diff and the tool tip provider
underneath this new tool tip. So tool
tip is fine, tool tip trigger is fine,
toggle is fine, size is fine for the
pressed property. We don't want you uh
listen for bold but instead for itallic.
As you see, we don't get any type
safety. So please make sure that you
spell it correctly. Also I don't want to
toggle bold but instead toggle itallic.
Also for the class name instead of
listening for the bold state we want to
listen for the italic state. Then for
the icon instead of bold I want to get
the italic icon from lucid react. And
then for the tool tip content this will
also be itallic. As you see this looks
quite good. Then what's the next toggle
which I want to render? Well, this is
the strike uh toggle. This means I will
again copy this tool tip. I will paste
it down below and then we can again
update it. So the size is fine for
pressed. Instead of listening for
italic, I want to listen for strike.
Then for the on pressed change, instead
of toggling itallic, I want to toggle
strike. Then for the class name, instead
of uh checking for italic, we want to
check or listen for strike. And instead
of rendering the itallic icon, we will
render the strike through icon imported
from Lucid React. And for the tool tip
content, this will be strike. So these
are already three toggles. As the next
step, I want to create the headings.
This means H1, H2, and I think also H3.
This means we can again copy this tool
tip. I will copy it and paste it down
below. Then for the toggle, the size is
fine. for pressed. I don't want to
listen for the strike anymore, but
instead for a heading. So, I can delete
strike. I will say heading. And here's
the thing. There's not only one heading,
but we have multiple headings. Level
one. This means H1, level two, H2, level
three, H3, and more. This means we can
add a comma, open an object, and pass a
level right here. And this will be one
because I want to listen for the heading
one H1. For the on press change instead
of toggle strike I want to use the
toggle heading method. So toggle heading
I can invoke it and then I can the
structure inside of here I have to pass
the level and the level will be one
again H1. And then for the class name I
can just copy this code and paste it for
the class name.
And then instead of rendering the strike
through icon, we can render the heading
one icon imported from Lucid React. And
for the tool tip I will say or for the
tool tip content, I will say heading
one. So if I again go back, you will see
yeah this looks absolutely beautiful.
Also currently the gap is horrendously
bad. Don't worry, I will fix that later
on. For now, this is fine enough. So as
the next step, I want to render the
heading too. This means we can copy this
tool tip, paste it down below and then
we can update it. So size is fine. For
pressed this will be level two. For the
unpressed change this will be level two.
Then for the class name this will be
level two. And then for the heading or
for the icon this will be the heading
two icon. This time also imported from
lucid react. And for the tool tip
content this will also be heading two.
Then I want to render one more heading.
This will be heading three. This means I
can copy this tool tip, paste it down
below and then we can update the um
levels. So this will be level three.
This will be level three. Then this will
be level four. No, I'm joking. Level
three. For the icon, this will be
heading three icon. And then for the
tool tip content, this will be heading
five. No, heading three. So we have now
in total three headings. And as the next
step, I want to render a tool tip or a
button for a bullet list icon. This
means I can again copy this tool tip. I
want to paste it down below. And let's
start with the pressed um property. So I
don't want to uh listen anymore for a
heading but instead for a bullet list.
So I will remove this heading and
instead say bullet list. Again please
make sure that you don't misspell it.
And also bullet and then this L will be
uppercase. So bullet lowerase and then L
uppercased and then ST. So then for the
on press change instead of calling
toggle heading I want to instead call
toggle uh bullet list again we can
invoke it. Then for the class name I
want to copy bullet list and also paste
it inside of here. For the icon I want
to get the list icon. List icon is
imported from lucid react. And for the
tool tip content this will be also
bullet list. As you see, I get one error
for the class name and that's because I
have to of course render this in
strings. This means if I again go back,
I will get my bullet list right here.
And if I click on it, it's now active
and it works and looks beautiful. Then I
want to also create a button for the
ordered list. This means this is a
bullet list with dots and I want to
create an ordered list with these
numbers. So 1 2 3 and stuff like that.
This means we can go back. I will copy
this tool tip. I will paste it down
below again. And we want to first of all
update the pressed state. So instead of
listening for the bullet list, we will
listen for the order list. And again
ordered will be lowercased and then this
L will be uppercased. Ordered list. For
the on press change, we want to toggle
the ordered list method. So toggle
ordered list. Then for this class name
again we want to listen for the ordered
list. And then for the icon instead of
list icon this will be list order icon
imported from lucid react. And for the
tooltip content this will be ordered
list. So we are actually finished with
the basic buttons. So we have a bold
icon an italic button this strike button
h1 h2 h3 ordered list bullet list. It
looks great. But now I want to also
create buttons so that the user can
align his text. This means left, center
and right. So we can go back and then I
want to go underneath this div. So
underneath the tool tip and then
underneath this div and I want to create
another div. This div will be a
separator. This means we can give this
div a class name and this will be width
px. This means width 1 pixel height six
bg which will be border and then also
margin x2. This means if you again go
back then you will see this very light
border. But this kind of looks weird.
It's aligned um vertically as a column
but it should be aligned horizontally.
This means if we again go back how is
this created? We have a tool tip
provider and with what is everything
wrapped? Well, we have one main div.
This means I can update this div and
give it a class name or align it
horizontally. So for this div I can give
it a class name. This will be border
then border which will be input rounded
top which will be LG padding which will
be two bg card flex flex wrap. So if
there's no space horizontally anymore we
will wrap the children then also gap one
to have some spacing and items which
will be center. So as you see if I again
go back this is now aligned horizontally
and this already looks way better.
Nevertheless, this section, so again, if
I get uh my handy little line tool, this
section is too close to each other. I
want to also create a gap. This means we
can go back and this diff wraps all of
our tool tips. So I can give it a class
name and this will be also flex flex
wrap. So if there's no space, we will
wrap the children and then also gap one.
So if I again go back, yes, this looks
absolutely beautiful. So we have
finished with this side. We have a nice
separator and then we can continue with
the next section again the left
alignment, center alignment and right
alignment. So I want to go underneath
this div separator and I want to create
another div element. So since this will
again be a layout div. This means inside
of this div we will render or create
three buttons. We can give it a class
name which will also be flex flex wrap
and then gap one. inside of here. I want
to then create again my tool tip. This
means I can just copy the tool tip and
paste it inside of here. And we want to
again update our pressed state our on
press change uh function and stuff like
that. So this will be for the text
alignment to the left side. This means
for the press change instead of
listening for ordered list we want to
listen for text align. This means
instead of uh having strings right here
we can destructure it and we can get
text align. And then this will be equal
to left. For the on pressed change, I
don't want to toggle order list but
instead set text align. But I don't get
this method. What's the problem? Well,
as mentioned, if we go to the editor for
the extensions, we currently provide the
starter kit. The starter kit is a nice
starting point, but it does not give us
a lot. I mean, it g it gives us the base
functionality. So again H1 H2 this bold
state it gives us this base
functionality but it does not allow us
for example to configure this text
alignment. This is a new extension which
we will have to use. So we can head over
back to the documentation and inside of
here we can search for text align. Here
you will find the text align extension
and as you will see this extension adds
a text align attribute to a specified
list of nodes. The attribute is used to
align the text left center right. This
means we want to first of all install
this extension. I can copy the name and
then in my terminal I will stop my dev
server and then I will just install it.
Once installed we can restart our dev
server and then we want to first of all
import this extension. This means what I
will do is just go back into my editor
create an import statement. This will be
text align and this will be imported
from at tip tab extension text align.
Then in my extensions array I can add a
comma and I want to get my text align
extension which I just imported. So I
will paste it right here. And then I
want to also configure it. So I can use
this configure function. I want to
invoke it the structured. And inside of
here we have to provide types. So the
types where the text align attribute can
be applied. This types will be equal to
an array. And we want to apply text
align to our heading and then also to a
paragraph. So heading, and then
paragraph. This means we will apply it
to any text style. If the user selects
H1 or this H1 right here, then we will
still allow the user to align the text.
If the user does not select any heading,
then we will still allow the user to
align the text because this means then
that the input will be a paragraph. So
this is now finished. We aligned or we
configured text align which means if I
go back to my menu bar in theory I
should then also get a set text align
method. And that's exactly what I get.
And as you see I get an error. What's
the problem? Expected one argument but
got zero. What argument did it expect?
Well, it expected an argument for
alignment. And in this case, I want to
align the text to the left side. This
means I will say left. We want to still
call the one method. And then this is
already finished. Then we can update the
class name. This means I can just copy
this text align left the destruct
showing and I will paste it inside of
here. Then instead of rendering the list
order icon, we want to get the align
left icon from Lucid React. And instead
of saying all list, we want to say align
left. And then we can again copy this
tool tip, paste it down below. And this
will be for the alignment to the center.
This means for text align, this will be
center. For the on press change, this
will be center. Um I can also just copy
it. Then for the class name, this will
be center. For the icon, this will be
align center. And then for the text,
this will be align center. We can then
copy this tool tip one more time and
paste it down below. And this will be
for the alignment to the right side.
This means text align right. For the on
pressed change, this will be right. For
the class name, this will be center. No,
right. Then for the icon, this will be
align right. And then for the tool tip
content, this will be a line D right.
Yes, you are right. Wow, so many
rightes. And if I go back, you will see
right here these three buttons and they
look absolutely beautiful. So we have
finished with the main section. But
there are two more buttons which I want
to render and that's a button to how
would you call it undo your changes and
then redo your changes. So as you
probably know from Google Docs or word
or whatever you can always redo or undo
what you just created. This means we can
again go back. I want to first of all
again create the separator. This means
we want to go underneath the div but we
want to stay in the tool tip provider
and we want to create a new div. This
div will have a class name which will be
width px width 1 pixel height of six
then bg border and margin x2. Underneath
the separator div, we want to create a
new div. Let's give it a class name. And
again this will be this flex layout.
This means flex flex wrap and then gap
one. In this div, we want to again
create two tool tip trigger toggle
button thingies. This means I will copy
this tool tip and then I will just paste
it inside of here. And this tool tip or
you know what this button is very
interesting because I don't want to use
this toggle component anymore because if
a user for example undo his change then
there's no active state. The user just
clicks the button once and then the
change is undone. There's no active or I
guess inactive state. This means what I
will do is just delete everything in the
tool tip trigger. So we will leave the
as child property and then inside of
here I want to get the button component
from shad C or from our components. For
the button I want to first of all give
it a size property. This will be SM. For
the variant this will be ghost. So this
button will look exactly the same as a
toggle. Then for the type, this is very
important. This will be button. Again,
if you don't add a type of button, the
button will be treated like a submit
button. This means whenever you click on
this button, it will submit the form and
you don't want that. Then we want to
also use the onclick handler. And this
will be an inline callback function.
Then we want to get our editor instance.
I want to call the chain method, then
the focus method, then the undo method,
and then the run method. I know a lot of
chaining, but this will allow the user
to undo the changes. Then we can also
get the disabled state, and disabled
will be true if there's no content. I
mean, if the user did not make any
changes, then the user will also not be
able to undo his changes because there
are no changes. This means disabled will
be true if there's no exclamation. So
exclamation mark editor dot can this is
the method and then dot undo. So if the
user cannot make any undos then this
button will be disabled. My god this is
almost plain English. Wow. And then in
this button I want to get the undo icon.
This is imported from lucid react. And
for the tool tip content this will be
undo. This means if we again go back,
you will see this button and this is
disabled because I did not make any
changes. There's nothing to undo. So we
can go back. I can copy this tool tip
one more time the last time and paste it
down below. This will be for the redo
button. So the size is fine, the variant
is fine, the type is button. For the on
click handler, this will be redo instead
of undo. For the disabled state, this
will be also redo uh instead of undo.
And then for the icon, this will be redo
imported from Lucid React. And for the
tool tip content, this will be redo. And
if you go back, you will see this button
is also disabled because there's nothing
to redo. But once we create a bit of
content, we will be able to undo and
redo our changes. So the menu bar is
finished and we can continue with the
editor content itself. The editor
content is a component which we don't
have to create. This is a component
which is provided by um tip tap itself.
This means underneath the menu bar I
want to get the editor content and the
editor content is imported from tip tap
react. This is self-closing and the
editor content expects one property and
that's the editor itself. This means I
can click on control spacebar, get the
editor prop, and this will be equal to
editor. And what do you think? Is it
time to test it out? I think so. Because
if I go back
Uh-huh. So, we have our menu bar, which
looks great. And then we have this
nothing burger, if this makes sense. So,
there's nothing here. But if I click on
this nothing thing, then I get this
little outline. So, we have a text area.
And if I type something, I get my
content. If I click on enter, ah, it can
also create more space. So, we get this
text or editor content, but it's not
really styled. It does not look very
nice. So, we have to change it. We have
to style it. And how do we style this
editor content? Good question. We style
it in this editor instance itself. So,
we can go underneath this extensions
array and we want to get the editor
props property. This is an object.
Inside of here, we can get attributes.
This is also an object and then inside
of here we can get the class property
and what we say right here or what we
add right here will be then applied to
this editor content. So for the class
name I want to say minimum height of
custom value 300 pixels. Then I want to
also add padding. So padding four. And
this means if I again go back and do a
hard refresh this will already look a
bit better a bit but not great. So I'm
missing like a border. I think you all
know what I mean. A nice looking border
so that the user understands that this
is a text area. So what we can do is go
back and we can update this wrapper div.
We can give it a class name and this
will be with full border. Border which
will be input. So this is the color.
Then rounded which will be lg overflow
which will be hidden. And then we can
also use this dark would you call it
model thingy? I don't know. So if dark
mode is true then the background color
should be input with an opacity of 30%.
So if dark mode is true bg input 30% of
30% opacity. So if I go back this now
has the exact same background color as
our text area input and stuff like that.
But if you I'm not sure if you see it
but currently we have the problem that
we have two borders. So here at the
bottom we have one border. This looks
great, but on the right side, top and
left, we now have a double border. This
does not look nice. I'm sure you
probably don't see it right now, but if
you look at your screen with, I don't
know, with a very good glasses, then you
will see it. So, we can go back to the
menu bar. I can open it again. And then
I want to update this top class name.
So, currently we create a border for all
um sides, the top, left, right, bottom.
And but what we will do is just create a
border for the bottom. This means we can
say border top will be zero. And then
border x will also be zero. So yeah,
border top zero, border x. This means
the left and right side will be zero. If
I again go back, I'm not sure if you see
it, but this already looks 10 times
cleaner. Then I'm also not a big fan of
this blue outline or focus thingy. Kind
of ugly, I will be honest with you. So
we can go back to the editor to our
attributes and we can use this focus
class and if focus is true this I want
to say outline none. So if I now click
on the text area I don't get this ugly
border outline thingy. And let's test
out our rich text editor. So if I write
some content everything works. If I
highlight this and say that this should
be bold. It works. Then this for example
should be itallic. This here should be
strike through. This all works nicely.
But if I for example try to create a
bullet list, it does not work. What's
the problem? If I try to align it, does
it work? This aligns. I can also undo my
changes. This also works. But I this
bullet list and ordered list does not
work. So what's the problem? So this is
not a tip tap problem, but instead a
tailwind CSS problem. And to fix it, we
want to use the TIN CSS typography
plugin. So you can just go to Google and
search for TIN CSS typography. And then
you can click on the first link. This
will redirect you to a GitHub repo. And
here they say beautiful typographic
defaults for HTML you don't control. So
we can then use this pros class and this
will create beautiful typographic
defaults to any vanilla HTML you don't
control like HTML rendered from markdown
or pulled from a CMS. This means we can
install it and this is also a
development dependency. So I will copy
this installation command. I will go
back and then I can paste it in my
terminal. So pnpmi uppercase d t1 css
typography. We can then again restart
our dev server and we have to also then
add the plug-in to our main style file.
This means I can copy this plug-in taven
CSS and we want to open our globals.css
file and then underneath this import I
will paste this at plugin. As you see we
also get this yellow squiggly line and
it says unknown at rule plugin. Don't
worry this is not a problem. It just
throws a weird error. It always does
that. We can then close the globals.css
file and then for our attributes we can
use this pros class. So we can say pros
pros SM will be the default. On SM or
bigger this will be pros. On LG or
bigger this will be pros LG. On XL or
bigger this will be pros XL. So if we
again go back what will we get? Well I
have to do a hard refresh and I hope
that everything works. So now if I write
something, damn, I don't see anything.
What's this color? It's gray.
Ugly. So here's the thing. When you use
this typography plugin in dark mode, you
have to also invert the colors. This
means we can go back to the attributes
and we can say on dark mode, we want to
do a pro-ashinvert.
It will invert the colors. And if I go
back, yes, that's what I wanted. So if I
now for example use this bullet list,
you'll see it works exactly as expected
and that's what I wanted. But now
there's another problem. So as you see I
wrote a lot of content here. But if I
zoom out quite a bit, it just stops in
the middle. What's the problem? Well,
this pros class also adds a maximum
width. I don't understand why they do
that. Honestly, a stupid mistake or a
stupid thing in my opinion. They
shouldn't have done that. But hey, I
guess we can just update it by
ourselves. So for the class, we can add
this exclamation mark and then say with
full and then exclamation mark max width
none. This means if I again go back and
zoom out a bit and create a bit more
content, it will now take the whole
width as you see. So again, I'm not sure
why the T1 CSS team made such a
decision, but maybe there's a good
reason for that. I don't know. But
honestly, I wanted to take the whole
width and that's why I added this little
helper thingy. So, to be honest, I think
we have finished with the witch text
editor. I think I will later on maybe
change the text color and stuff like
that. But for now, we see that
everything works. And I mean, let's
again test out everything. So, I will
delete everything. We can get started
first of all with bold. If I click on
bold, yes, it works. Then, does italic
work? Yes, it works. Then does uh strike
three work? So if I highlight this and
click on strike, yes, it works. Does the
H1 work? Yes, it works. Does the H2
work? Yes, it works. How about the H3?
Yes, this also works. Then how about
this bullet list? Yes, it works. Then
how about this ordered list? Yes, it
also works. Great. And maybe alignment.
So align center and then align right.
Yes. Undo. Also great. So we are
finished with our rich text editor,
right? No, we are not quite finished
because there's one thing missing and
that's the connection to React took form
to our client side state management form
validation library. So here's the thing.
If we again go back to our creation
route, what do we get? We get this field
object. This field object exposes a lot
of things like an onv valueue change, a
value and stuff like that. This means we
want to pass this field to our rich text
editor. So I can go back to the editor
component itself and then in my params I
can destruct and I want to get a field
and this will be of type any. It has its
own type but you have to do a lot of
weird things to get the typing. So
that's why I will say type any. Again
you can create the real type but then
you have to do a lot of advanced
TypeScript and I don't want to write all
of this code. It's quite a lot of code
just to get the correct field typing. So
as you all know react hook form works
with controlled inputs. This means we
have to provide a value and then an onv
value change or in this case content and
then on update. So we can go underneath
this editor props and I want to get this
on update function and it will fire
whenever our text content updates. So
this will be equal to a standard arrow
function. I can then the structure the
params and I can get the editor and what
I want to do is set my field. So I get
my field and I want to update my field
and in this case this means I want to
use the onchange handler. So we can get
our field then dot onchange as you see I
don't get any typing that's fine please
make sure that you just spell it
correctly. Then we want to invoke it and
as an argument I want to get my JSON. So
here's the thing this editor allows us
to get JSON. So I can just say editor
dot and then you get a few methods and I
want to use the get JSON method. This
will get a document as JSON. But here's
the thing. If we open our schema and go
to the course itself, you will see that
I want to store my description as a
string. This means we will get JSON but
I will stringify this JSON and then
store the stringify JSON in my database.
And then once we then want to render
this content later on, we will then pass
this string again to a standard JSON and
um how would you say it propagated into
uh tip tap if this makes sense. So again
we will get JSON we will stringify it
store it in our database then retrieve
it pass it again into standard JSON and
then pass it later on to tip tap to then
render it nicely. And then in the editor
onchange I want to get JSON dot
stringify and then I want to invoke it.
And then as an argument I want to get my
JSON because what I pass inside of here
will be then stringified. And in this
case this will be editor.get JSON. So we
now get our JSON. We stringify it and we
set it in our field. So we update our
field. And then what else is missing?
Well, we have to also set the content
because again this is a controlled
input. we have to control it. So
underneath the on update I can get the
content and here I want to create a
turnary. If we get data from our field
this means for example later on we will
have an edit route. In the edit route I
will already have content predefined
because we will already have a course
which we want to edit. This means this
field will have JSON and here I want to
create a turnary and check if we have a
value. Then let's render this already
created content. If no uh if not then
let's just create a dummy p tag or
something like that. So right here I can
get my field dot value and if this is
true then we can use a turnary a
question mark and I want to do a JSON
pass and I want to pass my field dot
value. If this is not true we can use a
colon and I want to create or I want to
render a p tag. This means we can get a
p tag or we can create one. And for the
content I will just say hello world. So
let's test it out. If I go back and do a
hard refresh I get an error. Cannot read
properties of undefined. What's the
problem? Well the thing is currently we
don't pass this editor uh as a prop
because if I go to my creation route and
scroll to the bottom our rich text
editor expects a property and this is
the field and the field will be equal to
field and this should work. This means
if I go back and do a hard refresh, we
get hello world. And again, we get hello
world because we currently don't have
any predefined data. If we would have
already a JSON from our previous course,
then we would of course render the data
right here. But since there is no
predefined data, since we create a new
course, our turnary is false, which
means we render hello world. If you want
to, you can also change it up to
something else. Honestly, I couldn't
care less. So, as a next step, I want to
finally continue with file uploads. But
before we do that, we have to fix two
small bugs. So, if I go back and open my
terminal, you will see an interesting
warning. Tip tap error SSR has been
detected. Please set immediately render
explicitly to false to avoid hydration
mismatches. So, here's the thing. If I
open my editor, this component is marked
with the use client directive. A lot of
people think that this means that this
component is rendered on the client
side. No, this component is still
rendered on the server side. We just get
a client um a JavaScript client bundle.
Yes, that's what I wanted to say. And
the problem is tip tap does not work in
a SSR environment. Tip tap has to be
rendered on the client side. it has to
initialize on the client side. That's
why we can go to the editor to our
editor instance and we want to get a
specific property which is immediately
render and we want to set it to false to
not uh to not SSR tip tap to not server
render it. This means if I go back and
do a hard refresh and again open my
terminal this error won't show up again
because it's now fixed the problem. So
this is bug number one. That's great.
And then we have another problem. So
currently I'm signed in with my email.
This means I did not use GitHub but
instead I used this OTP email sign in
variant option whatever. This means if I
go back to my homepage I will get an
error as you see cannot read properties
of undefined and this has to do with my
avatar fallback. So what we can do is
open the user drop-down component
because this is where the problem is
created. So here I have an avatar
fallback and I render my name uh or I
get the first character in my name and
then I uppercase it. The biggest problem
is this does not work because what was
the problem with the name? Well, when a
user signs in with his email, we don't
get a name and that's why we used or in
our nav user we created this turnary
where we checked hey do we get a
username? If so we can render it. If not
then let's use the email and we want to
do the same thing for the user dropdown.
And as you see all of this data is
passed as props or we get it through the
params. This means if I go to my navbar
we pass the email image and name through
props. This means we have to update the
code right here. So if I go to the nav
user we have a turnary right here for
the username. What I will do is copy
this turnary. So session do user.name
name and if we have or if the length is
bigger than zero then we render the
username if not we render the email
let's just copy this code let's go back
to the navbar and then I will paste it
for the name property so if session do
user name exists and if the length is
bigger than zero then I want to return
the session uh session do user name if
we don't get the name which has a bigger
character length than zero then we will
return the session do user email this
means the email itself. Nevertheless,
this still has one problem because we
will now pass the whole email with the
at symbol. We don't want that. So, we
can go back to the nav user. And if I
scroll a bit to the bottom, we should
find the split method. So, split, we
want to split the at and we want to get
the first part because again, this
splits the user into two parts or the
email. First of all, the thing in front
of the at and then the thing after the
at. And we want to get the thing in
front of the at. So I will just copy the
split method. I can go back and then I
want to paste it inside of here. And
don't worry, I will fix or delete or
remove these AI suggestions in a second.
I forgot that. But if I again go back
and do a hard refresh, everything again
works. Nevertheless, we still have one
problem for the image because as you
see, this is just a dummy or there is no
image. recurrently just render the
avatar fallback. And that's again
because if you go to the navbar, you
will see if there's no user image, we
pass an empty string. We don't want
that. So we can go back to the nav user.
And if I scroll a bit to the top, you
will see that we have a turnary or we
created a turnary for the avatar image.
If there's no user image, then we use
this nullish qual. So if there's no
image, then we will render this avatar
URL. So this is this avatar API uh
provided by versel. So I will just copy
this uh nullish coalition code. I can go
back to the navbar and I will paste it
for the image. So again if we get the
session do user.image then we will pass
it. If we don't get it then we will
instead pass this URL provided by versel
itself. This means if I go back and do a
hard refresh nice we get this nicel
looking image. I get my name, the email,
everything looks beautiful and
everything is finished. There's only one
problem. This drop-down menu is too
small. It should take a bigger width
because this is kind of small and it
does not look very appealing. At least I
think so. This means if we go back to
the user dropdown, we have our drop-down
menu content here. And and it has a
class name which is maximum width 64.
This means the width won't be bigger. So
instead of rendering maximum width 64,
we will just instead render minimum
width and this will be how about 52. How
does this look? Yeah, maybe a bit too
big. How about something with 40? So 48
maybe. This should already look way
better. And yeah, I think 48 looks quite
good. So we will hardcode it uh with 48.
But since this is a minimum width, it
can also become bigger if needed. But I
don't think so. I think this should be
fine enough. So we fixed the two
problems, the two small bugs and we can
finally continue with file uploads. So
let's first of all again navigate back
to the admin dashboard. We want to go to
the courses create course and then
instead of rendering this stupid input.
Yeah, it's not stupid. But this ugly
input, we will render a nice custom and
accessible drag and drop zone. Now,
here's the thing. Here's my question to
you. How do you or how would you create
a custom drag and drop zone? So, you
might say, "Hey, Jan, natively, yeah,
that will probably be a bit too hard."
So, how about we use a pre-built
component? Sure, but I want to have a
custom component. And again, it should
also be accessible. I want to own the
code. I don't want to just install some
sort of pre-built component. So there's
this. So here comes the solution. React
drop zone. So React drop zone is a
simple React hook to create a HTML 5
compliant drag and drop zone for files.
So this is not a component. This is
nothing pre-built. This is not styled.
This is pretty much what Tiptap does. It
gives you an easy to use API in this uh
case a hook which you use and this hook
then exposes functions and you can use
these functions to create your own
custom and accessible drag and drop
zone. This means you fully own the code.
You also install a very small
dependency. The package size isn't big.
So this is a win-win in this case
because it's makes it easier to create a
drag and drop zone while also allowing
you to create a custom one. So what we
can do is first of all install react
drop zone. Here we have a installation
uh command. I will just copy it. Then I
will open my terminal, stop my dev
server and run pnpmi react drop zone.
This will install everything. And what I
want to do is create a separate
component again. This means we can open
the components or the explorer. Then we
want to go to the components folder. And
since I will reuse the file uploader, I
want to also create a new subfolder. So
this will be file-uploader
for the folder name. And inside of here,
I want to create an uploader.tsx
file. So this will be the component
itself. So we want to first of all mark
this component this file with the use
client directive because react drop zone
this means if I go back you will see
that react drop zone exposes a hook and
this hook I mean it does not expose it
it provides us with an h with a hook and
this hook exposes functions. These
functions at pretty much create this
internal state management and to make it
work they of course need a JavaScript
bundle. This means this is the reason
why we mark this file with the use
client directive and then let's go back
to the documentation and the first step
is to copy this code example where they
initialize the use drop zone hook. So I
will copy it. Of course we want to first
of all create a function. So this will
be an export function uploader. I will
also disable this AI thingy. And then
inside of here I want to first of all
create a return statement diff. And then
for the H1 I want to say hello, how are
you? Then we want to render this
uploader component in our creation
route. So I will again open my explorer.
We want to go into the app folder, admin
folder, courses folder, create folder,
page.tsx. Then here I can delete this
text area comment. We don't need it
anymore. We have our own rich text
editor. And then here you will find this
form field with the file key. I will
comment out this input and instead we
will get the uploader component from the
components. This is self-closing. Then
we can head over back to the uploader
and inside of here I want to paste the
code which I copied. This means where
they initialize the use drop zone hook.
Sadly use drop zone does not import for
me automatically. So I will just copy it
from the code example from the
documentation and then I can paste it on
top. So import use drop zone from react
drop zone. So this use drop zone hook
exposes three functions. So first of all
the get root props function, the get
input props function and is drag active.
Is drag active isn't a function. Instead
it's a boolean. This means when you drag
with your file over the drop zone, this
boolean will be set to true. If you
don't track with a file over the drop
zone, then this boolean will be set to
false. And this get root props function
and get input props function will be
used for the internal state system. So
we can head over back to the
documentation. And here you will find
this section drop zone props getters. So
the drop zone property getters are just
two functions that return objects with
properties which you need to use to
create a drag and drop zone. The root
properties can be applied to whatever
element you want. Whereas the input
properties must be applied to an input.
So again these two functions are there
to create the drag and drop zone. They
are used for the state system and just
the back end in general. And the first
function get root props. You can just
apply it to any element. It makes sense
to just apply it to the first element.
In this case, a diff. And the get input
props function has to be specifically
applied to an input, not to a button,
not to a P tag, just to an input. So
what we can do is again scroll to the
top and then I will copy this return
statement. We can go back and then
instead of rendering this diff, I will
paste what I just copied. Uh I get here
one ear slint warning. So I can click on
quick fix and then disable. If we again
go back then we won't see much because
if I do a hard refresh you will see that
my deaf server is not running. So I can
restart it with pnpm rundeaf and then in
theory I should see at least something
but I don't see anything on drop is not
defined. So what's the problem? Well
right here we destructure the use drop
zone hook. And when we do structured we
pass on drop. On drop is a function and
this function will be called whenever we
drop files into the drop zone. This
means if you go back to the
documentation then here they already
define the onrop function. So as a param
it will get accepted files and these are
all of the files which you drop into the
drop zone and then you can do something
with the files later on. We will then
upload them. So I can copy this ondrop
function and then I will paste it above
this used drop zone hook. For the
accepted files we want to also provide a
type because hey we are Typescript
developers and the type will be file
array because a user can of course drop
multiple files into the array. Uh later
on we will limit limit the whole thing
to one file but still accepted files is
an array of files. Then we want to also
import use callback from React. And in
theory, this should already be it. We
can also, for example, console lock the
accepted files to see what we get access
to. And this is already it. This means
if I go back again and do a hard
refresh, we get this thing. This is the
drop zone. Yeah, it does not look
beautiful, but in theory, it should
work. This means if I take a file and
drag over this drop zone, you see
something interesting. drop the files
here. If I remove the file from the drop
zone, we again get this initial state.
So this is this boolean uh or yeah this
is drag active boolean right in effect
because when we drag over the file, it's
set to true. This means we render this P
tag. If is drag active is not true, we
again render this initial state. And I
can also drag and drop a file into the
drop zone. So I will drop it and nothing
happens. But that's fine because if I
open the inspector and go to the
console, we get a console lock and it
console locks an array with one object.
And this one object is the file which we
just dropped. As you see, we get access
to the handle, path, relative path,
name, size, and stuff like that. So we
get access to the whole file, which is
cool. Great. But now we have one
problem. This drag and drop zone looks
relatively ugly but it should look
beautiful. This means we want to style
it. So we can head over back to our code
base and then um instead of returning
this div I want to return a card. So the
cart component then for the cart of
course we want to also style it. This
means we can give it a class name and I
want to style it dynamically using this
is track active boolean which means I
will use the CN helper function. Then we
want to first of all give this card
default styles which will be applied
always. This means the position will be
relative. Then we will pass a border
too. So the border width will be a bit
bigger two pixels. Then border will be
dashed so little dots. Transition will
be colors. Then also duration 200 W full
and then height 64. As you see this
already looks kind of like a drop zone.
Nevertheless, this of course should be
centered. But before we do that, we can
first of all use the is drag active
boolean to style the card further. This
means we can add a comma after these
default styles and then we can create a
turnary. So if is drag active is true
then let's use a question mark and then
I want to render border which will be
primary this means this orange color bg
primary but I don't want to render the
full opacity so this will be / 10 10%
opacity and then border which will be
solid and if this is not true then we
can use a colon and we will render
border border then also hover and this
will be border primary so I guess This
should look quite nice. And yes, if I
hover over my cut, I get this nice hover
state. If I take a file and again drag
over the drop zone, I get this nice
hover animation. That's because the is
drag active boolean is set to true. And
that's why we change the background
color and also the border. So we are
finished with the cart. We can then
continue. I want to wrap the content in
the card content component. So we can
get cart content from the components.
Then we can again paste all of the
content in the cart content and we can
also style the cart content. So this
will be flex then item center. So for
the class name justify center. So this
means we want to center all of the
children put them right into the middle
and then also height full width full and
padding for uh on all sides. So as you
see um nothing has really changed. The
only thing is that our text is now
centered and that's way better. Then we
can continue and I don't want to use
this is drag active boolean inside of
here anymore or this turnary. So I will
delete this code and for now just create
a p tag with some dummy data with some
dummy text. Yeah, this does not look
beautiful. But what's the reason or why
did I just do that? Well, that's because
I want to create a new function a render
um how will I call it? I think render
content because we will have a few
states. We will have the uploading
state. That's when we drop a file and
the file is actively uploading. Then we
will also have the uploaded state. So if
a file is successfully uploaded, I want
to display the file. Then we will also
have a default state. This means when
nothing is uploaded and when also
nothing is uploading. So just a default
state. And then we want to also create
an error state. And this will be
displayed if there is an error. Who
would have thought? So what we can do is
again go back and I will create a
separate component for that because it's
quite a bit of code. So in the file
uploader folder we can create a new file
and this will be render states or
state.tsx.
Then inside of here we want to start
with the first state and this will be
the default empty state. So I want to
create an export function. This will be
render empty state. Then we can just
open this function and inside of here
let's create a return statement. In the
params I want to also the structure them
and I want to get the is drag active
boolean. This means I can go back to the
uploader. I can copy the name is drag
active and then paste it inside of here.
As you see I get an error and that's
because is track active has an any type
but the type is boolean. This means we
can just give it a type. So is track
active will be of type boolean. Then in
the return statement we can finally
create something. So let's render a div.
Yeah. Uh autocomp completion. Hello.
Yeah. Thank you. And then for the div
let's give it a class name. And this
will be text center. In the div we want
to create another div. And in this div,
this will be the wrapper div for the
icon because how will my empty state
look like? We will have an icon on the
top, then a little title, and then a
small button. This means this wrap. Um,
yeah, let's not style it for now. And
inside of here, I want to get the cloud
up icon or cloud upload icon from Lucid
React. This is self-closing. And I want
to also style it. So, we can give it a
class name. And I want to use the CN
helper function because I want to style
this icon dynamically using this is drag
active boolean. So we can invoke it
inside of here for the default styles.
This will be size six. Then text muted
foreground. And then we can use the is
track active boolean. So if is drag
active is true, we can use this double
and sign. And this will be equal to text
primary or in other words we want to
render text primary. Then we can also
style this wpper div. So we can give it
a class name. And also this will be
quite simple. So this will be flex items
center. Then also MX auto to center
everything. Justify center to center the
children. This means the cloud upload
icon. And then also size 12. So this is
the size of the wrapper. So again this
is size six. This is size 12. This
background thingy this div will create a
background color. It will have a
rounding and stuff like that. And then
the icon will be rendered in this div.
So in this wrapper rounding background
thingy. So size 12 then also rounded
which will be full and then BG muted so
to have this grayish color and margin
bottom four. Now if we save this and go
back you will see nothing. What's the
problem? Well this function is not
rendered anywhere. So here's what we
will do. We will go back to the uploader
and instead of rendering this gibberish
I will instead get my how was it it
again called render empty state. So I
can just get my render empty state
component which is imported from the
components or from the render state
component. This is self-closing and as
you see it throws an error and the
problem is that it expects a property
which is is track active. This means is
track active will be equal to is track
active. If we go back, you will see or
we will see this right here. Yeah. No,
no, no. This isn't really nice. So, we
can go back to the render state. And we
are finished with the icon. As a next
step, I want to render this little, as
mentioned, not really title, but
description and then a button. So, we
want to go underneath the diff, the diff
which wraps the icon. And then we want
to get a P tag inside of here. I will
say drop your files here or then I want
to get a span element not PSN but span.
I got PSN PlayStation. Okay, whatever.
And in the span I will say click uh
click to upload. As you will see this
does not look very nice. It it looks
fine but it could look better that we
could give it maybe a bigger font weight
and maybe a different color. Who knows?
So let's first of all style the P tag.
We can give it a class name. This will
be text base font which will be semib
bold and then also text which will be
foreground. Then for the span element I
want to give it like a even bigger font
weight because this is font semibold.
This should be font bold. So let's give
it a class name. This will be text
primary. This um orange color and then
font bold and cursor pointer pointer. As
you see this already looks way better.
And this click to upload text has a
different color and also a bigger font
weight. And if I click on click to
upload, this finder window opens. So
this also works great. And I think
that's already it. I mean I mentioned we
can also render a button. So I guess why
not? So we can go underneath the P tag,
get the button component from the
components and inside of here we can
just say select a file. Then if I again
go back. Yeah, this looks all right. We
need some margin to the top. So class
name margin top four. Yeah, I think this
is finished. If we click on select file,
uh nothing happens or we get a lot of
validation errors. What's the problem?
Well, as mentioned at the start, if you
don't give a button or if you don't give
this button a type of button, the button
will be treated like a submit button.
That's why we will right here say type
and this will be button. If I again go
back and click on select file, we don't
get any validation anymore. And that's
because this button is not treated
anymore like a submit button. And if we
do a bit of drag and drop also,
everything looks beautiful. So what's
the next state? Well, as a next state uh
state, let's create a render error
state. So we can go back and we can
collapse this export function and
underneath it, we can create a new
export constant or export function. This
will be the render error state. And then
we can just open this function. Inside
of here I want to return a div element.
And then for the div I we want to also
style it. So for the class name this
will be text destructive. Text
destructive or destructive itself is a
CSS variable uh provided or created by
shad and UI and it will give us like a
red color. And then I want to also say
text center to center the text. Inside
of here I want to get the image icon.
The image icon is imported from Lucid
React. This is self-closing. And for the
class name, this will be size 10. And
then also MX auto and margin bottom
three. Uh we want to also display this
error state because currently we only
have the empty state. So we can go to
the uploader and then instead of
rendering the empty state, we want to
render the error state. This is imported
from the render state or yeah render
state component. And this means if I
again go back, yeah, it could look
better. So we can go back to the render
state. And you know what? What is if we
also create this little background color
for this image icon. So what I can do is
go to the render empty state. And then
we have this div, this wrapper div which
wraps the cloud upload icon. We can just
copy it. This whole div, I can go back
and paste it instead of this upload
icon. Then instead of using the cloud
upload icon, we will again get this
image icon which is already imported. I
want to delete the is track active. We
won't need it. And then for the diff,
instead of using this BG muted, this
will be BG uh destructive destructive/
30 uh% opacity. And then for the image
icon, instead of saying text muted
foreground, this will be text
destructive. So this should look quite
nice. And yeah, you know what? I'm quite
a big fan. Then I want to also render a
little text. So underneath the vera div,
we can get a p tag and inside of here I
will say upload failed. This will be
like the title. We can also style it. So
we can give it a class name and this
will be text base. And then also font
which will be semibold. Underneath this
P tag, we can create another P tag and I
will say something went wrong. Also I
want to style the P tag and then this
will be text XS and margin top one. And
also I want to give it I mean let's for
now save this. Um yeah this is fine but
text destructive does not look very
nice. So what's the problem? Dum dum dum
here. This is the problem. As you see
the main div has a class name which is
text destructive. This means all of the
children get text destructive as a
color. I don't want that. I'm not even
sure why I added this. So, we can just
delete it again. And yeah, this is
already way better. The only problem is
it has a white color. Maybe a grayish
color would look better. So, and also
this shouldn't be text XL, but instead
text XS. And yeah, I want to use a
grayish color. So, this will be text
muted foreground. And then underneath
this small P tag, I want to render one
more P tag. And this will just say click
or drag a file to retry. So click or
drag file to reach YY. Then I want you
also style the P tag. And then this will
be or we will give the P tag a class
name. This will be text XS margin uh top
of three. And then also text muted
foreground. This means this grayish
color. And yeah it looks quite gr uh
quite nice. I don't know what's wrong.
Maybe a button would work a bit better.
I think so. So instead of using this P
tag I will instead again get a button.
Of course we want to give it a type
which will be button. And for the text
this will be retry
file. No. Yeah. My god retry. Uh okay.
Yeah this is great. We want to give it a
bit more margin to the top. So for the
button I will add a class name with
margin top four. And yep this is quite
good. Retry. Yeah that's not enough
text. So maybe retry file selection. Is
this better? Yeah. You know what? I
think we can leave it like this. And if
I click on the button, we don't get any
validation errors. And that's because
again we added a type which is button.
So what's the next step? Maybe we can
create the render uploaded state. And
after that or you know what? Let's maybe
for now implement the ondrop
functionality because currently a user
cannot really upload a file. So we can
go back to the uploader. We get an error
currently for an unused import. So
instead of using or instead of rendering
the error state, I want to render the
empty state. So let's get render empty
state. This is imported from the render
state component. Of course, we want to
pass the is track active boolean. And
don't worry later on we will make
everything dynamic. But for now we will
just showcase this one component. And I
want to first of all imple uh implement
file uploads and then after that I will
create the uploading state and also the
uploaded state. So first of all I want
to update my use drop zone hook uh in
general. So currently a user can
literally drop any file into the drop
zone. A video a or not a video but a
PNG, a JPEG, some sort of zip, some sort
of DMG, whatever. A user can literally
drop anything and I don't want that. I
want to only accept videos and then also
images. That's it. Nothing else. This
means what we can do is we can go
underneath the onrop and then we will
get the property which is called accept.
Except uh is just equal to an object and
then in this accept object um I can just
provide the type. In this case for now I
want to only allow users to upload
images. This means I can get an image
right here in the string. then slashstar
and this will be equal to an empty
array. This means I will only accept
images. Then underneath this accept we
can also get the max files property.
This means how many files does the user
or can the user drop into the drop zone.
In this case only one because the user
should only upload one image. And then
multiple will be set to false because
again a user can only select one file.
And then we can also create a max size
property. And this is the maximum size
of the file. In this case, this should
be 5 megabytes. And you can't really
just say in strings 5 MB. This does not
work. You have to calculate the bytes uh
to get to this 5 mgabytes. So in this
case, this will be 5 * 1,24
* 1,024.
So 1,024 * 1,024 uh equals to 1 mAB. And
then 1 mgabyte * 5 equals to 5 mgabytes.
So we can just create a comment and say
5 MB calculation. Yeah, why not? So this
is finished. But currently we still have
one problem because if I go back and try
to for example drag and drop what could
we drag and drop? How about we drag and
drop a video? So if I drag and drop this
video inside of here, nothing happens.
But I would like to get some sort of
error toast. So some sort of feedback I
as a user want to know hey this was
incorrect user try again this means I
want to return a toast and to return a
toast we have to check for the specific
error if you want to call it like that
yeah that's how you call it this means
inside of the use drop zone hook where
we destructure it we can get the ondrop
rejected property and this will fire
whenever we reject a file drop so onrop
rejected will right now be equal to
nothing because I want to create a
separate function. So we can go above
this use drop zone and I want to create
a function which will be called rejected
files and then we can just open this in
my params. I want to get the rejected
file. So in this case this will be file
rejection and this will be of type file
rejection imported from react drop zone
and we want to append an array because a
user or how how should I say it all
files in this drop zone are treated as
an array you can't store one singular
file no everything is an array and
that's why I append this array symbol
and then inside of here I want to create
an if statement first of all because it
could be that the user did not or that
our drop zone did not reject anything.
So we will say if we get a file
rejection.length so if at least one file
is rejected then we can create or we can
listen for the specific error messages.
So we can first of all listen for the
too many files error. So I will create a
constant too many files and this will be
equal to file rejection dotfind and I
want to find a specific rejection.
Here's the thing. This file rejection as
mentioned is an array. This means we we
want to find the specific error in this
array. And that's why I use the find
method. In this find method, I can of
course get a param. This will be the
rejection itself. This is the iterator
over when we iterate over this array. So
rejection and then we want to create an
inline callback function. And I want to
get the rejection itself dot errors. And
I want to get the first array of this
errors array. So array symbol zero and
then the code. So dot code. And this
should be equal to strings. And inside
of here 2-y
files. Sadly I don't get any typescript
types. So please try to spell it
correctly. Two-man
files. And if this is true, we can go
underneath the constant and we want to
again create an if statement. So if too
many files is true. So if this error
state is triggered then we can open the
if statement and we want to return an
error toast. So toast is imported from
sona do error and as an argument as for
the message I want to return too many
files selected uh max is one as you see
we get currently one error and that's
because our onrop rejected is equal to
nothing. So we can just pass this
rejected files function for the ondrop
rejected property. This error is now
gone and this function also works.
Currently we only listen for too many
files and I want to also listen for the
error when the file size is too big. So
we can create another constant. This
will be file size too big and this will
be equal to file rejection dotfind. Then
as a param we want to get the rejection.
This is an inline callback function. We
want to get the rejection itself dot
errors. This is an array. So we want to
get the first error and then dot code.
And this should be equal to
file-2-large.
And if this is true, we want to create
another if statement. So if file size
too big, then we want to return a toast.
So toast. And for the message, I will
just say file size exceeds the limit.
And in theory, this should already work.
So if I again go back and try to drag
and drop a lot of files, I get an error
a to host and it says too many files
selected max is one. If I again only
select one file, I don't get any errors.
That's because the validation itself is
correct. And then we can also test out
the max size limit. So right here I just
say that this should be 1,024 bytes.
Which means if I take a new image or a
new file and drop it into my drop zone,
my god, my mouse is broken. I'm sorry,
guys. And as you see, I get an error and
it's and it says file size exceeds the
limit. So I can again update this to 5
mgabytes because that was the original
or the original file size limit. And I
think we have finished with the
validation itself or in other words with
the rejected files. What's the next
thing which I want to implement? Well,
this will be our ondrop function itself.
And here's the thing. So when I upload
my file later on, as mentioned, I want
to display it right here. This means I
have to also store the dropped files in
state. So what we want to do is create a
new state. So um I want to first of all
delete this ESLint warning. And then in
my uploader function itself, I can
create a constant. And then we want to
get an getter and a setter. So this will
be file state. and then also set file
state and this will be equal to use
state use state is imported from react
and as you know we have to pass also an
initial state so what I can do is create
an interface at the top so this will be
interface uh uploader state yeah that I
think that's a good name and inside of
here I want to get a few properties this
means in my state there will be quite a
few properties which I want to store
first of all for example in unique ID
the file itself the progress because
later on as you all know I want to
display the uploaded progress as a
percentage 10% 20% whatever then for
example the URL itself the file type the
key and stuff like that so first of all
I want to get an ID so this will be of
type string or null because as an
initial state we won't have any files
which also means the ID will be null
then we want to also store a file the
file will be of type file or null
because Again as an initial state we
won't have any uploaded files. Then we
want to get the uploading state itself
and this will be a type boolean. So we
are either uploading or we are not
uploading. Then I want to also store the
progress indicator and this will be of
type number again 5% 10% 50% whatever.
Then we will store the key. So here's
the thing later on we will upload our
file to S3. S3 will return us or give us
a unique key which it uses to reference
or identify the file and we will use the
key to then later on construct our URL.
The ID is only there to then map over
our items in this uploader component
itself. But the key is what is really
important because it will allow us to
get the file from the S3 bucket but also
to delete the file and this key will be
optional and it will be of type string.
Then I want to also get an is deleting
boolean. So this will be of type boolean
as mentioned. And if we are deleting a
file, I will set this boolean to true.
Then I want to also get an error and
this will be of type boolean. So if we
get some sort of error, we will set this
boolean to true. Then I want to also get
an object URL and this will be optional
and also of type string. So this will be
the local URL of our file of our video
of our image and then I want to also get
a file type and this could either be an
image or a video. This means we can get
a string. So this will be either image
or with this or sign a video. So this is
our uploader state and we can pass the
uploader state to our use state hook
itself. So as a generic I will pass the
uploader state and then right here for
the initial state we can structure it
and pass all of the properties and since
we pass the generic we of course also
get help from TypeScript. This means if
I click on control spacebar I get all of
my properties. So first of all for the
error itself this will be false because
we don't have any error. Then for the
file itself this will be null. We don't
have any file. For the ID this will be
null. For the uploading boolean, this
will be false. For the progress, this
will be zero. Then for the is deleting
boolean, this will be false. And then we
have two more things. First of all, the
file type. And for the file type, right
now, I will just hardcode image. And
that's already it because the rest of
the properties are all optional. We will
update them later on. But for now, we
don't really need them. So our file
state is finished which means I can go
into my ondrop function and I want to
update it because we get our accepted
files and I want to put these accepted
files or in other words this one
accepted file into my state. So I can
delete first of all the console log. I
don't need it anymore. And inside of
here we want to first of all create an
if statement and we want to check if we
even have accepted files. So if accepted
files.length length is bigger than zero
then we can upload our file. So we can
first of all get the file itself
constant file will be equal to accepted
files and I want to get the first file
in the array. This means array symbols
zero and then underneath this file I
want to upload my or I want to set my
state. This means set file state I want
to invoke it the structured and then for
the file this will be equal to file.
Then for uploading this will be false.
Then for progress this will be zero. For
the object URL I want to create a new
object URL. This means we can use this
URL. How would you call it? Interface.
Does this make sense? I think it's
called interface. And then we can use
the create object URL method. And as an
argument I want to pass my file. So what
we can do is click on MDN. So this is
just the documentation website. and I
will open it in a new tab. So create
object URL is a static method and as you
see the create object URL method is a
static method of the URL interface and
it creates a string containing a URL
representing the object given in the
parameter. The URL lifetime is tied to
the document in the window on which it
was created. The new object URL
represents the specified file object uh
or blob object. So what exactly is meant
by that? Well, this file which we pass
right here is an object, right? We get
the um what do we get? We get the size,
the created at time stamp, stuff like
that. But this is an object and we can't
render an object for our image tag
itself. This means we have to create a
local representation of the file as a
URL. And using this URL interface and to
be more specific using this create
object URL method we can take the file
the object and convert it into a local
URL. This is stored then in our document
as a memory itself. We will have to then
also revoke it. But for now we don't
really have to think about these
problems. Right now we just generate
this new URL this local URL and that's
great. Then as a next step for the error
this will be false because we don't have
any error. And for the ID, I want to
pass a unique ID because this is what I
will use to map over my files. So we
could create one using the crypto
package. But the biggest problem is
crypto does not really work in a
serverless environment in versel or in
the edge environment. This means what I
will do instead is install the UYU ID
package. The UU ID um let me get it
right here. So npm UU ID. This is the
package which I want to use and all it
does is it will give us a unique
identifier. That's it. Nothing
groundbreaking. So we will use uyu ID v4
to generate such an ID and this will be
then used to identify our file. So I can
copy this uyuid package name and then in
my terminal I will run pnpmi uyuid. Once
installed I can restart my dev server
and then on the top I want to import
uuid. So I will copy this import
statement and then on the top I can just
paste it. This means import v4 as uyu uh
id v4. I can then copy it. Scroll to the
uh bottom again not to the top and paste
it. We have to also invoke it. And now
we generate a new unique identifier.
Underneath the ID we also have to update
the is deleting state. This will be
false. And then for the file type as
mentioned this will be an image. So we
update our file state. That's great.
This means our file is in our state
itself. But I want to also upload our
file. And to upload our file, I will
create a separate function. So I want to
go above this onrop function. And I want
to create a new function. This will be
called um how about upload file. Then we
can just open it. And that's it. As a
param, I want to get the file itself.
And this will be of type file because we
want to upload a singular file. You
can't upload arrays. You can only upload
singular objects and inside of here we
want to again first of all again update
our state because now uploading will be
true and the progress will still be
zero. So we can uh get for example or
not for example we can get our set file
state the function then we want to
invoke it as a param. I want to get my
previous state and then this will be an
inline callback function. We can
destruct and inside of here I can update
my state. So what exactly do we do right
here? Well, the set file state setter is
a function and this set file state as a
param gets our previous files or our
previous state. What does this mean?
Well, this previous is just a
representation of our current state.
It's pretty much the same thing as file
state. And I want to now keep my
previous items. This means I want to
spread my previous items. So all of my
previous properties, this means the
error will be still false. the file will
still be the file which I added here.
The ID will stay the same. I won't
update these fields but I want to update
the uploading boolean and this should be
true. And for the progress I will set it
to zero. I know we already set it to
zero in this uh onrop function.
Nevertheless, I want to also do it
inside of here. So again this set file
state updates our state itself. this
previous
param I guess yeah that's how I will
call it is the local representation of
our state it's the exact same thing as
file state and then we just uh spread
our previous items this means the error
the file the ID the progress and stuff
like that we only up uh update two
properties and that's the uploading
property and the progress property
that's it groundbreaking it's quite
simple as you see and the next step is
to already upload our file trial. So I
will create a try catch statement and
for now in the catch statement I won't
do anything. We want to first of all get
started with the try statement. And
here's my question to you. How do you
upload a file in XJS through the server
side through the client side through the
server and client side? Well I want to
show you a little diagram. So your first
idea might be hey Jan let's upload the
file on the server side. I mean we have
Nex.js JS we have route handlers API
routes let's funnel the request through
the server sure let's look at this
diagram so we have a client you for
example you are the client and you make
a request to the server with a file so
you want to make an upload request the
server gets the request that analyzes
everything maybe arcjet analyzes the
request and says hey everything is fine
and then we forward the request to S3 so
we make an API request to S3 and we will
say hey S3 we want to upload this cool
file. S3 will take the file and it will
return the URL back to the client or the
key to be specific and then we are
finished, right? So, congrats. Great
idea. Actually, it's not a good idea.
Why is this not a good idea? Or in other
words, why is this not a good solution?
So, Nex.js has a body size limit. By
default, the maximum size of the request
body as sent to a server action is 1
megabyte. Now, you might say, "Hey, Jan,
who cares? We will use a route handler
and even if we would use server actions,
this is just the default. We can update
it to for example 10 megabytes. Why not?
Sure, good idea. So later on we will
deploy our application to Versel and
then we have a new problem. So Versel is
a serverless environment as you
hopefully and probably know. This means
it uses serverless functions to serve
your application. And the maximum body
size limit for the request body or the
response body of a versel function is
4.5 MGB. This means if you upload a file
which is bigger than 4.5 megabytes, it
will just fail and you can't update the
body size limit. 4.5 mgabytes is the
maximum. You can't do anything about it
because again this is a serverless
environment. it does not work or there's
no infinite body size limit. But now you
might say, "Hey Jan, you know what?
Forget Versell, forget serverless. Let's
upload or let's deploy our application
to a server full serverful provider." So
let's say Hetszna for example. He hats
now will give you a box and this is just
a full-on server and then you will and
then you won't have any body size limit.
Sure, this will work. But you don't
really want to upload a file through the
server side because with that you will
also create quite a big strain on your
memory on your bandwidth on just in
general you will take up quite a lot
resources just to upload your file on
the server side. So the client side is
way better because your machine won't
handle this file upload. You won't incur
any bandwidth or anything like that. So
now you might say then hey Jan so if you
say that the client is a better idea
then let's upload the file on the client
side why not sure so what we can do is
get a line let's scratch the server who
cares about the server and instead we
will make a direct request to S3 so this
is this white line the client make a
will make a request to S3 S3 will upload
the file and return the key to the
client great success we now don't have
any body size limits anymore we don't
strain stain our machine. So if we are
on a serverful deployment, we don't
strain our machine. And if we are
deployed on a serverless envir or in a
serverless environment, so if we
deployed our application using burcell,
then we won't hit any body size limits.
Great. But here comes the big butt. But
but but the client side is insecure. You
want to never do something like this on
the client side. You have to always
validate everything on the server side.
Because right now, if you give the user
direct access to S3, the user could
literally upload anything, a video, a
photo, some sort of malicious software.
You can't validate it because this is
the client side. This means we still
need the server side. We still need the
server side to validate the request to
validate the file to check that
everything is secure. And only if it's
secure, we want to then upload the file.
But again, this does not work. So we
need some sort of solution which still
gives us the ability to validate the
request on the server side and then
allow the user to upload the file on the
client side. H what could be a good
solution? Let me think about it. How
about we use pre-signed URLs? What are
pre-signed URLs? Well, let's look at
this diagram. A user, a client makes a
request to the server, an upload
request. The server analyzes the
request. that analyzes the file. Maybe
ArcJet analyzes everything and then the
server makes a request to S3, an API
call to upload the file. But instead of
uploading the file, we will instead ask
S3 for a pre-signed URL. This pre-signed
URL will be defined with some sort of
expiration time. Let's say 3 minutes. So
S3 will generate an URL which is valid
for 3 minutes. This URL will be returned
to the client and the client will then
upload the file on the client side using
this pre-signed URL. And again, this pre
why is this safe? Well, that's because
we validate everything on the server
side. This pre-signed URL will only
allow you to upload a file which um how
would you say it which has the correct
info because in the server we will
create this pre-signed URL and when we
generate the pre-signed URL we will say
hey the file will have a size of XYZ it
will have uh I don't know this and that
XY content type for example will be XYZ
so this pre-signed URL will have
specific data and then the user can only
upload a file which matches this uh
requirements that's the word that I was
looking for. So the client will only be
able to upload a file if the requ if the
file data the info matches the
requirements of this pre-signed URL and
that's why it's safe to use pre-signed
URLs and why it's also recommended
because again we don't put any strain on
our server and we still upload on the
client side and we validate everything
which means we want to use pre-signed
URLs. Yoohoo!
My god, cringe. Okay, guys, drink some
water. This was quite an explanation.
So, this means we can go back to our
application. And what I want to do is
create a new route handler. This route
handler will generate a pre-signed URL.
We will then use the pre-signed URL to
upload our file on the client side. And
once that's done, we will be pretty much
finished at least with the basic uh
functionality. So I want to first of all
create a route handler as already
mentioned. This means we want to go into
our app folder and then in the app
folder I want to create a new folder or
we already have the API folder and in
the API folder I want to create a new S3
folder and then in the S3 folder I want
to create a child folder and this will
be called what could be a good name
maybe upload. Yes, S3 upload. And then
for the upload folder I want to create a
new file and this will be route.ts.
So in this file or in this route handler
in this API route we will generate the
pre-signed URL. And I think you all know
what route handlers are because we
already discussed it at the start. So
inside of here I want to create an
export function or this should be an
async function. And here's the important
thing. We have a few request methods
right? You have a post request, get
request, put request, delete request,
and a few other requests. But these are
the four main requests. What request are
we trying to do right here? Delete. I
don't think so. Get I don't think so.
It's post. We want to do something. We
want to pretty much create a mutation.
So, this will be then uppercase post.
And then we can just open this function.
And if a user or we could say if a
malicious user tries to make a request
here using for example a get request
this won't accept it. So we only allow
post requests and in the params I can
also get a request object and this will
be of type request. Inside of here we
can first of all create a try catch
statement for error handling. So inside
of here I want to first of all get the
body itself. This means we can create a
constant body or and with body I mean
the request body right? I think you
understand what I mean. And then this
will be equal to await request.json.
And then I want to invoke it. So here's
the thing. Our body or later on we will
pass for our body the file name content
type size and then also if it's an image
or a video. This means I can create a
zot schema and we will then validate the
body against the zot schema. Because
currently there's no type safety. If I
say body dot, you see I don't get
anything. That's why we will use a zot
schema. This means we will hit two birds
with one stone. Is this the correct
saying? I'm not sure. But we will first
of all validate everything on the server
side. And secondly, we will get type
safety. So above the export function, we
can create a new export constant. This
will be called file upload schema and
this will be equal to z.object.
Z is imported from zot. So on top I can
create an import statement. The
structured and this will be from zot.
Then where we d the structured we can
get z itself and then as mentioned again
this will be z.object
and then we want to invoke it and the
structured. So what properties do I want
to get from my body or what properties
will I pass. First of all the file name
itself and the file name will be of type
z.string.
We can also add further validation. This
means dot minimum. This will be one at
least one character and then I want to
of course return a message an error
message and this is or this will be file
name is required. Then I want to also
pass content type. So is this a video?
Is this a PNG? Is this a JPEG? Whatever
this will be also of type Z.string we
want to invoke it and do further
validation dot minimum one. And for the
error message this will be I don't know
maybe content type is required. Then
what else are we missing? Well we are
also missing the size itself or that's
what I want to pass and the size will be
of Z or of type Z dot number. I want to
invoke it again. Further validation dot
minimum one. And for the error message
this will be size is required. This is
finished. And then there's one more
property and this is the is image
boolean. So is image will be equal to Z
dot boolean and then we can invoke it.
And we need this because I want to then
later on dynamically update the file
size limit because for example a video
should be or or I not a video an image
should have a max size of 5 MGB. A video
for example 10 GB. So that's a huge
difference. So that's why we need this
boolean. And since I created my Zot
schema I can now also validate my body
against this Zot schema. So we can
create a constant. This will be called
validation and this will be equal to
file upload schema dots save pass and as
an argument we want to pass the body. So
this save pass um method won't throw any
error. Instead this validation will now
have two um could you say results? Yeah
I think this makes sense. So the
validation could either be successful or
it could be failed. If it's failed then
this means that for example we did not
add a content type or a size. If it's
successful then this means that our form
data or our body compares correctly
against our Z schema. So underneath the
validation I want to create an if
statement and I want to say hey if the
validation do success is not true. So we
do that with this exclamation mark. So
if it's not successful then I want to
return an error message. So return next
response. Next response is imported from
next/server.json
JSON and then as an argument we want to
pass the error message itself. So we can
structure it and for the error itself
this will be invalid request body and
then I want to also pass the status. So
after this object I can create another
object and this will be a status of 400.
This means it failed. If the validation
was successful we can of course get our
types. This means I can create a
constant the structure and this will be
equal to validation dot data and then
where we the structure we can get the
file name the content type and also the
size. So what's the next step? Well the
next step is to finally generate our
pre-signed URL. But to generate a
pre-signed URL we need a S3 bucket. But
we don't have one right now. So here's
the thing. There are a lot of S3
providers. For example, AWS. I mean AWS
created S3. Of course, they also have an
offering. The only problem is it
requires a credit card. It's not free.
And that's why I won't use AWS in this
video. All of my videos are structured
the same. A credit card should not be
required. And since AWS requires one, we
won't use AWS. Cloudflare is a great
option. They offer R2. So, Cloudflare
R2. Cloudflare R2 is a global object
storage with zero egress Agress fees and
it's also S3 compatible and it's very
very affordable. Again, they have a free
tier. The only problem is it requires a
credit card. So sadly I can't use R2
even though the product is absolutely
great. That's why we will use in this
video Tigris. It's not called Tigris. I
thought that it's called Tigris but it's
called Tigris. So, Tigris is a globally
distributed S3 compatible object
storage. Now, I will use it in this
video because it does not require a
credit card and because it has a
generous free tier. That's it. It's not
This video is not sponsored by Tigris.
You can use any other service. I don't
care. I will only use it because it has
a free tier which does not require a
credit card. This does not mean that
Tigris is bad. No, it has very very
fancy technology or it has a very fancy
architecture and it's a very cool
product. So, Tigris is a globally
distributed S3 compatible object storage
service that provides low latency
anywhere in the world, enabling
developers to store and access any
amount of data for a wide range of use
cases. And the nice thing is again it
has zero egress fees. So, it's the same
thing as R2. It's S3 compatible and it's
globally available. And if I remember
correctly, it all of your files are also
behind a CDN, but I'm not sure with that
right now. It could I could be mistaken.
So, please don't take my word for that.
But without any further ado, we want to
first of all log in. I will continue
with Google. And then the first step is
to first of all create a new bucket. So,
we will click on create bucket. For the
bucket name, this will be marshall-l
video-subscribe.
Then this will be a public bucket. So
objects in this bucket will be publicly
readable. And then for the consistency,
this will be default. We can then click
on create. This will create our bucket.
And as you see success, nice. So what we
can do is first of all create new access
keys. So in the sidebar you will find
this access key section. We want to
click on it and we want to create a new
access key for the name. This will be
Marshall or yeah Marshall LMS key. Then
I want to also enable admin access. And
it says right here enabling admin
access. Give the access key admin
privileges to all the buckets in your
organization. I can then click on create
and I should get all of my keys right
here. So as you see we get an access key
ID, a secret key, an endpoint URL, an
endpoint URL I am and then also the
region. So we want to select environment
variables and we can then copy these
environment variables. So we want to
open our env file and just paste them
right here underneath the arcjet key. So
again this is the AWS access key ID, the
secret access key, the endpoint URL. And
even though we don't use AWS since it's
S3 compatible, we have this AWS uh
prefix. So I can save this. And as you
all know, we use T3 ENV for type safety,
which means I want to open the T3 file
or not T3 file, but the env.ts file. Um
I can open it right here on the left
side and then I will just do a bit of
copy pasting. So all of these
environment variables are on the server
side or they should only be accessible
on the server side. Which means in the
server object we can get our AWS access
key ID. This will be of type Z.string.
And then further validation dominimum
one. What else do we have? We have the
AWS secret key. Again I can just copy
paste it. This will also be of type
Z.string dot minimum and this will be
also one. And then we have the what was
this? The endpoint URL. I will copy it,
paste it. This will be of type z.tring.
And then dot minimum one. And then we
have the AWS endpoint URL. AM. I will
copy paste it. This will be of type Z
do. Dot minimum two. No one of course.
And then also the AWS region. And this
will be of type Z.S. And then dot
minimum one. So as a next step, I want
to generate the pre-signed URL. And to
generate it, we have to install two AWS
or S3 specific packages. And this is
first of all the AWS SDK client S3. So
this is the official AWS SDK for
JavaScript projects. It will allow us to
interact with the S3 API. And then we
also need the AWS SDK S3 request
pre-signer package. And this package
provides a pre-signer based on signature
v4 uh that will attempt to generate a
signed URL for S3. So we need this uh
this package to generate the URL the
pre-signed URL and this will be there to
just uh talk to the S3 API in general.
So I will link of course everything in
the YouTube description. Don't worry if
I forget it then please scream at me in
the comments. But we can first of all
copy the name which is AWS SDK client S3
and then AWS request pre-signer. So as
you see I pasted everything in my
terminal pnpmi package one package two
and if I click on enter everything
should I hope install and yes it worked.
This means we can again restart our dev
server and what we have to first of all
do is create a new S3 client because we
have to configure S3. we have
environment variables and these
environment variables have to be used
somewhere. This means we can go into our
lip folder in our root directory and we
want to create a new S3 client.ts file.
Inside of here I can create an export
constant. This will be S3 and then this
will be equal to new S3 client. S3
client does not import for me
automatically. I'm not sure what's
wrong. So I will do it manually. import
I can d the structure and then this will
be from AWS SDK client S3 where I d the
structure I want to get the S3 client
and then again we can say new S3 client
we can invoke it and the structured
inside of here we have to provide three
properties first of all the region the
region will be auto then we want to also
pass the end point and what will the
endpoint be good question we can go back
to our Tigris dashboard And inside of
here you will find the endpoint URL S3.
So what we can do is just use our
environment variable. I will get the ENV
variable from the env file. And then I
want to get the S3 endpoint URL. So AWS
endpoint URL. And then we have to also
set the force path style property. And
this will be set to false. You don't
want to set it to true. This is super
important. So our S3 client is created
which is great. And before I continue
using it, I want to do a bit of
optimization. So here's the thing. This
S3 client should only run on the server
side. It should never run on the client
side and it should never be called on
the client side or from the client side.
This means we have to somehow tell
Nex.js that this is a server only client
or that this code should only run on the
server. And thankfully Nex.js has a very
nice helper. So let me quickly go to the
documentation and here you will find a
section preventing environment
poisoning. Oh no poisoning. So
JavaScript modules can be shared between
both server and client components
modules. This means it's possible to
accidentally import server only code
into the client. For example, consider
the following function. So here they get
data and as you see they also pass an
authorization header with an API key and
this API key should never be exposed to
the client. But if I call this on the
client side then this code will run. You
don't want that. So what we want to do
is we want to prevent accidental usage
in client components and for that we can
use the server only package because the
server only package will create a
buildtime error if the code or if the
function or in this case our S3 client
if it will be imported in or it will be
used in a client component and this
server only package is installed by
default. This means we can go back and
just go to the top and then import
server only. Again, this is already
installed. I don't have to do anything.
And again, in short, this just says,
hey, this function, this code, this
whatever should only run on the server
side and should only be called from the
server side. If this is called in a
client component, it will throw an error
at build time. If I don't add the server
only, we will only get an error at
runtime and you don't want that. So we
can also do that for the rest of our lip
files. So for example, this resend
configuration or resend in general
should only run on the server side. So I
will import server only. Then for the
env file, this is fine. For our DB in
theory, I can also import server only.
This should only run on the server side.
Then for the off configuration file,
sure also import server only. Then how
about the off client? Yes, this should
only run on the client side. So I don't
have to add that. And for ArcJet, I want
to also import server only because it
should only run on the server side. And
yeah, I think that's it to be quite
honest with you. Maybe I forgot
something, but I don't think so. So
since we have our S3 client, we can also
use it in our S3 upload route. So to get
started, we want to first of all create
a put object command. And this put
object command will be there to specify
our file content. And in there we will
for example define the bucket. So but
which bucket we will use to upload our
file. Then for example the key. So we
have to generate a unique key. The
content type and content length. So the
put object command is pretty much just
an object. And then this object will be
passed to S3 to upload the file or to
generate the pre-signed URL. If this
currently confuses you, don't worry. It
will make sense in a second. So
underneath this constant file name, we
can create a new constant. This will be
command and this will be equal to new
put object command. Put object command
is imported from AWS SDK client S3. We
want to invoke it and the structured
inside of here we get a few properties.
First of all the bucket and what will it
be equal to? Good question. We can head
over back to the tigress dashboard and
then here we get our buckets. We already
created one as you know and this here is
my bucket name Marshall LMS YouTube
video subscribe. This means I can just
copy this bucket name. Then I want to go
back to my env
file and I want to paste it inside of
here. So here's the thing. I will use
this bucket later on on the client side
and it's also completely safe to use
this bucket name on the client side. But
if I just create an environment variable
using this uh spelling. Does this make
sense? Is this is this using this
definition? Whatever man, if I use this,
it will only run on the server side. So
this environment vable will only be
accessible on the server side. But my
bucket name should be accessible on the
client side. This means we want to
prefix the environment variable with
next_public
and then underscore S3 and I will call
it bucket_ame
[Music]
images. So the whole environment
variable name will be next_public
s3_bucket_ame
images and this will be equal to the
value which I just copied. Then I can
copy the environment variable name. I
want to open my env file and then we
want to pass it inside of here. But we
don't want to pass it into the server
object because this is not a server
environment variable but instead this is
a client environment variable. This
means underneath the server we can get
the client. This is an object and then I
want to pass my next public s3 bucket
name images and this will be equal to Z
dot string and then dot minimum one. As
you see we get one error. What's the
problem right here in experimental
runtime? Well the problem is that we
have to destructure the client
variables. So we can again get this next
public S3 bucket name images and this
will be equal to process.env env
next public s3 bucket name images. As
you see I get one error and that's
because I forgot the comma here and now
everything is fine. I can close the env
files and then for our bucket we can get
the env variable from the env file and
then the s3 bucket name. So bucket name.
Then the second property will be the
content type and content type will be
equal to the one which we get from our
body. So content type is equal to
content type. Then we also have a
content length property and this will be
equal to the size which we get from our
body. And then there's one more property
missing and that's the key and this is
uppercased. So what exactly is the key?
Well, I already mentioned it at the
start but you probably already forgot
it. So the key is the unique identifier
which will uh which S3 will use to
identify your file. It's an ID in simple
terms. So this will then be stored in
your bucket. So let me show it to you.
If I upload a file for example, I can
click on uh browse. Then I will upload
not this video, not this, not this, but
this file. And as you see, this is my
file key. This is the unique identifier.
But this is not very unique because what
is if a user uploads another file with
the same name, we will get an error. We
don't want that. Therefore, we can't
just use the file name. So we get our
file name right here. But again, this is
not unique. We need something very
unique. So what could be an idea? What
could be a solution? Well, as you all
know, we installed this UYU ID package.
This means I can copy the import
statement. I can paste it on top and we
will use this ID or UU ID package
function. In other words, to generate a
unique key. So above the command, I want
to create a constant unique key. And
this will be equal to optics. Then we
can use this dynamic value. And inside
of here, we want to get the UYU ID V4
function. we can invoke it and then this
will be a dash or I want to pass a dash
after this and then I want to append the
file name. So file name which we get
from our body. So at the end our whole
unique key will look something like a
lot of jibush this will be the unique
identifier dash and then for the file
name I don't know 2024.jpeg
this will be our unique key which we
will use to then get our file but also
to uh to identify it. So for the key I
can just pass unique key. I forgot to
say key. So I will copy it and paste it
for the key. And this is already it. Our
put object command is finished and we
can use it and supply it to our um
serer. So we want to now generate a
signed URL. This means underneath
constant command I can create a new
constant. This will be pre-signed URL
and then this will be equal to a rate
get signed URL. As you see it does not
import for me automatically sadly. This
means I will go to the top and then
inside of here I want to create an
import. I will the structure and this
will be uh from AWS SDK. So at AWS S3
request pre-signer and then where I
structured I want to get the get signed
URL function. We can then again get our
get signed URL function and we want to
invoke it and we have to pass three
arguments. First of all, our S3 client
S3 is imported from our lip folder.
Please make sure that you import it also
from the lip folder. The second argument
is our put object command. This means
our command in general. And the third
argument is the expiry time. This means
we can open an object. And here we get
the expires in property. And this will
be equal to 306
360 seconds or in other words 6 minutes.
I will create a comment and say URL
expires in 6 minutes. So this means this
function will generate a pre-signed URL.
We pass the S3 client to talk to the S3
API. We pass the command to specify the
type of our file and also the bucket and
stuff like that. And we pass an expires
in property to tell the URL to expire in
a certain time frame. In this case, 6
minutes. After 6 minutes, this URL won't
work anymore, which is nice. And then
underneath this constant pre-signed URL,
I want to now return it. So, we can
create a constant response. This will be
equal to an object. And inside of here,
I want to pass the pre-signed URL, but
also the key. And this means we can pass
a key, and this will be equal to the
unique key. So, the response is
finished, which means we can also return
it. So, let's create a return next
response.json.
And as an argument, we want to return
the response or we want to pass it. Then
we also have a catch statement. And
inside of here, I want to just return
some sort of error message. So we can
say return next response.json.
Then as an argument, we want to pass an
object. For the error message, I will
say failed to generate pre-signed or
yeah pre-signed URL. And then we want to
also pass a status. This means a new
object. And for the status this will be
500. This means again something failed
terribly. So since this route handler is
finished, what do you think we can do?
Well, we can finally get our pre-signed
URL in our uploader function. This means
I will go back to the uploader. We can
scroll a bit to the bottom and we want
to go into the try statement. So the
first step is to first of all get the
pre-signed URL. So we can create a
comment and we can say step number one
get pre-signed URL. So how can we get
our pre-signed URL? Well, it's quite
simple. We want to fetch this route
handler or we want to use fetch to fetch
this route handler. So we can create a
constant pre-signed response and this
will be equal to await fetch. We want to
invoke it and as an argument we have to
provide the URL of the route handler.
The route handler URL will be /appi.
Then where do we have it? App folder. So
slappi/s3
/upload. So I can uh paste it right here
again /appi
/ s3 /upload and then we have to also
provide or pass a bit of configuration
which means we can add a comma open an
object and first of all we have to pass
the method. What was the method? Well it
was get no it was post as you see. So we
can copy it and paste it right here
post. Then we have to pass headers and
then in the headers I want to pass the
content type. In this case, the content
type will be application JSON. And this
is also the most common content type.
And underneath the headers, we want to
pass the body. Now, this will be equal
to JSON dot stringify because we want to
stringify it. And then we can invoke it
and open an object inside of here. So,
what properties do we want to pass?
Well, we want to pass a file name,
content type, size, and is image, which
is a boolean. So I can copy the file
name and paste it inside of here. This
will be equal to file.name.
Then we had our content type. I can copy
it, paste it, and this will be of type
or this will be equal to file.ype.
Then what else did we have? We also had
the size. I can copy it, paste it, and
this will be equal to file dot size. And
then we had one more boolean which is is
image. And this image will be set to
true. Again I will later on make a
dynamic but for now this is fine enough.
Then we can create an if statement
because it could be that this pre-signed
response is not successful. And also we
currently get an error. So before we do
that we first of all have to fix this
await error. So await expressions are
only allowed with an async functions but
this function is not asynchronous. So
this will be an asynchronous uh function
upload file. this error will go away
which means we can now create the if
statement. So underneath the pre-signed
response I will create an if statement
and if pre-signed response is not okay.
So you do that with the exclamation mark
then we want to first of all return a
toast. This means I can open it. I can
get my toast dot error. And for the
message, this will be failed to get
pre-signed URL. And then we want to also
update our state because again if I go
to my state, we have an error boolean
and this is set to false. But we want to
update it and set it to true. This means
what we can do is copy the set file
function set file state and then I can
paste it underneath the toast. So we
will again spread our previous
properties. Uploading will now be set to
false. Progress will be set to zero. And
then error will be set to true. And also
to not continue any further. I want you
also then return it at the end. So if
this response was not successful, we now
return a toast and we also update our
state. If everything was successful, we
can go underneath this if statement and
then we want to get the pre-signed URL
and the key because again this is what
we return in this object pre-signed URL
and key. So I can create a constant I
want to the struct and this will be
equal to a pre-signed response.json.
As you see we don't get any TypeScript
types. That's fine. We can just go back
copy the pre-signed URL paste it inside
of here and then also our key. So this
means we now return our response with
the pre-signed URL and key and I get it
in my actual uploader uh component and
we can use the pre-signed URL to finally
upload our file to our S3 bucket. So
let's do it. We are almost finished. So
as the next step we want to finally
upload all of the files to this pres to
S3 using this pre-signed URL. As you all
know I want to also track the progress.
So I have this progress property and I
want to store the uploaded percentage.
Now here's the thing you might say how
about we just upload the file using
fetch. The problem is fetch does not
provide us with progress tracking uh for
uploads and this is a huge problem. So
what's a solution? Well, one solution
would be to use Axios because Axios
gives us support or it allows us to
track the progress of an upload. But
here's the thing. I will only use Axios
to track the progress of an upload. This
is stupid. You don't want to install
packages just to do one small thing. So,
is there any native way to track the
progress of our upload? Yes, there is.
Because Axios uses XHR in the background
and XHR is an alternative to fetch. It's
like the older brother. It's I mean
fetch is nicer but I guess we will have
to use XHR. So XHR or how it's actually
called XML HTTP request objects are used
to interact with servers. You can
retrieve data from a URL without having
to do a full page refresh. This enables
a web page to update just part of a page
without disrup uh disrupting what the
user is doing. We don't really care
about all of this. At the end of the
day, XHR will just help us to send data
to a server and while doing that, it
will also allow us to track the progress
and also as they say right here, despite
its name, so XML, it can still be used
to retrieve any type of data. It does
not have to be XML. And what's the
difference to fetch? You might ask me.
Well, again, fetch is just the newer and
better version of you could say XML or
XHR. The biggest difference is is this
is that fetch does not allow you to
track the upload progress. As you see,
no upload. XHR allows you to do that.
Fetch only allows you to track a
download but not an upload. And that's a
huge problem. So that's why we will use
XHR. But thankfully it's not that hard
to set up. But you will have to create a
lot of boilerplate code. And that's also
the reason why we now have fetch.
Nevertheless, underneath this pre-signed
blah blah blah thing, we can create a
new promise. So, await new promise and
then as a param or we will get two
params. First of all, resolve and then
also reject. So, we will then either
resolve the whole request or we will
reject the request if there's some sort
of error. Then this is just a standard
call back or error function. And inside
of here, we want to first of all
initialize XHR. So we want to create a
constant XHR and this will be equal to
new XML or XML HTTP request. We want to
then invoke it. And now we already set
up XHR. So what we want to do or how XHR
works is is that you listen for events.
So for example, we want to listen for
the on progress event. This will give us
the progress percentage. Then we want to
listen for the onload event. This is
once everything is finished and stuff
like that. So again a lot of boiler
plate it's you have to write more code
than with fetch but again the end result
is the same. So we can say xhr uh
dotupload and then dot on progress
because we want to listen for the on
progress event. Then this will be equal
to a standard arrow function. So I can
just open it and as a param right here
we also get the event itself and this
event will periodically run. So as our
file uploads it will run and it will
give us the progress percent I mean it
won't give us the progress percentage we
will calculate it but it will give us a
progress and we can then use it to
calculate our percentage. So inside of
here I can first of all create an if
statement and I want to check if we even
get a length computable. What does this
mean? Well let's imagine you want to
upload a file 5 megbytes. How do you or
how will you track the progress? Well,
you need the total size and the
currently uploaded size. So, as an
example, let's say you want to upload a
5 mgabyte file and you already uploaded
2 mgabytes. You can then divide 2 by 5,
this will give you 0.4. If you calculate
or if you multiply this by 100, you will
get 40. This means you uploaded your
file 40%. And to calculate this, as you
see, we have to get the total size.
That's why I check if we even get a
length computable because only if we get
a length computable I can calculate the
uploaded progress percentage. So we can
then open this and we want to first of
all get the percentage. So we can create
a constant. This will be percentage
completed and this will be equal to
parentheses and inside of here I want to
create the same code as I just did. This
means I want to get the loaded size. I
want to divide it by the total size and
then multiply it by 100 to get the
percentage. So we want to get the event
dot um loaded divided by event dot total
and then we want to multiply this by 100
and this will give us our percentage and
as you all know we want to then update
our state. This means I can just copy
the set files uh function setter and I
will paste it inside of here. We will
again uh spread our previous properties
but I want to update the progress
property and we want to first of all
round our number. So we can use math and
then I want to use the round method and
as an argument we will provide the
percentage completed constant. So this
again gets our percentage. We now round
the percentage and then pass it as a
property for the progress. So if this is
50% we will then pass 50 to the progress
and later on I will then just display a
percentage symbol and that's it. So this
is already our on uh on progress event
we now listen for it and this is
finished. We want to now listen for the
onload event. This means once our file
is finished uploading and this onload
event will either be successful or it
will be failed for reason XYZ. I don't
know what maybe a network issue or
something else. So what we want to do is
again use XHR. Then we want to listen
for the onload um event and this will be
equal to a standard error function.
Inside of here we want to create an if
statement because again the onload event
or our state yeah our result could
either be successful or not. This means
inside of here we will check if the
status so XHR. status is equal to 200 or
again we want to use two vertical lines.
If the xhr status is equal to 204, this
would also mean that everything was
successful. If this is true, then we can
open the if statement and we want to
first of all again update our state. So
I will copy the setter. I will paste it
inside of here. We want to again spread
our previous uh properties. Then I want
to update the progress. The progress
will now be 100 because the file was
successfully uploaded. The uploading
boolean will be set to false because our
file is not uploading anymore. And then
I want to also pass my key. Where do I
get my key from? Well, right here we got
our pre-signed or we got reawaited our
pre-signed response and we got the
pre-signed URL and key. We will use the
pre-signed URL in a second because again
this is event based. You then upload the
file at the end. But we already get the
key which I can just copy and then I can
paste it right here. So key will be
equal to key. That's already it. Don't
worry, we still get a few errors here.
That's fine. So we created our if
statement for if it's successful. But I
want to also then now return a toast. So
if it was successful, we can go
underneath that uh the set file state
then I want to get a toast. And then I
want to use the success toast and for
the message I will say file uploaded
successfully.
And then at the end we want to also call
resolve because our request is resolved.
But as you see I get an error. What's
the problem? Well, it already gives us
the uh you could say solution right
here. It says expected one argument but
got zero. Did you mean to include void
in your type argument? Yes, that's what
we want to do. We want to go to our
arate new promise. We want to add a new
generic and this will just be void. And
with that, this error will go away. And
by the way, this error annoys me quite a
bit. I think I misspelled this await new
promise. So I will just copy all of the
code in this await new promise and I
will just write this await new promise
one more time. So again we can go inside
of here. I will just copy the whole
content constant xhr. I will copy it. I
will delete this await new promise and I
will write it again. So await new
promise. Then inside of here I can
invoke it as a param. I want to get
resolve and also reject. And then I want
to just create a standard arrow
function. Uh I still get one error.
What's the problem? Promise. I want to
also pass a generic which will be void.
And if I again paste my content,
everything works. So I'm not sure what
mistake I made. But now everything again
works. And that's what we wanted. So we
are finished with this if statement. So
if everything was successful, but we
want to also check if it was not
successful. This means I can create an
else statement. And inside of here I
will just reject the response. So I can
call reject and then as an argument I
want to return a new error. This means
new error. Then I can invoke it. And as
a message I will just say upload failed.
So this is finished. This looks good. We
have finished with listening for the
onload event. And then we can also
listen for the onair event. So I want to
go underneath this if statement. And
then I can again get xhr.on
error. Again this is equal to a standard
error function and inside of here we
want to again reject the um request. I
can invoke this and inside of here again
we will create a new error. We want to
invoke it and for the message this will
be upload failed. So we have finished
with all of these events and as the next
step we can finally create our uh or we
can open our request. This means
underneath this on error I will create a
XHR dot open and inside of here we have
to provide two arguments. First of all
the method this will be put uppercase
put and then the second argument is the
destination the URL or in other words
the server in this case this is our
pre-signed URL. We want to upload our
file to this pre-signed URL. And again
this open is just a not formality but
you right now just configure your
request as a next step we want to set
our request header. So xhr set request
header we can invoke it for the first
argument this will be the content type.
So I will say uppercase so content- type
and for the second argument this will be
the file type. So file type and then the
last step is to send our request. This
means we can say xhr. send and we have
to provide one argument and what's the
argument? The argument is the body and
what's the body? The body is our file.
This means we can just pass our file as
an argument. Then as a next step we can
continue with our catch statement. This
means inside of here we want to first of
all render a toast. For the message this
will be something went wrong. And then I
want to also update my state because I
want to showcase an error or I want to
update the error boolean. So we can just
copy the setter which we already created
on top. I will copy it, paste it in the
catch statement. We want to spread all
of the previous properties. For progress
uh this will just be zero. Then for
uploading this I can just delete it. I
don't have to update it. For the key I
will also delete it. I want to just uh
update my error and the error will be
true. And then uploading I will set
uploading to false because we are not uh
uploading anymore. So I think this is
finished. So we created our whole
function upload file. We have hy catch
statement. We get our pre-signed URL. We
check that the response is okay. If not,
we return an error message. If
everything is fine, we get our
pre-signed URL. We then create a new
promise. We use XHR to track our
progress. We then calculate uh the
progress as a percentage. We put it into
state. We listen for the onload event.
If everything is successful, we update
our state. If not, we reject throw a new
error. Then we listen for the on error
event. We also return a new error. Then
we finally configure our request using
the open method set request header and
send. Then we also have a catch
statement where we catch an error if
there is even an error. Quite a lot of
code as you see quite a lot of boiler
plate but we have finally finished. So
we can head over back to our ondrop
function and I want to call the upload
file function. So underneath set files I
can get the upload file function I want
to call it and as an argument we have to
provide the file which we want to
upload. This means I can pass my file as
an argument. So for see it seems like
everything is fine to be honest which is
kind of cool. I did not expect it. I
thought we would create some sort of
error but no it looks good. So as the
next step I want to create a function
which will be called render content and
inside of there we will create a lot of
if statements. We will check is file
state uploading. If so then we want to
render our render uploading state. If
files if our file has an error then we
want to render our error state. If we
have a if we have an object URL I want
to upload the rendered state. And if we
don't have anything, we will render our
empty state. So what we can do is just
go above this uh use drop zone hook and
then I will create a function which will
be called render content. Inside of here
we uh we can create an if statement and
we want to check if our file is
uploading. So if file state dot
uploading if this is true then we want
to return our render uploading state. We
haven't created this component yet. So
instead I will return an H1 which says
uploading dot dot dot. If this is not
true then we can create another if
statement. So if and I want to check for
the error state. So if file state dot
error then we can open this and we want
to render our error state which we
already created. This means I can return
the render error state component
imported from the render state file.
Then underneath this if statement we
want to create another if statement. And
here we want to check if we generate an
object URL. This means I can create an
if statement and we can say if file
state has an object URL then I want to
return the render uploaded state. We
haven't created this component yet. So I
will render in H1 which says uploaded
file. And as the last return statement,
I want to render my empty state. I don't
have to create any if statements for
that. So I will just create a return
statement and I want to return the
render empty state. This is already
imported but as you see we get one
error. What's the problem? Well, we are
missing the is track active boolean. So
let's get is track active and this will
be equal to what is it? Is track active?
Who would have thought? So this looks
quite good and we can use this render
content function in our global return
statement because instead of hard coding
this render empty state I will instead
just use my render content function and
we want to call it this means I will
invoke it and you know what I think it's
time to test everything out I mean who
knows maybe it will work maybe not so I
will take a file I will drag and drop it
and uploading dot dot dot yeah that's
good but hm H that takes way too long. I
mean this was a small image and nothing
is updating. If I go to tigress to the
dashboard, do I get something here? No.
H
it's time to investigate. So again d we
have our upload function here. So we set
our state. We map over this. We set
uploading to true progress to zero. Then
we create a try statement. We right here
create our pre-signed response. We fetch
our route handler. Is this the correct
route handler? I mean, it has to because
if not, we would get an error here, but
we don't. Had looks fine. Body looks
fine. This also all looks fine. We have
an if statement. We check everything.
Yeah, this looks good. We also return
it. So, this shouldn't be the problem.
Then we get our pre-signed URL. And
since we get our uploading state, this
means that we are probably up or that we
probably upload our file. Hm. Await new
promise. Void resolve. Reject XHR. Yes,
this looks good. On upload. Dum. Dumb.
This also looks good. Onload. We open
it. We reject. We don't close it. Wait,
that's weird. On error, open. Ah. Oh my
god, I see the error. Okay, you see
onload. This unload opens. And then this
code on error open set request header
and send is written in this unload. This
of course shouldn't happen. So I can
copy the send set request open and on
error or all of these functions. I can
just copy them and paste them down
below. So they shouldn't live in the
onload um event function. Instead they
are their own events, their own thingies
if you their own functions in this case.
So if I save this and again go back this
should work. So if I take So if I take a
file, drag and drop it. Okay, we get an
error. But this is already better.
Something went wrong. Upload failed. So,
does our terminal give us any hints?
Nope. This all looks fine. How about our
console? This is also always a good
friend. Uh-huh. We get an error. So,
access to XHR at laala from origin LA
has been blocked by course policy. So,
what's the problem? Well, it's quite
simple. Since we are trying to upload a
file on the client side course directly
comes into play and blocks the request
because I mentioned already at the start
the client side is very unsafe and this
server this means tigris is protecting
itself. It does not uh it does not want
to allow any client to upload files. No,
we have to whitelist specific domains
which are allowed to upload on the
client side. So even though we have a
pre-signed URL, this is not enough. We
need to whitelist our own domain. So we
can go into the tigris dashboard. We
want to go into the bucket to the
settings. And then if you scroll a bit
to the bottom, you will find this course
configuration configuration section.
Yeah. And we want to add a new rule. So
for the origin, this will be localhost
3000. I can copy the URL and paste it
inside of here. Now please make sure
delete the slash at the end. This should
be localhost 3000 without any slashes or
anything like that. Then for the allowed
methods, this will be put, post, delete,
and get. That's it. For the allowed
headers, this will be a star. And for
the exposed headers, I will leave it
empty. I can then add the rule and also
save my configuration. This is also
important. And in theory, this should
all work. This means if I do a hard
refresh, take a file and drag and drop
it, I should upload the file. Yes,
uploaded file. File uploaded
successfully. And if I go into the
tigress dashboard, I should also see the
file. Nice. Oh my god, this worked so
well. That's so great. But we want to of
course update our render state because
uploaded file. Yep, that's great. But I
want to showcase the file and I want to
showcase a progress state. This means we
can go back to our render state
component. We already have a function
for the render empty state and for the
render error state. Now I want to also
create a function for the for example
let's say uploaded state. So we can
create an export function. This will be
called render uploaded state. We can
then open this function and inside of
here we can first of all create a return
statement and in the return statement a
standard diff element. So through my
params I want to get a few things. So we
can structure them and I want to get for
example the preview URL. This is the
object URL and then this should be
enough for now. I will add more things
later on but for now this is fine
enough. And the preview URL will have a
type of string. So this looks good. And
then in my div I can first of all render
an image component. This image is
imported from next / image. This is
self-closing as you all know. And this
image needs the source. So for the
source this will be our preview URL.
Then we want to also provide an alt and
this will be uploaded file. And I want
to also give this image a fill property.
So fill and then also a class name. And
this will be object contain. and also
padding too. This should already be
enough. And the only thing which I want
to also render is a delete button uh on
the top right corner. So we can go
underneath the image but still in the
div. And then we can use the button
component imported from the components
or it's already imported. Then I want to
give the button a variant. This will be
destructive. Also a size. This will be
icon. Then of course a class name. And I
want to use the CN helper function
because later on we will listen for this
deleting or is deleting boolean. This
means the CN helper function is already
imported. And we want to first of all
add default styles. So this will be
absolute because I want to position it
on uh on the top right corner. This
means absolute top four and right four.
This should be already enough. Uh we
will later on also add an on click
handler and a disabled state but we will
do that again later on. For the content
itself I want to just get the standard X
icon from Lucid React and let's also
give it a class name which will be size
4. This should already be enough and I
think we can test it out. So we can do a
hard refresh. I will again just drag and
drop some weird file and in theory I
should get the image but I don't get
one. What's the problem? Well, currently
if I go to my uploader, instead of using
this component which we just created, we
showcase an H1 or we render an H1. So,
we can delete this and instead we want
to get our what was it? Render uploaded
state. So, render uploaded state. This
is imported from the render state
components. And here we have to provide
one property. This is the preview URL
which will be equal to the file
state.object
URL. If I save this and go back. Oh my
god. What is this? This is our image. I
will cry in a second. I'm so happy. My
little child. No, my uploading state.
It's finished. It's beautiful. We have
this error button. Not error button,
this deletion button, which does not
work, but it's fine. We will fix it. In
general, it looks so good. But if I
again drag and drop a file, our
uploading state is still broken. As you
see, that's not quite what we want. So
we want to create another component for
uploading. So I will go to the render
states fi uh file where we store all of
our components and then we can create
another function. So I will create an
export function. This will be called
render uploading state. We can then just
open this function and I want to get in
the param to properties or I want to get
two params. This is the progress and
then also the file. So this means we can
just structure this. Then I as mentioned
I want to get progress and then also the
file. We can also give it a type. So
progress will be of type number and file
will be of come on tell me it file will
be of type file. Yes, you're right. So
this looks good. And then in the
function we can first of all open it and
then we can return a standard div
element. So diff or I have to first of
all create a return statement. Then we
can return a div. For the div we can or
let's style the div. So let's give it a
class name. This will be text center
flex justify center and item center
because we want to center everything in
the middle and then also flex column
because this should be a column layout
not horizontal layout. In this div I
want to first of all display an
uploading text or yeah uploading text.
So I will get a p tag and then say
uploading dot dot dot. We can also give
it a class name and then this will be
margin top two because we will render
something above this P tag in a second.
Then text which will be SM font which
will be medium. I think you all know
what these basic styles are. They are
not groundbreaking. Text SM makes the
text smaller. Font medium makes the font
weight bigger and then also text which
will be foreground. So uh the foreground
color um underneath the uploading P tag
I want to then also render the file
name. So underneath it this means we can
just get a standard P tag inside of
here. We can get the file dot name and
we want to also style it. So let's give
it a class name margin top one text
which will be XS text which will be
muted foreground muted foreground. This
means this grayish color and then also
tranate or yeah truncate. What does this
mean? Well, this means if the text or
the file name takes too much width, it
will just create this dot dot dot. So it
won't overflow or anything like that.
And also I want to add a maximum width
to not make it too big. So maximum width
which will be XS. So again truncate will
create these three little dots and a
maximum width will just limit the width.
I mean yeah not nothing groundbreaking.
Also above this uploading text for now I
will just get a standard P tag and then
render the progress itself. So we can
test it out. We can copy the name render
uploading state. We want to go to the
uploader. Instead of returning this H1,
we want to return the component. This
means render upload uploading state.
This is self-closing. We have to provide
two properties. First of all, the file.
This will be equal to the file state dot
file. And for the progress tracker, this
will be equal to our file
state.progress.
As you see, I get one error and it says
type file or null is not assignable to
type file. Yeah, in theory this does not
work because in the render state we
expect the file but our file state says
that the file could either be null or it
could be defined. Who would have
thought? And the thing is sure at the
start it's null. But once we start this
upload file process, it will be set to
true or we will get a file. Therefore, I
will do something that you shouldn't do
too often and I will just say as file
because I know that the file will exist.
This is fine to do. So you can do it. So
this is in theory already it. So how
about we test it out? I will do a hard
refresh just to delete this file again.
And then I want to again get a new file.
Let's do something else. This one I will
drag and drop it. Oh, okay. I didn't see
much. So how about we just um make this
whole network request a bit slower. I
will throttle my response. So I guess
let's again test it out. I will take a
file. I will drag and drop it and file
size exceeds the limit. Oh my god, dude.
Okay. Uh how about this file? Okay, did
you see this little progress tracker?
Wasn't this great? We can again try out
hard refresh and zero D and then we get
what's that? Okay, who cares? You saw we
got this little percentage symbol. And
here's something very very cool which I
implemented so please thank me. And
that's the object URL. So here's the
thing. Where do we define our object
URL? Well, we define it in our onrop.
So, we have our onrop function and then
we already put our create object URL in
state. So, we do it inside of here. In
theory, you could also do it down below.
You could just say right here, create
object URL and then pass the file in
there and then it will also create the
URL. And that's a mistake that a lot of
people do. But here's the thing. We have
progress tracking implemented. our
number updates and this means this
content here rerenders 100 times and if
I would create a create object URL
inside of here. So if I would create
this URL then I would also rerender this
file this image at 100 times. I would
recreate this image URL 100 times. But
if I put it right here in state right at
the start then I won't rerender it. I
will create it once and that's it. But
here's one thing which I haven't talked
about and that's that this create object
URL creates an URL. This is great. The
only problem is where's the stored? This
is stored in memory. So if you create
one trillion images, so if you allow the
user to upload one trillion images and
if you don't clean up these URLs, well
then you will have a memory leak. You
don't want that. This means once a file
is uploaded and then maybe later on
deleted or not used anymore, you want to
also revoke this object URL. This means
we can go to our ondrop function. Where
is our onrop function? Is it on the top?
My god. Upload file. No, here we have it
onrop. And before we set our file state,
we want to check if we have already an
object URL. If so, we want to revoke it.
We want to clean up our memory. This
means we can create an if statement and
inside of here I want to check if we
have our file state.object URL and this
means two and signs if there's no file
state dotobject URL dot start with and
then HTTP. What is meant with the starts
with HTTP? Good question. How does an
object URL look like? It does not look
something like this. No, instead it
starts with a blob and then colon HTTP.
And that's why we check if the file or
if the object URL starts with HTTP
because if it starts with a standard URL
then this means the file is uploaded and
we display a remote URL. You cannot uh
revoke or you cannot clean up a remote
URL. You want to only clean up your own
URLs which start with this blob. And
that's why we check that it does not
start with HTTP with this exclamation
mark. We can then open this if statement
and inside of here I want to use the URL
interface. I want to use the revoke
object URL method and as an argument we
have to provide the URL. This means the
file state file stateobject
URL. And as you see we get one warning.
So react hook use callback has a missing
dependency file state.object URL either
included or remove the dependency array.
So we will move or we will add the file
state object URL into the dependence
into the dependency array. This is
great. And then I want to create another
use effect to clean uh to also clean up
my object URL. Why do we need that? So
in this or on top we only revoke the
object URL when we drop a new file into
our drop zone. But I want to also revoke
the object or the file URL if our
component is unmounted. This means what
we can do is go underneath the on drop.
We can go underneath the rejected files
underneath this render content. So just
above this uh this used drop zone I will
create a use effect hook. So use effect
this is imported from react as you all
know. Then I want to invoke it inside of
here as you all know a standard arrow
function. And then we want to create a
return. This will be equal to an arrow
function. Return error function. And
then we can again create the same if
statement. So I can go back to the on uh
drop function. I can copy this if
statement with file state object URL and
does not start with HTTP. I will copy it
and paste it into the if statement. If
this is true then we will just revoke
the object URL. So when the component
unmounts but we have to also add a
dependency array. So at the end I can
add a comma then open an array and we
want to you could say listen uh for the
file state.object object URL and that's
already it. We now clean up or we
prevent memory leaks. That's what we do
in reality. So you know what we are
almost finished and there's only one
more thing which we have to implement
and that's file removal. So deleting
files this means we can go underneath
our onrop function for example and then
uh underneath it I want to create a new
function handle remove file. So function
uh handle remove file. This should be
also an async function. So async
function and inside of here we want to
first of all create an if statement. So
if we are already deleting a file or if
we don't have an object URL then we want
to just break pretty much. We don't want
to continue. So if file state dot is
deleting or double vertical line if
there's no file stateobject URL then
let's just return it. This means we will
stop. We won't continue any further.
Then as the next step we want to create
a try and catch statement. In the try
statement I want to first of all update
again my state. So I can go into the
upload file function and I will just
copy the set file state setter. I can
then go into the try statement and again
paste it inside of here. We want to
spread our previous items and then we
want to set is deleting to true because
we're now deleting the file. Underneath
the set file state, we want to make a
response to a route handler to delete
our file. This means we want to first of
all create a new route handler. In the
app folder, in the API folder, in the S3
folder, we can create a new folder and
this will be delete. So we have an
upload folder and the delete folder. In
the delete folder, we want to create a
route.ts. And as you all know, we have
to now first of all define our request
or our function, I guess. So export
async function. This will be uppercase
delete and then we can open it. Inside
of the params we want to get a request
and this will be of type uppercase
request. Inside of here we can create a
try and catch statement. And then in the
try statement we want to first of all
get the body. So constant body equals to
await request dobody. From the body I
want to get the key because how can we
delete a file from S3? Well, to delete a
file, we need this unique identifier.
And the unique identifier is our key.
And also, I get an error and it says
cannot invoke an object which is
possibly null. That's because I don't
want to get the body, but JSON H silly
mistake. And then inside of here, we
want to get the key from our body. So,
constant key will be equal to body.key.
We don't have to create a Z schema right
here. This is fine enough for uh I guess
getting our value. I don't need type
safety right here. Nevertheless, we want
to validate it. We want to check that we
get a key. This means we want to create
an if statement and we want to say, hey,
if there's no key, then let's open this
and let's return a next response.json.
So, return next response.json,
I want to invoke it. And inside of here,
I want to return an object with an
error. This for the error, I will say
missing or invalid object key. And then
I can add a comma open another object
and for the status this will be 400.
This means something went wrong. Not
good. So what's the next step? Well the
next step is to again create an object.
So when we uploaded our file. So if I go
to the upload route.ts you will see that
we created a put object command. But now
we want to create a delete object
command. So let's create a constant
command. This will be equal to new
delete object command. This is imported
from the AWS SDK. We can then invoke
this the structured and inside of here
we have to provide two key properties.
First of all the bucket and this will be
equal to our env. This means we want to
get the envable from the lip folder and
then dot next public s3 bucket name
images. And we want to also provide the
key and this will be equal to the key.
And the next step is to use this command
this object pass it to our client S3
client and delete the file. This means
we can say await s3 s3 is imported from
our lip folder. Please make also sure
that you imported from the lip folder
dot send and as an argument we want to
provide the command underneath this we
want to return a successful message.
This means return next response.json
JSON for the message. This will just be
file deleted successfully. And of
course, we want to also return a status.
And the status will be 200, meaning
everything was great. And in the catch
statement, we want to also return a next
response.json. I can just copy this one
and paste it inside of here. For the
error message, this is fine. And for the
status, this will be 500. So we created
our route handler which means I can go
back to the app uh to the uploader
component and I want to call this route
handler. So we can create a constant
response and this will be equal to await
fetch as an argument. We have to provide
the URL and this will be / API/s3
/delete. Then we want to add a comma
open an object and we have to pass the
method. In this case the method will be
uppercase delete. Then we have to also
pass headers and headers will be content
type JSON or application JSON. You can
just copy it from your upload file
function. And then we want to also pass
the body. And for the body again this
will be JSON dot stringify. We want to
invoke it the structured and we have to
provide the key and the key will be
equal to the file state key. So this
already looks beautiful and then we have
to do a bit of error handling. So
underneath this constant response we
want to again check if the response was
successful. This means if the response
was not okay exclamation mark response.
Then we want to open this and return
first of all a to host. For the message
this will be failed to remove file from
storage. And then we want to also update
the state itself. So I can copy the set
file state. I want to paste it inside of
here. And we want to set is deleting to
true. And also error this will be set to
true because we now have an error. And
at the end of course we want to create
an empty return because we don't want to
continue um yeah we don't want to
continue with the try statement if this
makes sense. Then as a next step I want
to again clean up my preview URL because
we now delete it in file which means we
also don't need this preview URL. We
don't need it to take up our memory. So
what we can do is for example go to the
use effect hook and copy this if
statement. So if we have an object URL
and if it does not start with HTTP we
will revoke the object URL and the last
step is to set our file state. So I will
again copy the set file state. I will
paste it down below. I will delete
everything and I want to set everything
again. So file will be null. Uploading
will be false. progress will be zero.
Object URL this will be undefined. Then
we also have the error itself. This will
be false because everything was
successful. The file type for now I will
hardcode it and this will be image. The
ID this will be null and is deleting
will be false because we are not
deleting the file anymore. And the last
thing which I want to do is return a
successful toast. So toast do.Success
and for the message this will be file
removed successfully. In the catch
statement we want to also return an
error toast. This means toast dot error
and for the message this will be our
removing file dot please try again. And
then of course we want to also update
our state. This means I can for example
copy the set file state. I can also
delete the previous from here. We don't
need it. I will again just copy it.
paste it down below underneath the toast
and as a param I want to get previous
here we will need it I will delete
everything inside of here we want to
spread our previous items uh but as is
deleting will be set to false and error
will be set to true okay this is
finished handle remove file is finished
and we can use it to delete our file so
here's the thing where do we render this
button the delete button well in the
render states file we have to render
uploading state component we don't need
it but we need the render uploaded state
component because here we have the
deletion button this means in my params
I want to get a few more things I want
to get the is deleting boolean and also
handle removal this will be a function
or handle let's say handle remove file I
think this is better we want to then
also add all of the types this means is
deleting this will be set to boolean
this is the type and then handle remove
file. This will be a standard function.
This means an error function which will
result in void. As you see, we get two
errors and that's because we don't use
these values. So, what do you think?
It's time to use them. So, I want to
update my button first of all. For the
button, I want to add an on click
handler. And this onclick handler will
be equal to handle remove file. And then
we want to also add a disabled state.
And this will be equal to is deleting.
So if is deleting is true, the button
will also be disabled. And then we can
also create a turnary for the content.
So if is deleting is true, we can use a
question mark. I want to return the
loader to icon. This is imported from
lucid react and it's self-closing. Then
for the class name, this will be size 4
and animate spin. And then if this is
not true, if we are not deleting, I will
just again render this X icon. So this
means we can go back and as you see we
get one error. What's the problem? Well,
if we go back to our function render
states, you will see that we get an
error for the render uploaded state
component. And why is that? Well, we are
missing two properties. First of all,
handle removal file. This will be equal
to the function which we just created.
Handle remove file. I will copy the name
and paste it inside of here. As you see,
we still get an error and that's because
we are also missing is deleting and is
deleting will be set to um file state is
deleting. So, what do you think? Is it
time to test it out? I think so. So, if
I drag and drop the file, file size
exceeds the limit. Okay, different file.
This one. Okay, we get the state file
uploaded successfully. And if I click on
this button, it's disabled. And then
this also looks great. As you see, I
just got this problem. my drop zone also
could you say invoked so it again opens
my finder this shouldn't happen because
my drop zone should be um disabled if
I'm uploading a file but also if I'm uh
deleting a file this means in the use
drop zone hook where we structured we
can get the disabled property and this
will be equal to file state dot
uploading or double vertical line if uh
for example we have an object URL so I
want to use two exclamation marks and
then file state dot object URL and what
is this double exclamation mark well
this converts the state or this look the
object URL is a string but we don't
really want to check if we have a string
we want to check for a boolean right so
if we have an object URL then this
should be disabled and using this double
exclamation mark I convert the value
into a boolean since we have a string um
this will be a boolean which will be set
to true that's it and then we can also
to test everything out. This means if I
go to my tigress dashboard and do a hard
refresh, you will see that I deleted all
of the files which I had inside of here.
And let's upload a file again. So for
example, I will click on select file. I
want to upload this file. Enter. Nice
percentages. File uploaded successfully.
And if I go into the tigress dashboard,
I will get my file. I can also open it.
You see this is the correct file. Then I
can delete the file. File removed
successfully. Okay. And if I go back and
do a hard refresh, my file is deleted.
Here's one thing which I want to quickly
mention. And that's that if you still
see this file in your dashboard. That's
fine. For example, a few hours ago, I
deleted a file. I went into the
dashboard, did a hard refresh, and the
file was still there. Even though my
operation, this means the deletion
itself was successful. After coming back
the file was finally deleted. So I
probably think that they cached the
files here but the operation itself is
successful. I mean you see the toasts
everything works. If it wouldn't work we
would get an error. But yeah so file
uploads work but we have one problem
currently. If we go back to our page.tsx
tsxo to the creation route you will see
yeah we have the uploader component but
it's not connected with we are took form
with our client side state or client
side state what am I talking about with
our form validation library so our
uploader will need three prop or two key
properties and this is again the value
and then the onv value change so we can
first of all delete this comment for the
input we won't need it anymore and then
in the uploader we will create a new
interface so right here interface what's
a good name I props this is my favorite
name then I want to get a value this
will be optional and this will be of
type string then I want to also get the
onchange handler what is the onchange
handler it's a function so on change and
then this will be also optional and as
mentioned this will be a function and
this will be void so it will return void
then as a param I want to also get a
value and this will be of type string
Then we can go to the uploader
component. We can just destructure this.
This will be of type I props. And then
where I d the structure, I can get the
onchange handler and then also the
value. This means if we go back to the
page.tsx, go to the uploader and click
on control spacebar, we get two
properties on change and then also
value. This means the onchange property
will be equal to the field do.change on
change and value will be equal to field
do value. So this looks good. We don't
get any errors here. And if we go back
to the uploader component, we want to
use the onchange handler and also the
value itself. So where do we want to use
onchange first of all? So when we drop
our file or in other words when we
upload our file, we want to update our
field because again this form field
stores our file key when I upload my
file. So I have to first of all find the
upload file function. So this is the
upload file function. When I upload my
file I get a key and I want to store
this key for the file key. This means
once uploaded we want to go to the
onload event. Then underneath this toast
or above this toast it does not really
matter. We want to update our field. Um
is it called field? Yes field. This
means we can get our onchange handler.
Then this will be optional dot and as an
argument we want to provide our key
because we will store the key for the
value for the file key. As you see I get
an error and it says the this context of
type void is not assignable to methods
this of type window. Is this English?
Well it's quite simple. I'm misspelled
on change. That's it. I know quite
funny. So this is updated which is
great. But as you all know when we
delete a file we want to also update
this on change handler. This means I
want to again close this um upload file
function and I want to go into the into
the handle remove file and then when a
file is successfully deleted we want to
uh update this on change and we want to
make it empty an empty string. This
means underneath this if statement where
we revoke the object URL we can again
get this on change handler. We can uh
this is optional. This means we have to
mark this uh or give it this question
mark. This means it could be not
defined. And then when we invoke it and
as an argument this will we will pass an
empty string because the key is now
empty. We deleted the file. There is no
key. But we want to also implement our
value. So the value will be the file key
and again it could be defined but it
could also be not defined. This means we
want to go for example into our state
and we want to update our state. So this
means I can get my key and this will be
equal to my value. This value could
either be a string, a real key or this
could just be an empty string or in
other words undefined. So we will either
have a key or we won't have a key. When
I create a new course, there will be no
key. If I addit a course, we will have a
key. And honestly, I think this is
already it. So we created our form, we
update or we put everything into this
react hook form state, which means it's
time to create the mutation. So if I
again go back and for example fill in a
title, click on generate slug and then
click on create course, I should get a
lot of validation errors. So we get a
validation error for the description. So
if I add a bit of description, the a bit
of text, this error goes away. We get an
error for the big description. This
means if I create a big description in
this case, so a lot of content, then
this error goes away. Then for the
upload file or for the thumbnail URL we
get an error. This means if I select the
file for example this one the error
should go away and yes it went away.
Then for the category and level we don't
get any errors and that's because you
see default categories are already
selected. Then we also get errors for
the duration and price. That's because
the duration has to be bigger than 1
hour. So 50 and the price should be also
bigger or than zero. So, as an example,
500. And as you see, we don't get any
errors anymore. But if I click on create
course, nothing will really happen
because if we go to the page.tsx and
scroll to the complete top. Wow, this is
so much code. Damn. Then you will see we
will only console log our values. You
know what? We can test it out. So, if I
click on create course, hm, no feedback,
no no toast, no nothing. But I mean,
this isn't that bad. But if I go to the
inspector and go to the console, what
will we see inside of here? Well, we
have an object. And as you see,
category, description, duration, file
key, everything is defined. So this
means it's time to create our mutation.
But here's my question to you. How do
you create mutations with Nex.js? Well,
it's quite simple. You have two options.
Option number one is to create a route
handler. This is what we did for S3. So
in our API folder we have a S3 folder
and then a delete and also upload route
handler. These are API routes and we can
use them to get data. So this means to
fetch data but also to mutate data. The
only problem is it's quite annoying to
write the boilerplate export async
function post try catch this that I
don't want to do that. So what's another
alternative? Well another alternative is
server actions and that's what we will
use. Now, if you want to know when to
use server actions, when to use route
handlers, then I created a video on that
for channel members. So, definitely
check it out. It's super helpful. But
again, we will use server actions
because they are quite easy to write.
So, as mentioned, I'm a big fan of
vertical slice architecture. This means
instead of creating a global actions
file and defining all of the server
actions in there, we will instead go
into the create route and create an
actions file inside of here. So how do
you create server actions? Well, I hope
that you know the basics. You create
server actions by first of all defining
the file with use server. So with the
use server directive, this means all of
the functions which are exported from
this file will also be converted into
server actions. This means inside of
here we can create an export async
function. This will be called create
course and then we can just open this
inside of here in the params I want to
get my data. This means we can get data
and this will be of type course schema
type which is imported from the zot
schemas file. Now as you all know we
already implemented client side
validation. This is client side form
validation. But form validation on the
server side is even more important
because why is it important? Well,
here's the thing. A lot of people think
that server actions are private
endpoints or something like that. This
is not true. Server actions are like
route handlers like standard API routes.
They are publicly accessible which also
means anybody can hit the server action.
I created a lot of videos on server
actions. So just go through my YouTube
channel. But the TLDDR is you want to
validate your data on the server side.
You want to make sure that the data
which you get here is the same data
which is also passed on the client side
because if it's not the same then this
means that probably some attacker tried
to attack your website. So what we want
to do inside of here is first of all
create a try catch statement for our
handling. Then in the try statement I
want to do serverside validation as
mentioned. So constant v I will call it
validation and this will be equal to the
course schema which we get from our
schemas file dots save pass and as an
argument I want to provide the values.
So again or not values but data. So this
again means we get our data and then we
take the data and we compare it against
the zord schema. If the validation is
successful then the success property
will be true. If it's failed then it
will fail. Who would have thought? So
underneath the validation we can create
an if statement and we can say hey if
the validation is not successful. So if
not validation dosuccess then we want to
return an error message. This means I
will create an return open an object and
inside of here I want to first of all
return a status and this will be error
and then also a message and the message
will say invalid form data. Great. So
this is finished and now we make sure
that all of the data is correct and
validated. This means underneath this if
statement I can create a mutation using
Prisma. So we can create a constant data
and this will be equal to arate then
Prisma. Prisma is imported from the lip
folder dot course then dot create since
we want to create a new course and then
we have to use the data property since
we want to pass data. This means I can
just get my validation. So I can spread
my validation dot data. And as you see,
we still get an error. What's the
problem? Well, if you hover over data,
you will see a lot of error messages or
a lot of text. But right here, they say
property user is missing because if you
go back to the schema, then you should
remember that we have a one to many
relationship between the user and the
course. This means I have to define the
user ID. It's required. So if we go back
I can just for now get the user ID and
this will be equal to some random
string. We will get the user ID a bit
later on. So again we take our data
which we validated. We just spread it.
You could also in theory just hardcode
everything. So we could get the category
set it true or set it equal to our
validation dot data dot category. This
is the same thing. It does not matter
but it's just easier to spread our
validation dot data. You don't have to
write so much code and it's just a cool
helper I guess. So this is nice. We
create the mutation using Prisma. This
means we create the course and then
underneath this constant data I can
create a return object. This means we
can return an object. And then I want to
again get a status. This will be
success. And then also of course a
message. And for the message this will
be cause created successfully.
But here's one problem. So as you see I
want to always return objects. But the
thing is right now it's very easy to
just misspell something. So here I could
say status and here I could say status.
As you see I misspelled both statuses
but I still return them. I don't get any
type safety or anything like that.
That's not nice. I want to always return
something and it should always have the
same you could say vables the same
properties a status and a message. And
the status should only be either error
or success. This means we want to create
a type. Now we could of course create an
interface on the top and then use it as
a return type. This is fine. But since
we will reuse this type in all of our
server actions, it makes a lot of sense
to go into our lip folder and create a
types.ts file. Inside of here, we will
store general types which we will reuse
throughout the application. So I want to
create a type for the API response. This
isn't an API response, but it's pretty
much an API. So that's why I will call
it API response. So export then type.
This will be API response. And this will
be equal to an object inside of here. As
mentioned, I want to have a status. And
this status can either be success or it
can be error. So we can get this
vertical line and then error. And then
we want to also return a message. And
this will be of type string. So this is
the API response. I want to always
return these values. And how can we now
tell the server action that I want to
specifically return an object with these
two properties. Well, it's quite simple.
You call it the return type parameter.
Here after the parentheses, uh we can
add a colon, then use a promise, and
then for the promise, we can add a
generic. And in the generic, we want to
pass the API response type. This means
if I go back, I instantly get an error.
It says status does not exist. You
probably mean status. And right here,
status does not exist. You probably want
to get the correct status. As you see,
this looks and works beautifully.
Nevertheless, we still get one error.
What's the problem? Well, currently we
only return objects if our data or if
our whole submission was successful. But
we have to also return data in this
catch statement. So in the catch
statement I can again create a return
then open an object and if I click on
control spacebar wow typescript typing.
So for the status this will be error
correct and for the message
I guess failed to create course because
the user probably failed and as you see
if you again go back this promise API
response does not throw any error
anymore and that's because we we return
these objects. Here's one thing which I
want to quickly mention. A lot of people
might say, "Hey Jan, why do we return
objects?" How about we just comment this
out and throw a new error? So, throw new
error. And then for the message, we will
say something failed. And throw new
error should of course be uppercased.
So, error uppercased. Why don't we do
something like this? Very good question.
I also created a video on this already.
Nevertheless, I will quickly explain it.
So later on I want to get the error
message in my page.tsx. So we will call
the server action in this onsubmit
handler. Then this of course will have a
result. This means our server action our
whole submission could either be
successful or it could fail. If it's
successful I want to get the error
message. If it's failed if it fails I
want to also get the error message. So
this message which we provide. So I will
get the result message and then return
it in a toast. If I use this throw new
error and want to then render this error
message, it won't work because React is
it it tries to do things very securely.
So it will omit the message in
production to not leak anything. And
that's a huge problem. I don't want that
because the thing is it will work in
development. So if I use throw you
error, it will render this error message
in uh development. But once you push
your application to production, it won't
render this error message anymore. it
will just omit it and instead it will
create an error message which will say
hey this error message has been omitted
due to security reasons blah blah blah
so that's the reason why we don't use
throw new error and instead we just
return a plain object and then uh I
guess render the correct state using the
status so yeah that's the easy and
simple explanation this means we can go
back to the page tsx and inside of here
I want to call the server action but
here's the We have a try catch statement
in the server action. But I want to also
create a try catch statement inside of
here. But here's the thing. Always
writing try then again catch. You know
what? This is kind of annoying. I don't
want to do that. So is there anything
else which maybe allows us to create a
try catch statement without writing this
annoying code? Good question. There
actually is a very nice solution. So,
what you can do is go to Google and type
in T3 try catch. Honestly, I always
thought that this was just some weird
gimmick created by Theo, but no, it's
actually a game changer and I started
using it literally everywhere. So, this
is like a simple, as he says, Theo's
preferred way of handling try catch and
TypeScript. It's literally just a
wrapper around try catch. So it still
creates a try catch statement but you
don't have to write so much boilerplate
anymore because you can now just h say
try catch this will be a new function
and then you invoke it and as an
argument you provide your function you
don't have to write anymore try catch
return console log no so what we can do
is just copy this code I will copy it
then we can go back and then in the
hooks folder I want to create a new file
which will be called schwai-catch.ts
ts and then we will paste the code
inside of here. So again this is a
wrapper around standard try catch we get
right here try and catch but how does it
work in effect I mean I show you boring
code TypeScript nobody understands
anything so how does it work well I can
first of all delete this try catch we
don't need it anymore instead we will
use the try catch code library let's
call it function library let's call it
function so in this function on submit I
can first of all start a transition so
because I want to show a pending state
this means above the form we can first
of all create a constant. Then we want
to create or get a getter and setter.
This means this will be is pending and
then also start transition and this will
be equal to use transition and use
transition is imported from react. Then
we can copy start transition go back and
then in the onsubmit function I will get
start transition. I want to invoke it
and inside of here we will create a
standard async arrow function. So let's
open it and then inside of here we can
finally use this uh try catch function.
So we can create a constant we want to
destruct and then this will be equal to
a rate try catch. Try catch is imported
from the hooks file. Don't click on this
try catch because it will create a
standard try catch but import try catch
from the hooks folder. And then inside
of here we can invoke it and as an
argument we want to provide the function
the server action. How is our server
action called? It's called create
course. We will copy the name, paste it
inside of here. We can import it from
the actions. We want to invoke it and as
an argument, we want to pass our values.
Okay, this looks nice. But what exactly
does this code do now? Well, where we
destructure this try catch or the
result, we will get two properties.
First of all, data and then error. And
this data is what would result if our
try is successful. This error is the
response which will be handled in the
catch statement if this makes sense. So
this is literally just your try. This is
your catch. That's it. This means
underneath the constant we can create
first of all an if statement. And if
error is true, this means if our catch
statement I don't want to say was
successful but if it catched something
then we can return a toast error and
host is imported from sona. Then for the
message this will just be an unexpected
error occurred. And of course we want to
also return it at the end to not check
any further. Then after this if
statement we can create another if
statement because this means if this
error wasn't triggered then our
submission was successful. And I want to
check if our result type was success or
error because here's again the thing we
have two try catch statements. our our
submission could either fail on the
server side and land in the catch
statement or our validate or our
submission could fail on the client
side. We now check if the uh submission
failed on the client side with this
error state. But one we want to also
check if the uh submission failed on the
server side. This means if data do
status is equal to success. As you see
we get nice typescript types then we can
open this and I want to return a toast.
This means toast this it's already
imported dots success and for the
message this will be data dot message
and honestly I don't like this name data
so I will rename it to result I think
this is a bit better so if result status
is success then we will return data uh a
toast dosuccess with the argument result
dossage if this is not true then we can
create an else if statement and inside
of here I want to check if the result do
status is equal to
If so, we want to again return a toast
dot error. And for the message, this
will be result dossage. Great. Then also
if success is true, I want to also reset
the form. This means form dot reset. We
can invoke it. And then I want to also
redirect the user. I want to redirect
the user to the courses route. How do
you redirect a user in a client
component? You use the use router hook.
This means if we again scroll to the
top, we can go underneath the use
transition and we want to create a
constant router and this will be equal
to use router. Use router is imported
from next /navigation we want to invoke
it and then we can copy the router. This
means we want to redirect the user. So
router dop and as an argument this will
be /admin /courses. Then there's only
one more thing which I want to do and
that's first of all delete these stupid
imports which I made and secondly I want
to use the pending boolean for the
submit button. So I will scroll
completely to the bottom. D wow wow wow.
Here we have the button. First of all
the button should be of type submit.
This is number one. Secondly for the
disabled state and this will be equal to
pending. So I renamed it from is pending
to pending. I like the name a bit
better. So if we are pending the button
will be disabled. And for the content, I
don't want to render create course, but
instead I want to render the uh content
dynamically. If pending is true, we will
return a loader icon. If pending is not
true, we will just return this thing.
So, we can just copy this. Don't delete
it. Keep it in your clipboard. And then
we can use the pending boolean. We want
to create a turnary. If pending is true,
let's use empty tags. And inside of
here, we can say creating dot dot dot.
And then we want to get the loader icon.
So I will uh get the loader icon from
lucid react. This is self-closing and
then we can give it a class name which
will be animate spin. If this is not
true we can use columns and then we want
to return what I just copied. So I will
use empty tags and then paste what I
just copied. Also for this load two icon
I want to give it margin left of one.
And in theory this should be it. So do
you want to test it out? I think so. So
we can go back. We can do a hard refresh
and I honestly hope for the best. So
this will be subscribe now. I can
generate this lock for the small
description. Hey, how are you doing
today? For the description, hey, how are
you? Then for the thumbnail URL, I will
select this file. For the category, how
about music? Level intermediate,
duration 50 hours, price $500. and for
the status publish.
Okay, I hope for the best I will click
on create course. We have a pending
state and failed to create course. No,
no, no, no. So, let's analyze our
actions file because as you see the
message was failed to create course.
This means this error message was
rendered which means our catch statement
was um triggered. So if we analyze the
code the validation can't be the problem
because if the validation would fail
then we would render this error message.
This means there's some sort of data uh
database error and yes I passed the fake
user ID. So we can also console log the
error in the catch statement as a param
I can get the error and then I can just
console log it down below. So error this
means if I go back and click on create
course we get the pending state we get
the toast and if I open my terminal you
will see invalid Prisma course.create
create an invocation foreign key
constraint uh constraint violated on the
constraint course user ID foreign key so
we are missing a valid user ID so we can
first of all delete or I can delete the
console log I can delete the error it's
not needed anymore and I want to get my
real user ID so above this constant
validation I will create a constant
session this will be equal to a weight
of off is imported from the lip folder
dot API get session we can invoke it the
structured and we want to pass headers
and headers will be equal to await
headers and then we can just invoke it.
So we get our session which means I can
copy the session itself. Then for the
user ID this will be equal to session do
user do ID and also you see we get an
error. What's the problem? Well it says
type string or undefined is not
assignable to type string because this
currently could be undefined but the
user ID has to be defined. I know this
is a big problem for now. I will mark it
as string. But we will make a lot of
changes. So that's fine for now. This
means if I again go back and click on
create course d course created
successfully and we got redirected. So
how about we check out our database? So
I will head over to the neon console.
And if I go to my tables I should see a
new course. So course and yes one new
course. So we have an ID, we have a
title, description, we get the file key.
Then what else do we have? We have the
price, we have the duration, the level,
category, small description, slug,
status, created at, and then updated at,
and of course the user ID. So this
worked exactly as expected, which is
super nice. But I don't display my
courses here. Don't worry, this is not a
huge problem. For now, I want to fix a
few small things. So let's start with
the first problem or the first thing
which I have to or want to change. So we
have two route handlers to upload a file
and then also to delete a file. The
thing is these are public route
handlers, public API routes. Anybody can
hit this route handler for example the
deletion route. This somebody could pass
some fake ID, some fake key and then
just hit this route handler. The same
thing is also true for the upload route
handler. Any user can hit this post
request just add uh these properties a
file name content type size and then
this is image property and can then just
literally upload a file. This means we
if we take my friend he's not a friend
but let's say next to me I have somebody
he is called John and John is a very
malicious user he wants to attack your
application and he sees that you have
this beautiful route handler which is
not protected. So he will say hm how
about I create a bot army a bot farm and
this bot uh farm will attack this
application thousands of upload requests
but because again I don't validate
anything I mean I validate that I get
these properties but there's no bot
protection and there's no rate limiting
that's not great so we will implement
arc chat again let's get started first
of all with the upload route and we want
to first of all set up arc chat this
means we want to define the rules the
properties. This means we can create a
constant. This will be called AJ. And
you have to do that or you should do it
above the export async function. And
then this will be equal to arcjet.
Please make sure that you import arcjet
from the lip folder. And then we want to
use the with rule method because again
we already have an arcjet base instance.
This caches everything. And using this
with rule method I can add um more rules
because we have one base rule. This is
shield. Wherever we use arcjet, shield
will also run. But in addition to shield
inside of here, I want to use the bot
rule and then also um weight limiting.
And then I want to use the fixed window
algorithm. So let's first of all get
started with the detect bot rule. So I
want to invoke it. Then I want to get
detect the bot and detect bot is
imported from the lip folder. We want to
invoke it the structured and there are
two properties which we have to pass.
This is first of all the mode and this
could either be dry one or live. Again
dry one will console lock everything.
Live will block the request if needed.
And then we can also get the allow array
or the allow property which is an array.
And here we can say for example the open
AI bot is allowed to interact with our
website. But in this case I don't want
to allow any bot to interact with my uh
route handler. That's why this will be
an empty array. Then I want to use
another rule and this will be a weight
limiting and I want to use the fixed
window algorithm. This means we can
again chain with rule we want to invoke
it and inside of here I will get fixed
window. Again fixed window is imported
from the lip folder. We want to invoke
it and the structure. So this fixed
window needs three properties. First of
all the mode again this will be live.
Then we have to pass the window and also
the maximum amount of requests. So I
want to say a user is allowed to upload
five files in a 1 minute window. This
means we will just say 1 minute and then
max will be five. So five requests in a
1 minute window. If you want to you can
make it bigger, smaller, you decide. I
think this is good. I think this is a
good limit but again you can change it.
And also we can quickly go to the arcad
documentation and look at the detect bot
or bot protection itself. So, Arcjet bot
detection allows you to manage traffic
by automated clients and bots. This
means if my friend John, who is again
not my friend, attacks your website with
bots, we will see that or Arcjet will
get a request. Arcjet will analyze the
request and it will see hm this kind of
looks weird. This is probably a bot. I
think I will just deny the request. So,
Arcjet will deny it. But currently, we
just set up Arcjet the rules. We want to
also now pass the request to Arkhat.
This means we can go into our post
request and we want to go underneath the
try or into the try statement and above
this constant body. Arcjet should first
of all validate the request and only
after that we will do the rest. This
means delete or in other words upload
the file. So this will be a constant
decision and this will be equal to a
rate h.protect.
We want to use the protect method and as
an argument we have to pass the request
itself. Since we use a route handler, we
get the request uh right through our
params. And as you see, we get an error
and it says expected two arguments but
got one. What is missing? Well, we are
missing the fingerprint because in the
arcjet configuration file, we added
custom characteristics. And right here,
we want to now pass some sort of unique
value which we will use to um not
verify, but you could say track the requ
identify and track the request. So we
can either use for example the user's
IP. But again this is not very
recommended or we can use the users uh
ID so the session ID. This means what I
will do is go above this try statement.
I will create a constant session and
this will be equal to a rate of off is
imported from the lip folder API.get
session. we can invoke it the structured
and we have to pass headers and headers
will be equal to await headers and
headers is imported from next/ headers.
This means here uh for aj.protect
protect I can add a comma open an object
pass the fingerprint property and this
will be equal to session do user do ID
this means and we can also mark this as
string don't worry we will fix all of
this I will rewrite the code later on
but for now this is fine enough so arjet
will now verify or it will identify the
request using the user's ID and this is
also nice because this isn't related to
some specific IP means if the user for
example creates an attack from home, he
will have one IP. If the user then also
creates an attack from uh for example
some sort of cafe which has a different
IP, then this would of course have
different IPs. This means if we use the
user ID, we don't really care where the
user is. We don't care about the IP
because we identify the user using this
unique identifier and this is a huge
benefit. And you know what we can also
test it out or before we test it out, we
have to of course check if the decision
was denied or allowed. This means we can
go underneath the decision create an if
statement and I want to say if the
decision not this but if the decision is
denied we want to invoke it then we can
return just a new response. This means
return next response.json JSON. Uh, for
the error, this will just be Hm. What do
we want to say, dude? Not good. Of
course, you want to add something
better, but this is fine enough. And
then for the status, so I can add a
comma, open an object, and the status
will be 4 to 9. So, we will protect our
route handler. And a user in this case
will only be allowed to upload five
files in a 1 minute window. I want to
also do the same thing for the deletion
route. So we can go into the delete
route and I will just copy this constant
AJ paste it in the deletion route above
the export async function and then we
want to import arcjet from the lip
folder. Detect bot this will be imported
from the lip folder and fixed window
will be imported from the lip folder. As
you all know we want to await the
decision or in other words we want to
pass the request to arjet. This means we
can just copy this constant decision,
paste it into our try statement. We want
to get the user session. So I can copy
this constant session, paste it above
the try statement. Then we want to get
off or we want to import it from the lip
folder. And we want to import the
headers from next/ headers. We want to
then create an if statement for the
decision. So I will copy this if
statement and then just paste it down
below. This means our create or our
upload route is protected. and then also
our deletion route. Both are protected
and that's super nice. So, what do you
think? Should we test it out? I think
so. So, you know what? I will implement
a very small weight limit. This means
for the upload route, I will say in a
window, so in a 1 minute window, a user
is only allowed to upload two files. I
will later on update this again. So, if
I select a file, um I can just get this
one. If I click on enter, this will
upload everything. As you see, uploaded
successfully. I can delete it. This
should work. Yes. And then if I select
the file one more time.
And if I select one more file, you see
upload failed. Retry file selection. And
this is because arc chat blocked the
request. So if I open the terminal API
S3 upload 429 and 429 was the error
which we returned with um AR. So for
arcjet as you see dude not good status
429. We can also open the arcad
dashboard and here you will see
something interesting. The request was
denied. The reason weight limit of
course we can also open the request and
inside of here again the conclusion was
denied. The reason was weight limit. Why
is the reason weight limit? Because the
maximum amount of requests was two, but
I used two requests. And this weight
limit will only reset in 45 seconds
again. And in the configuration tab, you
can also see what rules we configured.
We configured the shield rule. This is
the base configuration or we implemented
the rule in our base configuration. We
implemented weight limit and also bot
detection. And in this case, weight
limit was triggered. So I want to again
go back. Of course, I want to update the
maximum window. Two is not enough. Five
is a bit better. If you want to, you can
make it bigger because five is also not
that big. But I think this is fine
enough. So, this means our two route
handlers are uh completely secured. This
means no bots can attack this route
handler. No malicious users can attack
this route handler or these route
handlers. Everything is great. So, we
can close this. We are finished with all
of this. But there's one problem. You
see currently any user um can upload
files but I want to only allow verified
or not verified but authenticated users
to upload files and also I want to only
allow authenticated users to create
courses. Right now anybody can access
this admin dashboard and anybody can
interact with this website or with this
admin dashboard. I don't want that. I
want to only allow admins to view this
dashboard and interact with this
dashboard. This means what we can do is
we can head over back to the better of
documentation website. Then you can
click on documentation. You want to then
click on integrations or not
integrations but plugins and here you
will find a very interesting plug-in
called admin. So the admin plug-in
provides a set of administrative
functions for user management in your
application. It allows administrators to
perform various operations such as
creating users, managing user roles,
banning, unbanning users, impersonating
users, and more. So, we want to use this
um plug-in because we will then have two
roles, either a standard user role or an
admin role. An admin will be able to
interact with this dashboard. A standard
user won't be able to interact with this
dashboard. So the first step is to first
of all use this admin plugin or in other
words to configure it in the off config
file. This means we can copy the import
statement go into the off.ts file and
paste it on top. So import admin from
better off plugins. Then we want to add
it into the plugins array. So underneath
email OTP I will just add admin and I
want to invoke it. So this is step
number one. And step number two is to
migrate our database or in other words
generate a new database schema because
we want to add a few more fields. This
means I will copy this generate command.
I can go back and then in my terminal I
will run pnpm dlx better off cli
generate. So this will generate new
tables. In theory it will just update
our database schema and add a few more
properties. But as you see I got an
error. What's the problem? Hm. cannot
read your offconfig file. Error cannot
find module server only. Yes, this is
correct. So we don't want to import
server only in the off.ts file. So we
can delete it again. And if I again want
PNPM DLX better off CLI generate, then
this error should go away. But it did
not go away. What's now the problem?
Better off couldn't read your offconfig
file. So this could be our DB file. So
if I delete import server only from
there, will it then work? PNPM DLX.
Again I will paste the command and this
should then work. Nope. I again got an
error. Hm. Ah require stack. Oh
thankfully they even have a path. So
this means we want you also delete the
import server only from the recent file.
So we can open the recent configuration
file. Delete this import server only.
And then again if I run pnpmdlx better
off cli generate it should work. Oh my
god. Thank you. So the file
schema.prisma already exists. Yes it
exists. Do you want to overwrite the
schema to the file? Yes. And if I again
open the schema, we will have a new
property or I think multiple properties.
So in the user model, we have a new
role, a banned property ban reason and
ban expires. So the role as a default
will be user. Every user will have the
role user. But we can update the role
and set an admin role. So what we can do
is first of all again push this new
schema to our database to neon. This
means pnpm dx prisma db push. This will
sync our local database schema with our
remote real database schema. So as you
see your database is now in sync. By the
way, don't worry about this error. Then
we want you again open our Prisma
studio. This means pnpm dx Prisma
studio. And this is like a local
representation of your database provided
by Prisma. So as you see um if I zoom in
a bit we get all of our models account
course session user uh verification and
if I open the user model and here you
will see first of all on the left side
we have an email but I won't showcase it
email verified this all looks good and
if we scroll to the right side we have a
role and this is null because we just
added this admin plugin but once new
users will be created uh these plugins
or these roles be will be um propagated
with user so what we can do is just
delete both users. I will delete the two
records. Then the course has also been
automatically deleted. This means if I
again close this and again go back. We
can restart the def server with PNPMe
defaf. Then we can head over back to
localhost 3000. As you see everything
works and on the top right corner it
showcases a login and get started
button. That's because we don't have a
valid session. We don't have any users.
We had a valid session a few moments
ago. But because I deleted all users,
there's no user anymore, which also
means there's no valid session anymore.
So I will click on log in. Then I will
continue with GitHub. As you see, signed
in with GitHub. You will be redirected.
I got redirected. I see my beautiful
image here. And then I can again head
over back to the admin dashboard. This
should still open. Yes, it works. That's
great. And then we want to again open
our Prisma Studio. So I will just create
a new terminal tab and then inside of
here I will run pnpmd dlx prisma studio
and as you see the user role as a
default is user and that's exactly what
we wanted. So we can again close this.
We don't need it anymore. Then we can
head over back because we're still not
finished with the could you say quick
start guide. So we are finished with
step number one. This means to add the
plugin to our off config. we migrated or
in other words generated our database
and the next step is to add the plug-in
to our off client itself. This means I
will just copy this import statement
again. We can open the off client. This
means in our lip folder we have an off
client and then we can add a comma after
this email OTB client and or and first
of all we have to import it of course.
So import admin client from better of
client plugins and then we can add the
admin client and we want to invoke it.
So this is finished and we set up this
admin plug-in. This means we can head
over back first of all to our two route
handlers. So in the app folder, we want
to go into the API folder into the S3
folder and then into the delet into the
deletion route handler. And inside of
here, I want to check if the user is an
admin and also has a valid session
because currently we just get the user
session, but we don't really verify if
the user has a valid session and also if
the user is an admin. Now, here's the
thing. We could of course just create a
code inside of here. It's completely
fine. You can do that. But since we will
reuse this code in multiple places, this
means in the deletion route, in this
upload route, wouldn't it make sense to
create a separate file and then just or
a separate function and store the code
inside of there? Yes, it will make so
much sense you can't even believe it.
So, Nex.js recommends you to use the
data access layer. So, we can head over
back to the documentation and search for
data access layer. So how to implement
authentication in X.js. And if you
search for the data um access layer then
you will see we recommend creating a
data access layer to centralize your
data requests and authorization logic.
The data access layer should include a
function that verifies the user session
as they interact with your application.
So this means what are they trying to
tell us? Well, Nex.js wants us to create
a separate file, a separate folder. This
does not really matter but in this case
just a separate file and then in this
separate file we want to move all of our
data related logic into this file into
the separate location. So this will then
be a separate data access layer because
all of the data axis will happen in this
one uh you could say section I think
this uh you should then understand it
better. So it will be a separate section
and in this section we will store all of
our data access related logic. This
means we will when we fetch our data we
will create the file in the separate
section and then call this function from
our actual component. So for example for
in the route handler I want to call a
verify user function and this will
verify the user and also check that the
user has a valid session and the benefit
is that we then have centralized logic
because our data access logic will be
stored in one place. it won't be stored
in multiple places which also means we
uh will centralize everything. We will
centralize our business logic. What we
can do is open our explorer. Then we
want to go into the app folder and to
create a separate data access layer. It
makes a lot of sense to create a new
folder and name it data. I do that in
most cases. And since this function
which we want to call or which we want
to create is directly related to the
user, we can also or to the admin or to
the user, we can create an admin folder
in the data folder. So app folder then
data and in the data folder an admin
folder and in the admin folder we want
to create a new file and this will be
called require- user.ts.
And again the code which will be or the
code which we will create inside of here
is quite simple. we will get the user
session. We will check if the user has a
valid session. If so, we will check uh
if the user is an admin and if this is
also true, then we will just return the
user. And this means we will then get
the user ID and then we can uh create or
we can get the decision from arc chat.
If the user does not have a valid user
session or is not an admin, then we will
just redirect the user. So that's what
we want to do. So for this require user
function we want to first of all create
an export async function. This will be
called require user. Then we can just
open this function and inside of here we
want to first of all get the user
session. This means constant session
equals to arate of off is imported from
the lip folder dot API.get
session. We can invoke it the structured
we want to pass headers and headers will
be equal to await headers. headers is
imported from next slash headers and we
want to invoke it because this is a
function. After this constant session,
we want to check if the user has a valid
session. This means if there's no
session, then we want to redirect the
user and we want to uh so let's say
return redirect and redirect is imported
from next slashnavigation and we want to
redirect the user to /loin because this
means the user is not authenticated.
It's that simple. By the way, I also
made a mistake. This shouldn't be
require user, but instead require admin.
I'm not sure why I said require user.
So, require admin. And then the function
will also be require admin because again
we want to require an admin. So, we now
check if the user has a valid session
and we can also check if the user has
the correct role. This means we create
we will create another if statement and
if the session do user.roll role is not
equal. This means exclamation mark and
then two equal signs. If this is not
equal to admin, then this means the user
is not an admin. So we want to again
create a return redirect and we want to
redirect the user to a route which will
be not /admin. If these two if
statements are not true, then I will
just return the session again because
this means the user has a valid session
and also the user is an admin. Also
since this is a function which should
only be called and also should only run
on the server side. We want to import
server only. So we created our function
require admin. We imported server only
which means we can also use it. We can
go back to our route handler and we want
to delete this constant session. And
then instead we want to use the require
admin function. So I want to go above
the try statement and then we can create
a constant. um this will be session and
this will be equal to a wait require
admin. We want to import this from our
data folder and then we can invoke it.
We want to do the same thing for our
deletion route handler. So above the try
statement I will again paste this await
require admin function or this code. I
mean we are not pasting a function we
are pasting code. So we now in both
routes check that we have a valid user
and also that the user is an admin that
the user has the role of admin. This
means if I go back and do a hard refresh
everything works. We currently don't
validate the user on the page level. We
will do that a bit later on but for now
we want to check out or test out this
thumbnail or image upload or file
upload. So if I click on select file and
select this file I will get an error
failed to get presigned URL. Hm. And if
we open the terminal, what do we see
inside of here? API S3 upload 307. So
what's exactly the problem? Well, it's
quite simple. If I open my require user
require admin function, we use the
redirect function. And the redirect
function um responds with a 307 as you
see. So again in the terminal, we get a
307. And the redirect function also
returns or responds with a 307 code. The
thing is since we use this function in a
route handler, it does not work as
expected. So it does not redirect the
user. This is fine. I don't also really
want to redirect the user inside of
here. We can just throw an error. The
thing is once we later on use the
require admin function in, for example,
a server action, it will work fine. But
in this route handler, it cannot
redirect the user. But this is fine. We
don't need it. Also one thing or you
might ask me, hey Jean, why did we
define this require admin function not
in the try statement? I mean I can just
go here and put it into the try
statement. Why don't we do that? Good
question. Because if I go back and do a
hard refresh and again select a file and
click on enter, we still get the same
error. Everything is still protected.
But if I open my terminal, there's a new
error. This time 500. So here's the
thing again. This redirect function
responds with a 307. As you all know,
the thing is when you use a redirect
function in the try statement, it throws
an internal error. It throws an it
throws a redirect error and that's why
this catch is triggered and we return
the status of 500. So whenever you use a
require admin function or a require user
function which uses internally the
redirect function or where you want to
redirect the user then you want to never
put this session or this function into a
try statement. It has to live outside of
a try catch statement. So that's why I
define this constant session await
require admin above the try statement.
Of course I could do it inside of here.
It does not matter in this context in
the route handler example. But when we
use the function in a server action, we
want to never implement it or define it
in the try statement itself. And that's
already it. As you see, it's quite
simple. So we are protecting our route
handlers, but our creation route itself
is not protected. What do I mean by
that? Well, if we open our actions file,
you will see currently we get the user
session, but we don't check if the user
has a real valid session and that the
user is an admin. This means we can
delete this constant session and instead
we can go above the try statement and
again say constant session equals to a
rate require admin. We can import it and
invoke it. As you see this all works. We
can delete the unused imports. We don't
need them anymore. And this all looks
good. Now here's the thing. What I will
do quickly is go back to the upload
route handler and I will comment out
this decision or this constant session
and I will also comment out this arc
chat code because I want to test out if
this redirect works itself. This means
if I go back and do a hard refresh
everything works. If I select a file
everything works. So as you see uploaded
but I got an error. What's the problem?
Hm. Was this the ah this was the
deletion route? My god. So I want to go
into the upload route not into the
deletion route handler. Then I can com
uh comment out this constant session and
then also the arc chat code itself. This
means if I again go back and select a
file it should also work. And yes
uploading uploaded. Then for the title
this will be some gibberish. For the
slug this will be some gibberish. For
the small description this will be some
gibberish. For the category this will be
design for level intermediate price 500.
Duration 50. This does not matter
because we will get an error. And for
the status published, if I click on
create course, we get an error. That's
because I forgot the description. Silly
mistake. So I can add a bit of content.
And if I click on create course, we
should get redirected. And we got
redirected. We got a toast. An
unexpected error occurred. And also we
got redirected to notadmin or /notadmin.
That's again because if we go back to
the actions file, we check or we verify
the user session, we check that the user
has a valid session and also that the
user is an admin. Currently I'm signed
in but I don't have the correct role and
that's why I got redirected to not admin
and as you also see I got redirected and
the reason for that is uh quite simply
because the redirect works in a server
action and if I would define this
constant session code in the try
statement I wouldn't get redirected
instead this catch statement would
trigger and then this error message
would be returned because again this
redirect function internally throws a
new error even though it's not really an
error but it throws an internal error
which means the catch statement is
triggered. So this all looks good. We
can go back to the upload code. I can
again uncomment my decision and I can
also uncomment the session code and I
want to also protect my server action
because yeah right now we check that the
user is an admin and also has a valid
session. Nevertheless, let's imagine a
user somehow gets the admin rule then he
could still attack this create course
route. We don't want that. That's why I
want to again implement arcjet and I
want to implement weight limits and bot
detection or bot protection. This means
we can just open our route handler the
upload route handler and we already
created the code constant AJ equals to
arcjet with rule with rule. So I will
just copy this code. Then in the actions
file I will paste it above the export
async function. We want to import arcjet
from the lip folder and we want to also
import detect bot from the lip folder
and then fixed window will also be
imported from the lip folder. Then we
want to get the decision itself. This
means in the try statement above the
validation we can create a constant.
This will be called decision and this
will be equal to a rate arc jet dot
protect and as an argument we have to
pass the request. But here's the thing.
We don't get a request in a server
action. We get our values but no
request. So how can we fix this problem?
Well, we can go back to the
documentation. So to the archae docs.
Then you can scroll a bit to the bottom
and then you will find the SDK reference
section. We want to click on nextjs not
nest js and here you will find the
section um server actions. So arjet
supports server actions in both
next.js14 JS14 and 15 for all features
except sensitive data detection. But we
don't use this rule, so we don't really
care. So what we need to do is call a
utility function called request. And
with that, we will get the request
because again in the route handler, we
natively get a request. In a server
action, we sadly don't get it. But
thankfully, Arjet created a helper
function request which we can use. So I
will just copy this code. We can go
back. We can paste it. And as you see
access request data that archet needs
when you call protect. It's similar to
await headers and await cookies and next
headers. So this gives us or this gets
us the request. We want to also import
this request function and it's imported
from arcjet next. And then we can pass
the request as an argument.
Nevertheless, we still get one error.
What's the problem? We have to pass the
fingerprint. What was the fingerprint?
It could either be the user's IP or we
can for example pass the user ID and as
mentioned the user ID is preferred. And
why exactly is again the user ID
preferred? Well, let's imagine the
following. A malicious user can create
attack from his home with the IP XYZ. He
can also create an attack from an cafe,
from a restaurant with a different IP.
So this means he could also create a bot
army with different IPs. And that's why
we don't want to really in most cases
use the IP but instead we want to use
something which can be identified uh
without looking at the IP and the user
ID is something which we can use for
that because it never changes. So for
the fingerprint this will be equal to
session do user do ID and this looks
great. As you all know we have to also
um check if the decision is denied or
allowed. So we can create an if
statement and then if the decision dot
is denied we want to invoke it then we
want to return an object. So I can
create a return then I want to return an
object for the status this will just be
error because we have an error and then
we can also add a message and for the
message um we can say looks like you are
a malicious user and you know what we
can of course also create multiple
statements because if statements because
currently we only check for the global
is the night you could say event or for
the global decision but we could also
check for the specific reason. So I
could for example delete this return
statement and instead create another if
statement and we can check if the
decision not describe but decision dot
reason and then we can say is weight
limit for example we can invoke it and
then return a different object. So let's
do it. You know what? Why not? So we
will return again an object for the
status. This will be error. And then for
the message we can say you have been
blocked due to weight limiting. Yeah, I
think this is fine. Then we can create
an else statement. And here we will just
return again an object for the status.
This will be error. And here we will
know that the user has been um blocked
because he's probably a bot. So for the
message we can just say you are a bot.
Never touch my website again. No, I'm
joking. You are a bot. If this is a
mistake, contact support. Yeah, I think
this is fine enough. So, we now check if
the decision is denied. If so, we check
if the reason is weight limit. If so, we
then return a specific weight limit
error message. And if not, then we
return a error message which
specifically mentions that the user is
probably a bot. And I just realized that
I made a mistake here. I use arcjet, but
I don't want to use arcjet. I want to
use AJ because I just configured the
arcjet rules because if I just use
arcjet and use the protect method then
we will only use shield but I want to
use shield detect bot and fixed window.
So I will copy AJ and then instead of
saying arcjet this will be AJ. This
looks good. Did I also make the same
mistake in the route handlers? No, this
looks good. So what's the next step?
Well the next step is to again first of
all go back or you know what we can
create this notadmin route. So this will
be a simple page which will just say hey
you are not an admin go away from here.
So we can open the explorer again or we
want to go back to our codebase. Then in
the app folder we want to create a new
folder. This will be not dashadmin. And
then inside of here we want to create a
page.tsx because again how do you create
routes in x.js? You should all know it.
You create a new folder and you create a
new page.tsx. That's it. It's that
simple. So the UI will be relatively
simple. First of all, since this is a
route and not just a standard component,
we have to create an export default
function. Then for the name, this will
just be not admin route. And then we can
just open this function. Let's create a
return statement. And inside of here, we
want to use a div. Then I want to style
the div. And this will be a class name,
which is minimum height screen. So we
want to take the whole height. Then flex
item center and also justify center. So
this means we just take the whole
screen, the whole width and the whole
height. And then we just take our
children and we put them in the middle.
That's it. Or in the center, I'm not
sure how you want to call it. And in the
div, I want to center my card. So I want
to create a card component or I want to
render it because we already created it.
And for the class name or for the cart,
we want to give it a class name. And
this will be a maximum width of MD. This
means 448 pixels and width full. Then in
the cart we want to first of all get the
cart header from the components. And for
the cart header I want to render an
icon. This means we can create first of
all a wpper div which will create a
background color. And inside of here we
want to get the shield x icon from lucid
react. This is self-closing. We can give
it a class name. And then this will be
size 16. And then text destructive. This
means this red color. And for the wrap
again this will create the background
color. So we can also give it a class
name. This will be bg destructive and it
shouldn't take or it shouldn't have the
full opacity but instead an opacity of
50%. So / 50 or not 5010 I'm sorry. So
slash 10 and then also rounded full we
want to say padding four to have some
spacing and then also width which will
be fit and MX auto to center everything.
So if we go back then we should already
see something. And you know what? This
looks kind of good to be honest with
you. So underneath this card header or
underneath this icon, I want to render a
title and a card description. So we can
go underneath the div, but we want to
stay in the card header and we can first
of all get the card title component.
Inside of here, I will say access
restricted. Then um if I go back, you
see this is not centered. This is not
quite what I want. So what wraps the
cart title? Well, it uh the cart header
wraps the card title. This means we can
style the cart header and give it a
class name which will be text center.
And with that, this card title will be
automatically centered. Also, this title
is a bit too small. So we can give it a
class name which will be text to Excel.
Underneath the card title, we want to
get a card description. And for the card
description, I want to say, "Hey user,
you are not an admin, which means you
cannot create any courses or stuff like
that." Dot dot dot. Then if we go back,
you will see, you know what, this looks
quite good, but maybe we should add a
maximum width. So for the cut
description, we can give it a class
name, which will be maximum width of MD.
Maybe let's see. N MD does not work. So
probably SM. Yeah, SM is fine. Maybe XS
will be even better. Uh yeah, I don't
know. And this is not centered anymore.
This is a big problem. But XS is quite
good. So we can also give this a text or
MX auto. And this should already look
way better. Yes. So text uh text XS and
then also MX auto to center it. Then
underneath this card header, I want to
also display card content which will
just be a standard button to redirect
the user back to the index page. So we
can go underneath the uh cart header. We
can get the cart content component from
the components and then we want to use
the link component inside of here import
it from next/link
and for the content this will be back to
home. Also we can render an icon in
front of this text. So this will be the
arrow left icon imported from lucid
react. We can also give it a class name
and then this will be margin right one
and then size 4. As you see the link
currently complaints and that's because
it's missing one key property which is
the href and the href will be an empty
slash. We can also add a class name and
this will just be button variance
because I want to style this link like a
shad CN button. We want to invoke it and
we can also you know what save it for
now. And as you see this is the button
but the button should take the whole
width. I think this will look better.
This means we can go back to the button
variance function. We can just d the
structured and give it a class name. And
this will be equal to width full. And if
I save this you see the button takes the
whole width. And this looks already way
better. Is there anything missing? If I
click on the button I will get
redirected. Honestly, I think this is
it. The button works. That's what I
wanted. So, we are finished. This means
we can again close this page.x. But our
core problem is still not fixed. I'm not
an admin. This means we want to again
start our Prisma Studio, our local
representation of our database. So, I
will just again say PNPM DLX Prisma
Studio. Then we want to open the user
model. We want to go to the right and we
want to update the role. And instead of
saying user, I will say admin because
I'm an admin. We can then save the
change. And in theory, everything should
work. So we can go back to the admin
dashboard. We want to go to the courses.
And I want to create a new course. So
for the title, this will be subscribe.
Now for the slug, I can generate a slug.
For the small description, hey, how are
you doing today? We want to also update
the big description. So I will add a bit
of content. Then we can up uh upload an
image. So this one as you see uploading
successful. Then for the category this
is fine. For the level this is fine. For
the duration this will be 50. For the
price this will be 500. And for the
status this will be published. If I
click on create course we have a pending
state. I got redirected and it says
course created successfully. But there's
one problem. We don't see any courses.
So what's the next step? Well, as the
next step, we want to render the courses
here. And also, currently, anybody can
reach this route. So, if I open the
route in the new incognito tab, I can
still view it and I'm not logged in.
Don't worry, we will fix it later on. We
want to first of all finish off this
overview page and then we will fix this
authorization problem. So, we want to
first of all get our courses. This means
we have to go back to our explorer and
in as you all know we use the data
access layer to get our data. This means
in the data or in the app folder in the
data folder we want to create a new file
which will be called something like
admin getcourses or something like that.
This means I can go into the admin
folder create a new file and this will
be admin-get-courses.ts
TS and inside of here we can create a
function to get the courses. And if this
data access layer still confuses you,
don't worry. I will um explain it a bit
further later on because then I will
also show you a diagram and why it's so
cool. So we can first of all create an
export async function. This will be
called admin get courses. And inside of
here before getting the data I want to
first of all verify that the user is an
admin. I don't want to allow anybody to
fetch this data. Only admins should be
able to fetch this data or in other
words see this data. This means we can
create or we can say await require admin
and then we can just import it from the
require admin file. So underneath this
aait require admin. We can create a
constant data and this will be equal to
arate prisma. Prisma is imported from
the lip folder dot course.find
many. Then we can invoke it the
structured and in here we can first of
all use the select property because we
don't want you select everything we want
you only get specific fields like for
example the title small description
duration and stuff like that but I don't
need the big description as an example
this means we can set ID to true then we
can set the title to true we can get the
small description let's set this to true
we can get the duration let's set this
to true how about the level yes let's
set it to true. Then the status, this
will also be true. The price, this will
be true. I want to get the price. And
then also the file key. And finally also
the sluck itself. So as you see, we will
get an ID, title, small description,
duration, level, status, price, file
key, and slug. The rest of the
properties won't be returned because we
don't select them. Again, with that, I
mean, for example, the big description.
And also, we can order the result
because we will get an array. So an
array with multiple objects and each
specific object will be one course but
currently the order will be completely
random. So for example the first object
could be a course which I created two
months ago and then the second object
could be a course which I created today.
I don't want that. I want to order the
result. This means our array based on
the created at time stamp. So above the
select statement we can get the order by
property. This is an object and we want
to order our result based on the created
at time stamp. And you have two options
either ascending or descending.
Ascending means that you get the oldest
results first. Descending means you get
the newest results first. And we want to
get the newest results. So I will select
descending. And then we can add a comma
also here. So this should already be it.
We can of course also return our data.
This means we can go back to our
page.ts. tsx this means admin courses
page.tsx and then we can get our data
inside of here. So this means inside of
here we can create a constant data and
this will be equal to arate um admin get
courses we can import it and of course
invoke this function. As you see we get
one error and that's because uh we
haven't marked this function as
asynchronous. This means this will be an
export default async function. And
again, this is safe to do so because
this is a server component which only
runs on the server side. Great. So we
get our data which means we can also map
over it. So underneath the div but still
in the empty tags we can create another
div and inside of here we can get our
data. We can use the map method as a
param. We can get a singular course and
then just uh return this. Then what do
we want to return? Maybe a simple P tag
and in the P tag we can render the
title. So autocomp completion where are
you and then I want to get the course
dot title. Of course we get one error.
What's the error? You should know it.
Well when we map over data we have to
provide a key a unique key. What's
unique? Our ID is unique. This means
course do ID. If I save this and again
go back you will see subscribe. Now,
this is the title of what of our course
because we only have one course and
that's also why we only get one title.
But is this beautiful? No. Does this
resemble a course cut? No. So, I want
you to create like an admin course cut
which looks beautiful, which is
appealing and which also works because
um at the end of the day, we want you
also edit the course. This means we want
to create a separate component and this
will be the admin course card. As you
all know, I love vertical slice
architecture. This means we will create
a separate component in or we will
create a new components folder in the
courses folder. So, we can create a new
folder. This will be underscore
components and inside of here I want to
create an add minourse.tsx.
So, this will be the component and right
now it's empty. So, let's get started.
Since this is a component, we can get
started with an export function. This
will be called admin course cart. And
then we can just open it. Inside of
here, we can get started with a return
statement. And I want to create a card.
So here's the thing. We will create a
card. On the top, we will render the
image, the thumbnail URL which we
uploaded. Underneath the image, we will
render the title, a small description,
and then an edit button. And then also
on the top right corner we will create
like a drop-down. So this drop-down will
then have a button to first of all edit
the course then to preview the course
and also to delete it. So first of all
we want to get the cart component from
the components. Then we want to also
already style the cart component. So we
can give it a class name and this will
be group and then also relative. in the
cart. Um I want to first of all create
or we will create a div and you know
what I will also create a comment to not
forget it and I will say inside of here
absolute uh dropdown. So again this is
this thing which we will render on the
top right corner but for now I don't
want to create it. I want to first of
all render the image. So we can go
underneath the diff and then we want to
get the image component from next /
image. This image component needs two
properties. First of all, the source,
then also the alt for the source. This
will be equal to our thumbnail URL. But
here's the thing. We don't get any data.
We want to get right here. If I hover
over course, we want to get these types.
So, how can we get them? Well, we want
to get them through the params, right? I
want to pass them here as props and then
use them and pass my thumbnail URL for
the source. So, in theory, we could, for
example, create an interface I props.
Then I can h could go here just copy all
of the types paste them inside of here
then the structure everything and then I
will get my data. Yes, this works and
this is also what I have done for most
of my career to be honest with you. But
here's the thing. If we for example
later on update this query so we could
for example get the category and if I
select or set this to true our whole
interface would break because we would
have a new item. then I would have to go
to the admin course card, update the
interface. You see the problem? It's
annoying and it's not scalable because
if we reuse this type in multiple places
and then also recreated in multiple
places, then it won't work. So, we want
you to somehow infer the types from this
query itself. This means the types
should be almost dynamic. They should
update with the query itself. So, how
can we achieve something like that?
Well, thankfully I recently found uh
found out about a way to infer the type
of or the types of this query. We can go
underneath the export async function. So
in this admin get courses um file and
then we can create an export type admin
course type and this will be equal to
awaited. Then we want to pass a generic
and inside of here we want to get the
return type and we can again pass a
generic and this will be type of admin
get courses. This means the name of this
function admin get courses. So we pass
it as a generic and since this is an
array because if I would hover over
admin get courses you will see that this
will return as an array but I want to
get this singular object. This means we
can append an array symbol or we can
append array symbols with a zero inside
of there. And if I hover over the admin
uh course type, then you will see that
we get all of the types here. And I and
if I for example add the category inside
of here, this would also update. So if I
set this to true and hover again over
here, I will get the category. So this
is dynamic and that's exactly what you
want. So we can copy the name admin
course type. Then we can go back to the
admin course card. I want you still
create an interface. We will still need
it. So I uh props great name and inside
of here we will get data and data will
be of type admin course type. We want to
import that from our data access layer.
And then in our params we can
destructure them and this will be of
type I app props. Then where I
destructure it I want to get the data
and we can finally get started using the
data. So we can pass our data dot file
key for the source and for the alt this
will just be I don't know thumbnail URL.
Yeah, I don't really care. So we want to
then use the admin course card for or in
our page. So we can delete the P tag. We
can get the admin course card from the
components. This is self-closing. As you
see, we get an error and that's first of
all because we are missing the key
property. This will be equal to course
do ID and also we are missing the data
property. And this will be equal to our
data. So if we pass our course, you will
see that this error goes away. So if we
go back and do a hard refresh, we get an
error. Image with source laala is
missing required width property. You
know what? We can add a width and
height. So here's the thing. When you
use the image component in XJS and you
use a remote URL as we do right now, we
have to then define a width and height
property. If you use just a local image
which you import here, then you don't
have to define the width and height
because it's just inferred. But since
this is a remote URL, Nex.js can't
really infer the width and height. So we
can just add a width and height. So for
the width, this will be 600. And then
for the height, this will be 400. This
means if we again go back, we shouldn't
get this error anymore. But we get a new
error. Failed to construct URL. invalid
URL. What's the problem? Well, here's
the thing. What do we store in our
database for the file key? Well, we just
store the file key. We don't store the
real URL. So, we can head over back to
the Tigris dashboard. And then inside of
here, we can click on any file. It does
not really matter. So, for example, I
can get this file and I can just not
download it, but we can copy the URL and
open it in a new tab. And here you will
see the domain Marshall LMS YouTube
video subscribe.fly.sto.tigwress.deaf
and then slash the ID or slash the key.
This means we can copy everything which
is in front of the key. So again this is
the bucket name. Thenfly dots
storage.tigress.deaf.
I will copy this. We can go back and
just to not forget it or to not delete
it I will paste it right here. So again,
https/bucket
name.fly.sto.tigy.deaf.
So how can we construct our URL? Well,
it would make a lot of sense to just
create a new hook and then use it or
yeah, use the hook to construct the URL.
So we can open the explorer again. We
want to go into the hooks folder and we
will create a new file called
use-construct.ts.
I hope I spelled this correctly. I think
so. And then inside of here, we want to
create pretty much a new hook. So,
here's the thing. For example, is this
try catch file function a hook? No, it
isn't a hook. But still, I store it in
the hooks folder because it just kind of
makes sense to me. Of course, in theory,
you would probably want to create some
sort of functions folder or stuff like
that, but it would be empty. So, that's
the reason or it would only have this
one file. So that's the reason why I
store the try catch file in the hooks
folder even though it's not really a
hook. And the same thing is also true
for um use construct. This won't really
be a hook. It will be just a function.
Nevertheless, it makes a lot of sense to
store it inside of here. And also this
shouldn't be use construct but use
construct URL. So this will make a bit
more sense. Then inside of here we want
to create an export function. This will
be use construct URL. And then we want
to get the key in the params. This will
be of type string. And then we can just
open it. Inside of here we want to
create a return statement. And we will
construct the URL here. This means we
can use optics. Then if I go back to my
admin course card, we can first of all
copy this https colon / slash. We can
paste it inside of here. Then what was
the next value? The next value was the
bucket name. This means we can use
dynamic values. We can get our envy
variable from the lip folder and we want
to get the bucket name. So next public
s3 bucket name images. Okay. And then
the next value we can again go back. So
bucket name then it was dofly.s
storage.tigus.deaf.
We want to copy that paste it right
here. And then we want to add a slash
and the next value will be the key. This
means again a dynamic value. And then
key. And this is our URL. again https
col//bucket
name.fly.s
storage.htigquest.deaf/dynamic
value key and this should already be it.
One thing which we can do is maybe also
add a return type right uh why not this
will be of type string. This means the
return type of this function is a
string. As you see we don't have to do
that because it's already inferred but
it's always nice to explicitly mention
it. So we can again close this file and
we can also delete this comment and we
can use this hook this function and get
or construct the URL. So above the
return statement I will create a
constant farm nail URL and this will be
equal to use construct URL. This is
imported from the hooks folder and as an
argument we want to pass the file key.
This means data dofile key and then
instead of passing the file key as a
source we will pass the thumbnail URL.
This means if I again go back I can
close this and again do a hard refresh I
get a new error invalid source prop blah
blah blah or next image host name la is
not configured. So what's the problem?
Well nextjs or not next.js but the image
component optimizes your images. This
has a resource cost. And if we again we
want to look at our application from an
attacker's uh perspective. If an
attacker sees that, what would he say?
Damn, this user optimizes images for
free. Let me just pass my URL. You don't
want that. And this is also a security.
You could say they try to prevent
something like that. And that's the
reason why you have to specifically pass
the host name in your configuration file
because with that you say, hey, Nex.js
JS or Versel only optimize these images
from this host name. If it's a different
host name then don't optimize the files.
So we can first of all copy the host
name which they already provide us with
here. Then we can go back to the next
doconfig file. And inside of here we
want to get the images property. This is
an object. Inside of here we can get
remote patterns. Sorry this is my Gmail.
And this will be equal to an array. And
then also we want to open an object
inside of here because the object is the
individual host name if this makes
sense. So we will get a few properties.
First of all the host name. This is what
I just copied. So this is the URL. Then
we have to also pass the port and the
port will be an empty string. And then
we want to also pass the host or not
host but the protocol and this will be
HTTPS. I don't know what's wrong.
Normally they also give us auto
completion. Probably some intern made a
mistake. So yeah, it should be https.
And if I open my terminal, I get an
error here. Hm. So they've found or they
tried to restart the server. It didn't
work. So I will just restart it myself.
Maybe this will fix the problem. Who
knows? So if I go back and do a hard
refresh, will this error go away? Yeah,
it works again. So this is the image.
And in my terminal, I also don't get any
errors anymore. This means we can close
the next doconfig file. And yeah, again,
we get the image. It's a bit too big as
you see, but we will fix it a bit later
on. For now, I want to style the image.
This means we can add a class name and
this will be width of full rounded top
which will be LG aspect and this will be
video. This is like a 16x9 aspect ratio.
Then we can also say height full and
object which will be cover. So this
should already look quite nice. Yeah,
it's a bit too big as you see. But don't
worry, we will fix it later on. Then we
can continue. This is our image. As the
next step, I want to render the title,
small description, a bit of info like
the duration and also the level and then
the button to edit the course. This
means we can go underneath the image. We
want to get the cart content component.
And in the cart content, we can get the
link component from next /link. Inside
of here, uh we I want to first of all
render the title. This means data.title.
And for the link, we have to also
provide an href. And then inside of
here, I want to use optics because I
want to pass the course ID into the URL.
This means this will be
/admin/courses/data.
ID because we when the user clicks on
the title I want to redirect the user to
the edit route. Currently we don't have
an edit route but later on we will have
one. Then we can also give it a class
name and this will be font medium text
LG line clamp 2. Line clamp 2 means that
if the text is too big it will just be
limited at two lines. So it won't create
four lines or five lines or anything
like that. The limit is two lines. We
can also say on hover underline so a
nice little animation and then also
group dash hover and this will be text
primary and also transition which will
be colors. So this should already look
quite nice and yeah this is our title
subscribe now. So we can again go back
and you know what this big image kind of
I don't know it breaks everything so I
think we should maybe update this a bit.
So we can go back to our page.tsx tsx
and inside of here I want to create a
grid layout because honestly the image
is just too big. So we can give this
wrapper div uh a class name and this
will be grid then also grid columns of
one this will be on the mobile screen or
bigger this will be grid columns two and
then on MD or bigger this will be again
grid columns one and on LG or bigger
this will be grid columns of two. Also I
want to give it a gap and this will be
seven. So this should already look way
better and yes as you see it takes less
space and with that it also looks
better. This means we can go back to the
admin course card again to our component
and we can continue. So we have finished
with the title and what's the next
thing? Well the next thing is our
description. This means underneath the
link component we can create a p tag and
inside of here we want to get a data do
small description. We can also style it.
So we can give it a class name first of
all line clamp two. This means the text
will have a maximum you could say
length. So it will only again take two
lines not anymore. It can be smaller. It
can be one line but it can't be bigger
than two lines. Then we can also say
text which will be SM text muted
foreground to have this grayish color
leading which will be tight. What is
leading? This is the line height and
then also margin top two. So as you see
this is our description. It's quite
small but nevertheless we have a
description. So what's the next thing?
Well as a next step I want to render
like a little bit how would you say like
little info slots. This means first of
all the duration and then also the um
level. So intermediate hard or advanced
or beginner. This means we can go back
and we want to go underneath the P tag
and we want to create a new div. This
will be the wrapper div. So we can give
it a class name. This will be margin top
four flex items which will be center and
gap x5 to have some spacing in between
because we will have two slots. Then we
want to create another div and this will
be the wrapper div for first of all the
duration. Inside of here I want to get
the timer icon. This is imported from
lucid react. And I want to give it a
class name. This will be size six. This
means width six and height six padding
one and rounded which will be MD. So it
won't be very rounded. It will have a
light rounding. Then the text will be
primary. This means the orange color.
And BG will be primary but this
shouldn't take the full opacity. This
means / 10 10% opacity. And if I again
go back you will see yeah this looks
kind of nice. Nevertheless, we still
want to also render the duration itself.
This means underneath the timer icon but
still in the div we can get a p tag and
we want to get the data dot duration.
Also I want to append an h at the end.
So this means xyz hours. And we can of
course also style it and this will be
text sm and text muted foreground. This
means a grayish color as you see. Yeah
this is good but it should be aligned
horizontally. Currently it's aligned as
a column. This means flex column. So we
can style this diff and this will be
flex item center and gap x of two to
have some spacing in between and this
already looks quite nice. Then we can
copy paste this diff one more time and
this will be for the level. So instead
of rendering a timer icon I want to get
the school icon and for the p tag
instead of rendering the data duration
we want to get the level. Uh we can also
delete the h because this isn't an hour
anymore. And if we go back 50 hours and
beginner very cool. And as the last
step, we want to display a button down
below to edit the course. This means we
can go back. We want to go underneath
this div and this div. So just above the
card content and we can get the link
component or we already imported it.
This means we can open it and inside of
here I want to just say edit course.
Also I want to render an icon. This
means I can get the arrow uh white icon
from lucid react. This is self-closing.
And then I can give it a class name
which will be size four. As you see the
link currently complains and that's
because we have to pass an href. And for
the href, I want to again pass up takes
because when the user clicks on this
button, we want to redirect the user to
this edit route. This means um we can
just scroll to the top and we can copy
this URL. So this href I will copy it
and then again paste it down below. And
also after this data do ID I want to add
/edit. The same thing is also true for
this title or this href slashedit. Yeah
this should already be it. This means if
we again go back. Yeah this is a link
but this should look like a shared CN
button. This means we can give the link
a class name. And as you all know what
will we use? We will use the button
variance function. we can invoke it and
then we want to also destructure it
because um we want to give it the width
full. This means we can add a class name
and then for the class name this will be
width full. As you see the button takes
the whole width and this is already way
better. Nevertheless, we need some
margin to the top. This means we can
also add a margin top which will be
four. And this is already very very
nice. Nevertheless, we have one problem.
You see this is our cart but on the top
it literally has some padding. I don't
want that. This looks ugly. So we can go
back. We can go to the main div and we
want to also say padding Y will be zero
and gap will be zero. This means if we
go back yeah this already looks better
but the bottom is kind of broken. This
means our content. So we can also style
our cart content itself and we can give
it a class name and this will be padding
4. And as you see this also looks way
better. So the admin cart is almost
finished and we want to also uh render
the drop-down menu. This means we can go
back into this div. So here I created
this dummy diff and first of all we want
to give it a class name because this
will be positioned absolutely on the top
right corner. So this will be absolute
top which will be two and then also
right two. Then we want to give it a Z
index and this will be 10. Inside of
this div as mentioned I want to create a
drop-down menu. This means we can get
the drop-down menu component from the
components. We want to open it. Inside
of here we can get a drop-down menu
trigger. This is also imported from the
components. Then inside of here I want
to render a button. And since this is a
component in a component, I have to also
give the drop-down menu trigger an ask
child property. Inside of here, I can
get the button component from the
components. And the button needs a
variant. The variant will be secondary.
Then uh the size, this will be icon
because it shouldn't be too big. And
then for the button itself, I want to
get a more vertical icon. This is
imported from Lucid React. And then I
want to give it a class name which will
be size four. As you see, we should see
the trigger or the button here. And yes,
it looks quite nice. The only problem is
if I click on it, literally nothing
happens. This means we want to create
drop-down menu content. So, underneath
the drop-own menu trigger, we can get
drop or the drop-down menu content
component imported from the components.
And this drop-down menu content needs
one property, one key property, which is
the align property. I mean you don't
have to define it because as a default
it will just um select center but I want
to align this drop-own menu content to
the right side. This means end. And if I
click on it again nothing happens or we
get this little thingy but of course the
content itself is missing. Also we can
give it a class name with a width and
this will be 48. And then in the
drop-own menu content we want to render
drop-down menu items. So we can get the
drop-own menu item component from the
components and inside of here I want to
render the link component. The thing is
since this is a component in a component
we have to give the drop-down menu item
an as child property. Then for the link
we want to give it an href and if the
user clicks on the link we want to
redirect the user to edit um or to the
edit page. This means we can just copy
the href from our previous link and
paste it inside of here. Then in the
link um I want to first of all get the
pencil icon from Lucid React. This is
self-closing. And then for the class
name this will be size 4 and margin
right two. And after the pencil but
still in the link um I want you to say
edit course. So I guess it's time to
test it out. And what do we see right
here? Yes, edit course. And if I click
on it I will get redirected but we get a
four not found. And that's because this
edit route right now does not exist.
Then I want to create one more drop-down
menu item and this will be to preview
the course. This means we can just copy
paste drop-own menu item. So the
component instead of saying edit course
we will say preview for the icon this
will be the I icon imported from Lucid
React. And for the href um this will be
slashcourses/data.sluck.
And then I want to also delete the
slashedit at the end. This means if I
again go back. Yes, this looks quite
good. And then as the last item I want
to display a delete button. This means
we can go back underneath the drop-own
menu item. We can get the drop-down menu
separator. This is imported from the
components and it's self-closing. And
here we can get the drop-down menu or we
can just copy paste again this drop-own
menu item component underneath the
separator for the text. This will be
delete course for the link. This will be
/admin
/courses
/data.
ID and then slash delete. And this
should already be it. Maybe we can also
update. We have to update the icon of
course. So this will be the trash 2 icon
imported from Lucid React. And I want to
also give it a color. This means text
which will be uh destructive. If I save
this and again go back. Yes, this looks
absolutely beautiful. So, we are
finished with our admin course card or
in other words with our general course
overview route and as the next step I
want to create the edit course route.
So, to create our edit route, we have to
first of all create a new route. Who
would have thought? Because if I click
on edit course, what will happen? Well,
we will get redirected and as you see
this is a 44 not found. The route does
not exist. But how does the URL
structure look like? Well,
slashadmin/courses
slash a course ID itself/add
uh slashedit. This means we can also
update our code structure, right? We can
create a new route. So in the we want to
go into the app folder into the admin
folder into the courses folder and then
inside of here we want to create a
dynamic route because we want to get the
course ID. How do you create dynamic
routes in XJS? Well, you use array
brackets. So in the courses folder, we
can create a new folder. Since this is a
dynamic route, this will be array
brackets or we will right here create
array brackets. And then in the array
brackets, we will create the name. This
will be the course ID. In this folder,
we can create another folder because
again, how does the route structure look
like? Well, slashcourse id /edit. This
means we can go back and inside of here
we will create a new folder, a new route
called edit and then we can create a
page.tsx. Since this is a route we can
do or we can create an export default
function called edit route and then we
can just open this function. Inside of
here we can create a standard return
with a statement with a diff h1. And I
will say hello world yo. That means if I
go back and do a hard refresh, I should
see hello world. Yo, and that's exactly
what is happening. And also, by the way,
here's a quick shortcut. If you click on
commandB, the sidebar collapses. So,
this is this is very cool. As you see, I
love it. Oh, I love the component. So,
we can style or we can get started with
the route. So, um I will delete this H1.
We will leave the div. And I want to
create a new H1 for the content. This
will be edit course. and then colon
because I want to render the name of the
course. But for that we have to first of
all fetch the course itself the data for
the course. This means we want to also
create a new file in our data access
layer. This means we want to go into our
app folder into the data folder into the
admin folder and we want to create a new
file called admin-get-course
because this is a singular course.ts.
Again we want to import server only
because this function should only run
and should also only be called in server
or in other words uh in a server
environment. So in server components as
an example. Then what we want to do is
create an export function or export
async function because we will fetch
data. This will be called admin get
course. Uh and then we can just open the
function inside of here. We want to
first of all call the require admin
function because only admins should get
this data or should have the ability to
get this data and also view the data.
And then underneath this function we
want to get our data with Prisma because
we now validate that the user is
verified or has a valid user session and
is also an admin. So we can create a
constant data and this will be equal to
a rate Prisma. Prismos imported from the
lip folder dot course.find find unique
because we want to find one unique
singular whatever course I think you
understand what I mean so we can invoke
this the structured and here's the thing
since we want to find a specific course
we have to pass a wear property because
again if I don't pass a wear property we
will just get any course but I want to
find a specific one and what is
something unique what is the primary key
in our schema it's the ID this means I
want to find a course where the ID
matches the ID which I provide. This
means in the params we can get an ID
which will be of type string and then we
can pass it here for the ID. Then we
want to of course create an uh select
statement. And what do we want to get?
Well, we want to get an ID. So we can
set this to true. Maybe also a title,
then a description. I want to also get
the file key. Um for example, also the
price, then also the duration. And you
want to always set this to true as you
see because with that you select the
individual property then maybe also the
level. I pretty much want to get almost
everything. So um level then also the
status then also the slug itself and
also the small description and then also
at the end the category. This should be
it for now. Maybe we will have to update
it later on or we will have to update it
later on but for now this is fine
enough. Then underneath this constant
data, I want you to create an if
statement. Because here's the thing,
this data could be defined. We could get
a result, but it could also be null.
Because if the ID is incorrect, for
example, instead of passing this ID, I
will pass some dumb gibberish. Then the
data will not be defined. We won't get
any cause. This means we can create an
if statement and we want to say if we
don't get any data, then we want to
return not found. Not found is imported
from next slashnavigation and we can
then invoke it. What is not found? Good
question. Not found will trigger a four
for not found page. So it will redirect
you internally to a non not found route
and this not found route will display a
404 not found error. That's it. It's
quite simple. Again, you can also head
over to the YouTube uh to the not
YouTube but to the next.js JS
documentation to learn more about this
not found function and if we get data we
want to then also return the data. This
means we can go back to the page.tsx and
we can fetch the data. So above the
return statement we can create a
constant data and this will be equal to
a rate admin get course. We can invoke
it and as you see we get two errors. The
first problem is related to um marking
the function as asynchronous. This means
we can say export default async function
and the second error relates to our
arguments because the function expects
one argument but we pass zero. And
what's the argument? It's the ID. But
how can we get the ID? The ID is stored
in our URL. Well, here's the thing. This
is a dynamic folder, a dynamic route. I
mean the folder is not dynamic. It's
static. The route is dynamic. This means
we can get the key or yeah, the key in
this case. So this ID not key and we can
get it through our params. And here's
the thing in previous versions of Nex.js
you could just structure the params and
then get the ID itself the course ID.
But with NexJS15 they changed it up a
bit because the params are now um a
promise. This means what we can do is
create a type. This type will be called
params uppercased and this will be equal
to a promise. Then we can pass a generic
open an object and how is our ID called
or how is our dynamic route called?
Well, it's called course ID. This means
inside of here I can pass course ID and
this will be of type string. Also, I
want to spell promise correctly. And
this looks good. So here's the thing. If
this dynamic folder would be called
hello, then you would want to get hello
here. If this would be called hey, then
you would want to get hey. I think you
understand what I'm trying to tell you.
And then we want to get the params. So
we can d the structure and then the
params will have a type of uppercase
params. So this should already be it. As
you all know again this is a promise
which means we have to await these um or
this param itself the course ID. So this
will be a constant. we can destructure
it and this will be equal to arate
params and then where I d the structure
I can get the course ID itself and then
we can just copy it and paste it as an
argument. So this means in theory we
should get our data. So for the edit
course we can then pass a span element
not PSN but span and then we can get the
data dot title. Of course, we want to
also style the span. But you know what?
For now, I want to first of all see if
we even get the data because if I go
back edit course, subscribe. Now, so as
you see, we get the correct data. But
you know what? I will now for example
delete the ID or I will create a fake
ID. If I click on enter, we will get
this four for not found page because the
id which we passed as a param here or so
or in the where statement is not a real
id which means this not found function
was triggered and it returned this four
for not found page. So this works
exactly as expected which means we can
finish off or not finish I guess we have
to first of all start with this edit
route. So we can first of all style the
H1. This will be text 3 XL font which
will be bold and margin bottom of eight.
And then uh we want to also style the
span and this will have a class name
which will be text primary the orange
color and then also underline. And as a
next step I want to create an
interesting layout. So um I will come to
this a bit later on. This is
interesting. This is the data access
layer but I want to show you the UI for
now. So this is our screen. Our yeah our
screen. And here's the thing. On the top
we first of all have a little title.
This is this one. Then I want to display
two tabs. So tab one and tap two. This
tab will be there to edit base info. And
this tab will be there for the course
structure. So if the user clicks on this
tab, we will again just showcase the
form or we will render the form then to
update the title, to update the slug,
the thumbnail and stuff like that. And
if the user clicks on this tab, then we
will display the course structure. This
means this drag u is it called? Yeah,
drag and drop thingy. So where the user
can then create a new chapter, a new
lesson and stuff like that. This means
what we can do is again go back and we
want to first of all create the tabs. So
underneath the H1 but still in the div
we want to get a tabs component from the
components. Then we want to open it. The
tabs has to get one key property and
this is the default value. Currently we
haven't implemented any value. So this
will be an empty string for now but we
will update it later on. Then in the
tabs we have to create a tabs list or we
have to render the tabs list component.
This is imported from the components and
inside of here we want to get the tabs
trigger component. So the tabs trigger
is this button. The button which we will
then showcase again basic info and
course structure. This means if we go
back the value will be basic info. And
as you see this uh tabs trigger
currently complaints. That's because it
expects one property which is the value
property. So in this case value will be
equal to basic dash info and then we can
copy paste the tabs trigger and this
will be for the course structure. So
course structure for the value this will
also be course dash structure and this
should be lowercase and then we can also
set our default value and this will be
basic info. So this means if we again go
back we should see something and yeah
these are our two tabs and you know what
they don't look good what I mean by that
is these two these two buttons this tabs
component should take the whole width
this means we can update the tabs
component give it a class name and this
will be width full and this should in
theory take the whole width let's see hm
this didn't work what's the problem well
it's quite simple we want to also update
our tabs list because For our tabs list,
we want to um create first of all a grid
with two columns. This means grid
columns too because we have two uh tabs
trigger and also width of full to take
the whole width. Yes, that's what I
wanted. So these are our two buttons.
This means we can go back and underneath
the tabs list we want to render tabs
content or the tabs content component.
This is imported from the components and
for the tabs content we have to also
provide the value because chat CN UI or
I guess in theory radics UI has to know
um to which tabs trigger it corresponds
to. In this case this will be for the
basic info. So I can copy the value name
and paste it for the value. Then inside
of here we want to render a cart. This
means we can get the cart from the
components. Then a cart header. This is
the next step. And in the cart header,
we want to get the card title. For the
card title, this will be uh basic info.
Then we can also get the card
description. For the card description,
this will be added basic information
about the course. This means if we again
go back, you will see the title and then
the description. I think the font weight
and the size is big enough. So I don't
see any reason to update anything. As
next step, we want to render the card
content. This means underneath the cart
header, we can get a card content from
the components. And here's the thing. We
want to create a separate component. Why
is that? Well, what is this? This is a
file. Who would have thought? But what
is it also? It's a server component.
This means if we need interactivity, it
won't work. But our form will need the
use form hook. It will need the use
stated. It will need interactivity and
it won't work inside of here. This means
we want to open our explorer and what we
want to do is create another components
folder because here's the thing. We will
create a separate component. I already
mentioned that. But where should we
store it? I mean the component will be
called for example edit form. Let's call
it like that. Where would you store it?
Would you store it in this components
folder? Would you store it in your main
components folder? What do you think?
What's the best location for this edit
form component? Well, here's the thing.
In my opinion, this is a very local
component. What I mean by that is I will
only use it in the edit route. This
means it would also make a lot of sense
to create a separate component uh
components folder for this edit route
itself because this component this um
edit form will only be used in the edit
route itself. If I would reuse it of
course for example throughout the
courses folder as an example then I
would create it in this components
folder. But since I will only use it in
the edit route, I will also create a new
components folder in the edit folder
itself or route. Call it however you
want to. So this will be underscore
components. And then inside of here we
can create a new file. What do you think
would be a good name? Maybe edit form.
Is this fine enough? Maybe edit course
form. Yeah, edit course form.tsx.
So first of all, this will be a client
component. This means use client. And
then since this is just a simple
function, we can create an export
function. This will be called edit
course form. And then we want to just
open it. And of course inside of here,
we want to create a return statement
with for example an H1 with some dummy
data. We can then go back to the edit
route and then just render the edit
course form component which is imported
from the components. As you see, we see
a lot of gibberish. So here's the thing
inside of here. I want to literally
showcase or render the same form as the
one which we already created in the
creation route. So what can we do? Well,
we can literally just copy everything
from the return statement. Maybe not
everything. We will just copy this form.
So as you see in the creation route, we
have a link. We don't need it. We have a
card. We don't need it. We already have
our own card. We only need the form and
of course also the content in the form.
This means we can just copy it and paste
it inside of here. I can delete
everything in the return statement and
paste it inside of here. As you see, we
get a lot of errors. But that's fine. We
can just do a lot of copy pasting. So
from our creation route, we can first of
all copy this constant form. So where we
initialize the use form hook, we will I
will copy it, go back and paste it above
the return statement. As you see again,
I get a few import errors. That's fine.
Don't worry about it. Then I can also
copy the onsubmit function and I will
also copy the comment paste it
underneath the constant form. And as you
see we get even more errors but it's
okay don't worry. Then from the creation
route I want you also copy this use
router uh hook and then also the use
transition. So I will copy both and
paste it also above the form itself. So
I think everything has been defined and
the last problem is that we have all of
these import errors. This means what we
can do for now is literally just copy
paste everything. So we can copy the
import statement for for the button
itself. Paste it inside of here. As you
see the import statement is correct. But
we won't use the button variance. So we
can delete it. Then we have the cart.
Again I can copy it and paste it. This
will import everything but the cart is
not used. So we can again delete it.
Then we have the course categories,
course schema, stuff like that. We can
copy the import statement and paste it.
As you see, no errors. The next step is
to get all of the icons. And you know
what? I will just copy everything and
then remove everything that I don't
need. So I will just copy it, paste it,
and voila. And as you see, we get a few
errors, but that's fine. So we don't
need the link component. We can delete
it. We don't need the arrow left icon.
We can delete it. Then we don't need the
card component. We can delete it. We
don't need the button variants. And then
there's only one more error left and
that's for the create course server
action. So I will comment it out for
now. It's fine. Uh what other errors do
we have? This one. That's fine. This
one. This one. This is also fine. I
think this is the only error. So our
server action itself. This means we want
to create a new edit course server
action. So where would it make sense to
create this new actions file in the
courses route? in the create route or in
the folder. Well, it will make a lot of
sense to create the actions file in the
edit folder because inside of there I
want to specifically store the server
action to edit the course. This means in
the edit folder we can create an
actions.ts file and since inside of here
we want to create server actions we have
to also mark the file with the use
server directive. Inside of here we want
to first of all export an a function.
This means export async function. This
will be called edit course and then we
can just open it. So here's the thing.
We want to first of all make sure that
the user has a valid user session and is
also an admin. This means we can say
constant user equals to a rate require
admin. We can import it from our data
access layer. And with this we make sure
that the user has a valid user session
and is an admin. If not, we will
redirect the user to the correct URL.
The next step is to create a try and
also catch statement. And as you know,
we want to return objects. And if I
currently try to return an object, I
don't get any TypeScript types. This
isn't great. So, how can we fix this
problem? Well, as you all know, I hope
you remember it at least, we created
this type API response and we want to
add it to our return type. So we want to
create a return type parameter. This
means after these parentheses we can
create a colon. This will be equal to a
promise. We want to pass generic and in
the generic we want to get the API
response type. This means if I again try
to create a return object we will get a
status and message. Great. This works
beautifully. And what's the next step?
Well what do we want to get through our
params? The data who fought. This means
we can get data and this will be of type
or of the type course schema type
imported from the Z schemas file. What's
the next step? The next step is to do
serverside validation. This means we can
create a constant result and this will
be equal to course schema imported from
the Z schemas files save pass and as an
argument we want to pass the data
itself. The next step is to check if the
result if the validation was successful
or not. This means we can create an if
statement and if the result is not
successful then we want to return an
object. For the status this will be
error and for the message this will just
be invalid data because the data is
quite invalid. So after the if statement
we know that the data is safe to use and
that we can create a mutation. This
means we can say await Prisma. Prisma is
imported from the lip folder dot course
and we want to update the course. This
means we can use the update method. We
want to invoke it the structured and
inside of here we have to first of all
provide the wear method because we don't
want to update any course. We want to
update a specific course. This means we
want to use the primary key. This is our
ID and I want to update a course where
the ID matches the course ID. Hm, but I
don't get the course ID. Well, I want to
get it through my params. So, we will
get data and we will also get the course
ID itself. This means we can add a
comma, get the course ID and this will
be of type string. Did I spell course ID
correctly? I think so. So, course ID
looks good and we can paste it uh right
here for the ID. But as you see, I still
get an error. What's the problem? Well,
we have to also define the user ID
because again we have a one to many
relationship and the user could you say
relation? Yeah, I think the user
relation is not optional. This means we
have to define the user ID because only
the user who um created the course can
also update the course and this will be
equal to the user user id. As you see we
still get an error. What's the problem?
Well, we are missing data. We want to
update data. And as you all know, in
theory, we could do everything manually.
We could get the categories, set it
equal to the result dot data category.
But this is so annoying. Instead, we can
spread our result. So, dot dot dot
result dot data. And voila, this already
looks way better. The last step is to
also return a success object. This means
return object. For the status, this will
be success. And then for the message
this will be cause updated successfully.
Of course we want to also catch any
errors. This means we can also create a
return. We want to open an object for
the status. This will be error. And then
for the message itself this will be
failed to update course. So this looks
good and we can use the server action
and we can copy the name edit course and
use it in the edit course form because
currently we call the create course
function server action. We don't want to
do that. So I will delete it and instead
I want to import edit course from the
actions file. As you see we get one
error and that's because expected two
arguments but got one. We passed the
data but we did not pass the course ID.
And how will we get our ID? Good
question. So here's the thing. I want to
get my data through the params. So here
I have my params and I want to get all
of the data. And also as you see
currently we pass for the default
values, nothing. So empty strings and
price zero and stuff like that. But this
is not true. Our form our course already
exists. We already have data which we
can propagate here. This means through
the params I want to get my data. But
here's again the thing. If I go to the
edit route and hover over data, I get my
data. But do I want to copy paste it?
No, not really. Instead, I want to again
infer the type right from the query.
This means we can go back to our data
access layer. So into the data folder,
admin folder, admin get course. And then
we can create a new type. This means
export type. This will be called admin
course type. And this will be equal to
awaited. Then we want to pass a generic
return type. Again we want to pass a
generic and this will be type of admin
get course. This means the name of the
function itself. And if I hover over
this type you will see that I get all of
the correct types. Great. So I will copy
the name go back to the creation or not
to the creation but to the edit course
form and inside of here I want to first
of all again create an interface. This
means interface app props. Then I want
to get data and this will be of type
admin get course type. And as you see I
get two options admin course type admin
course type. This isn't great. So I will
rename it. Instead of admin course type
this will be admin course singular type.
I think this will be a bit better or
could we say edit? No admin course
singular type. And then again inside of
here I can get the admin course singular
type imported from the data access
layer. And then in the params we can the
swapshot this will be of type I props
and then we can get our data. Then for
our default values we can paste our real
data. This means for the title this will
be equal to data.title.
For the description this will be equal
to data.escription.
For the file key, this will be data
dofile key. For the price, data dot
price. For the duration, data dot
duration. For the uh level, not
beginner, but data dot uh not beginner
data. For the category, this will be who
would have thought data.category.
For the status, this will be data.
status. For the slug, this will be data
dot slug. And for the small description,
data do small description. As you see,
we get one error and that's kind of
annoying. What's the problem? It says
type string is not assignable to type
development, business, finance. So all
of our categories. So what the error is
trying to tell us is that data.category
is a string. But our Z schemas file or
our Z schema itself expects uh this
category property as you see. But this
is not a normal string. but instead it's
an array of different strings. So,
development, business, finance, and it
says this random string is not
assignable to this um array. So, how can
we fix it? Because we know that the data
category is the correct type. Well, we
can say as course schema type. This is
the zot schema itself. And then we can
add an array and we want to get the
category. And this will remove this
error as you see. And the and this is
already great. Nevertheless, there's
still one problem and this is the edit
course because we want to pass the ID.
This means we can add a comma and then
this will be our data do ID. Then do we
want to update anything for the onsubmit
function? D. This all looks good. No.
Nope. This is great. Uh I think the
submit button this will need a change
because we currently say create course.
But do we create a course? No, we added
the course. This means instead of saying
create course I will just say for
example update course and then for the
pending state instead of saying uh
creating I will say updating. So this
should or this already looks good. We
can also update our edit route because
it currently throws one error. What's
the problem? Well the edit course form
needs one property the data property. So
we can get data and this will be equal
to our data. This error is gone. And
this means if we go back and do a hard
refresh. Oh my god, this is our form. It
looks so beautiful. Title slug. Small
description. Big description. Huh?
Where's my thumbnail URL? H. This is not
good. This does not look good. What's
the problem? Well, here's the thing. If
we go back and open our uploader
component, you will see that we get the
value. The value is the file key itself.
And we only set the key itself but we
want to also set the object URL. So we
get this object URL and since we have
the value we can also construct uh
construct the URL. This means above the
use state we can use our use construct
URL hook. So this will be or a constant
then this will be called file URL and
this will be equal to use construct URL
imported from the hooks folder and then
as an argument we want to provide our
value. As you see we get an error.
What's the problem? Type string or
undefined is not assignable to type
string. So here's the thing. This value
as you know is optional. That's why we
want to say if we don't have any value,
then we can use the or sign and just
pass an empty string. And then for the
object URL, this will be equal to the
file URL. And this should already be it.
This means if I go back. Wow. Oh my god.
We get the thumbnail image. Wow. I'm so
proud of you guys. We have finished. We
implemented the edit route. It looks
beautiful. But of course, we have to
test it out. This means we have to see
if it really works. This means instead
of saying subscribe now, this will now
be subscribe today exclamation mark.
Then I want to also generate the new
slug. And if I click on update course
duh course updated successfully, we got
redirected and it says subscri uh
subscribe today. So it really worked.
And if I click on edit course, it should
also update and it updated. Oh my god,
it works. So as the next step I want to
continue with the course structure and
inside of there we will allow the user
to create um chapters and then also
lessons. Chapters will pretty much
function like categories. So chapter
number one and then this chapter will
have multiple lessons. Lesson number
one, lesson number two, lesson number
three. And the thing is we will also
implement drag and drop functionality so
that the user can reorder chapters and
lessons. So for example, for now chapter
1 is the first and chapter 2 comes down
and chapter 3. But now I want to reorder
the structure and chapter uh three
should be the first chapter using this
D&D. So using drag and drop we will
allow the user to reorder the structure
easily. This means we want to first of
all go back to the edit form or to the
page.tsx.
And currently we only have one tabs
content and this is for as you see this
basic info. This means what we can do is
literally just copy paste the tabs
content instead of uh passing basic info
for the value. This will instead be
course structure. So we can pay uh copy
the name paste it. My god, copy it and
paste it inside of here. For the card
title, this will be course structure. So
I will just copy it and paste it. And
then for the card description, we can
just say something like here you can
update your course structure. So this
looks quite good. And then for the card
content, do we want to render the edit
course form? No, of course not. Because
if I go back course form, course form,
course form, course form. This isn't
nice. So uh we can just delete it from
here. And instead we want to create a
new component. This means we can open
the explorer go into this underscore
components folder where we already have
the added course form and we will create
another component and this will be the
course structure.tsx
file or the component itself. So since
this is a component we can create an
export function. This will be called
course structure and then we can just
open it. Then inside of here we can
first of all create a dummy return
statement with an H1 and hello world
just to see that everything works. This
means if we go back we can get the
course structure component from the
components. And if we again go back you
see hello spelling mistake. Yeah that's
fine. Then we can go back to the course
structure. And here's the thing I will
be honest with you. This section of this
video will be a bit dry because we will
write a lot of code and a lot of
complicated code. I will be honest with
you, it's not that easy and it was
probably this part is probably one of
the hardest parts or it is the hardest
part of this whole video. It's quite
complex. Nevertheless, I will try to
break down everything so that you can
also understand everything as I always
do. So we want to first of all delete
this return statement and we want to
create a new one inside of here. As
mentioned I want to implement drag and
drop functionality. Implementing drag
and drop functionality is not easy. It's
super hard especially if you want to do
it natively because you can of course
try to implement drag and drop
functionality without using any external
package. It's possible but you will
probably spend months uh implementing
everything. That's why we will use
DNDKit in this video. So, the website is
just dndkit.com
and as you see there's a new kit on the
blog. Wow, so funny. So, DND kit is a
lightweight, performant, accessible drag
and drop toolkit for React and we want
to use it to implement drag and drop
functionality. So, if we go to the
documentation, you will find the
sidebar. Here they give you a lot of
information about D&D kit. Again, it's
lightweight, modular, performant, and
most importantly, of course, accessible.
Accessibility is always important. And I
think or for my experience, this is
probably the best library on the market,
both based on the feature set, but also
based on the developer experience and
how easy it is to implement. It's still
not that easy to implement. It takes a
lot of boilerplate code, but it's better
than its alternatives. And we want to
specifically use the sortable preset
because we want to allow the user to
sort specific fields. So we will for
example allow the user to sort the
lessons but also the not categories but
the chapters. So we will pretty much
have um two containers and two
containers which can be sorted. So this
is even harder because we will have two
sortable contacts with multiple sortable
items. This is not that easy to
implement but we will do it in this
video. So what we can do is first of all
install dndkit. For that we want to
install the at dndkit/core
package. We can copy the name and then
in our terminal I will stop the dev
server and run pnpmi at dndkit core.
Then since we want to specifically
implement the sortable preset we have to
also install the uh sortable package.
And also what exactly does sortable
mean? Well, the sortable preset provides
the building blocks to build sortable
interfaces. And since we want to create
a sortable interface, we need this
sortable preset. This means we can copy
this package name and also install it.
PNPMI uh DND kit sortable. Then we can
restart the dev server and uh again and
then it's time to get started. So how
does the architecture look like? Well,
we can scroll a bit to the bottom and
then we should find this beautiful uh
section architecture. So, the sortable
preset builds on top of the primitives
exposed by uh the D&D kit core package
to help building sortable interfaces.
So, the sortable preset exposes two main
concepts sortable context and the use
sortable hook. The sortable context
provides information via context that is
consumed in the use sortable hook. The
use sortable hook is an abstraction that
composes the use droppable and use
dragable hooks. So these two hooks I p
are primarily used when you use dnd kit
natively. So without this preset which
is um sortable but sortable just
abstracts these two hooks and also
composes them into one hook which is
called use sortable and as you see we
use the use sortable hook and this is
the item and this is the droppable and
this is the dragable. So this is this
composition we have two things but they
are composed in one hook and as you see
also each use sortable item has its own
unique ID. So when we for example later
on will display multiple lessons each
lesson uh each lesson will have an ID ID
1 2 3 4 5 and then we will order the
items using this ID and then as you see
here they have a section on how to
implement a single container. So at a
high level the application structure to
implement a sortable list with single
containers looks as follows. We first of
all have the D&D context. Again, this
will just create the state management.
Then we have the sortable context. This
is also needed. And here we provide all
of our items. And right here you see we
provide specifically the ids. And then
we render all of the individual use or
the individual sortable items using the
use sortable hook. And each sortable
item has its unique ID which has to
correspond to the items array. as you
see here. And then when we for example
restructure this whole layout, so we
move this one item to the bottom, then
this ID or these ids or the whole
arrangement will update. Of course,
again, it can be a bit complicated at
the start, but uh once we implement it,
it won't be that hard anymore. It will
it won't be that complicated anymore. So
again, uh we want to first of all start
with the DND context provider. So in
addition to the DND context provider,
the sortable preset requires its own
context provider that contains the
sorted array of the unique identifiers
associated to each sortable item. So we
can first of all get started with this
example which means we want to first of
all implement the DND context. Again
this is like your global context which
handles all of the state management. So
we can first of all get DND context from
DND kit core. We want to open it and
here we have to provide a few properties
and the first one is collision detection
and collision detection will be equal to
rect. So recct
intersection. So rect intersection and
this is imported from at dnd kit core.
What is this? Good question. So here's
the thing. How does um this whole
sorting thing work? Well, they use an
algorithm. And to be specific, we use
this algorithm, direct intersection. If
we hover over it, it says returns the
rectangles that has the greatest
intersection area with a given rectangle
in an array of rectangles. Wow, this is
complicated. So, what does this mean? So
this algorithm detects a collision when
the rectangular bounding boxes, this
means the corners of this rectangular
box of the dragable and droppable
elements overlap. You can also use other
collision algorithms. I tested out most
of them and this one worked the best. So
for me it was a lot of trial and error
and at the end this one worked the best
and that's the reason why we will use
it. Then we have also a few other
properties which we have to define but
for now we will just skip them. Inside
of here we want to render a cart
component imported from the components
and then we want to get the cart header
imported from the components. So in the
cart header we will render a car title
and so we can get the car title and for
the car title I want to say chapters and
if we save this and again go back and as
you see we get an error and this is a
very weird error because it's kind of a
lot of gibberish. So what's the problem?
Well D&D kit itself requires or needs a
JavaScript bundle. It creates
interactivity. This means we have to
mark this with the use or the component
with the use client directive. This
means if we again go back we should see
something and as you see this is the
card with the title chapters. But you
know what I want to render a border
underneath this title. This means we can
go to the card header itself and we can
give it a class name which will be flex
flex which will be row items which will
be center to center everything in the
middle vertically. Then also justify
between because later on I want to
render um something. So a button next to
the chapters and I want to align the
children to the most outer corner so
that the car title is rendered on the
left side and then the button itself on
the right side. Then this should also be
border of bottom to render the border at
the bottom and border border. This is
the color itself. So as you see this is
this little underline. Um if I go into
light mode I think you will see it a bit
better. Yes, I know you don't see
anything. You want dark mode. But here,
this is this little line. So, I will
switch back into dark mode. And as a
next step, we have to get the cart
content. So, underneath the cart header,
we can get the cart content. This is
imported from the components. And you
know what? Before I even continue, I
want to first of all create a diagram to
showcase the UI itself. So, this is
first of all, our cut. This is this
card. And of course, we also have this
chapters title and then an underline. So
I can just create this underline. Here's
the thing. In this card, we will render
another card. And this card will display
the chapters. So we can say chapter and
this will be one. Then we will create
another underline underneath this. And
in this card we will render all of the
lessons. This means I can get the text
icon and this will be lesson one. And
then I can just copy paste this and this
will be lesson two. This will be lesson
three and then lesson four. And then we
will have another chapter. So I can just
copy all of this again. And then we can
just copy paste it. So down below. And
this will be chapter 2 for example. And
then also again lesson 1 2 3 4. So as
you see we have one big card. And then
in the card itself we will have more you
could say more smaller cards with the
individual chapters and the individual
lessons. And then in the card content I
want to continue by using the sortable
context because as they say the sortable
context provides information via context
that is consumed by the use sortable
hook which is covered in greater detail
in the next section. That's fine. We
will come to that in a second. This
means we can go back and then in the
cart content we want to get the sortable
context imported from DND kit sortable.
Then we want to open this and for the
sortable context we have to provide two
key properties. First of all the
strategy. This means do we want to sort
our items horizontally or vertically? We
want to sort them vertically. This means
we want to use the vertical list sorting
strategy. We can import it. And then we
need to also provide items. So here's
the thing. If we go back to the
documentation, they have here a little
use state example, a little demo
example. We can just copy this use state
example and paste it above the return
statement. I can also import use state
and use state is imported from react. So
these are our items and as you see ID 1,
ID2, ID3 and they are also arranged the
right way. This means we will first of
all display ID 1 then ID2 then ID3. In
the sortable context we have to provide
items. This means if we go back as you
see we can just copy this uh example
with the items property and paste it for
the sortable context. So the sortable
context needs an array of our items
which we now pass. Nevertheless, we
still get one error. What's the problem?
We are missing children. So we will just
continue with the documentation itself.
So it does not expose any call back
props. To know when a sortable this
means or a dragable item is being picked
or moved over another sortable or
droppable item use the call back props
of DND context. This means for example
the DND context provides us with the
onra and property. And this on drag and
property is fire or fires whenever we
drop a sortable into a new or into its
new place when we restructure our whole
items. This means we can copy this
function handle drag and then we can go
back and we want to paste it above the
return statement. So function handle
drag and and then in the D&D context we
can get the property on drag end and
this will be equal to handle drag end.
So this looks good. then we can continue
with the documentation. So in order for
the sortable context component to
function properly, make sure that it's a
descendant of a D&D context provider.
That's fine. We already made sure of
that. Then the next step is to already
use the use sortable hook. So as
outlined above, the use sortable hook
combines both the use dragable and the
use droppable hook to connect elements
as both dragable sources and drop
targets. So this here is a dragable.
This is a droppable. This means we want
to take a dragable and drop it into a
droppable. So the next step is to create
the individual sortable item. This means
we can just copy this function sortable
item. And then we can again go back and
paste it. For example, yeah, let's paste
it above the handle drag and function.
So this is the function sortable item.
We get props. But we yeah, we can leave
them. Why not? We want to then import
use sortable. Use sortable is imported
from D&D kit. And then we want to also
import CSS. So here holds useful CSS
related methods. And we have to also
first of all import the CSS method. This
is imported from DND kit utilities. And
also if this confuses you right now,
don't worry. I will explain everything
in a second. Let's for now just do a bit
of copy pasting. So we want to import
CSS from DND kit utilities. This means I
can just paste it on top and this should
also work. So as you see we don't get
any error anymore right here. And then
we have our diff. We pass a ref style
attributes and listeners. So what do we
do right here? So I will try to explain
this code using plain English because
this here is a bit complicated. So first
of all as you see we get the use
sortable hook and this is the core hook
provided by D&D kit sortable. It
provides us with all of the necessary
logic and properties to make the
component itself sortable so that we can
drag and drop it. As you see, this use
sortable hook is called with a unique ID
for the individual item and it returns
an object with several key properties
that we need to attach to our components
DOM element as you see here. So for
example, we have the set node ref. So
set node ref style attributes listeners
the set node ref this is a function uh
that we pass as a ref to our DOM element
that we want to make sortable and this
allows the indicate internally to access
the underlying DOM node to measure its
pos uh position and size. Then we have
these attributes which we spread. This
is an object and this makes everything
accessible and that's why it's called
attributes. Then we also have these
listeners which we also spread. This
means this is an object and it contains
the event listeners on mouse down on
touch start and other things. So this is
required to detect and initiate the drag
operation and we spread the listeners
onto the element so that everything is
applied and here we also for example get
transform and transform is an object
that represents the element's current
position. So is it position number one,
position number two, number three,
whatever. And then we also have this
transition as you see here. So to
summarize it quickly, this sortable item
which we just created is a component and
it's a wrapper to make its children
dragable. The items, they should be
dragable. And the use sortable hook
provides all of the very very complex
logic for this whole drag and drop
operation. And the component's only job
is to correctly apply the props and the
styles returned by this hook. That's it.
I know it looks confusing. It might
sound confusing, but it's not that
complicated. So, what's the next step?
We implemented this. We can update the
transition and stuff like that. We won't
do that. Not right now. And the next
step is to add sensors. So, sensors are
an abstraction to manage and listen to
different input methods. So, what
exactly are sensors? So if you're not
familiar with the concept, don't worry.
I will explain it. So in DND kit,
sensors are an abstraction used to
detect um different types of input
methods to initiate the drag and drop
operations. And you know what? You can
use multiple sensors. You can use one
sensor which is specifically designed to
handle mouse um events. So when we drag
with our mouse, then there's also for
example the touch sensor which is
specifically used. So as you see um uh
for example keyboard sensor but there's
also a touch sensor which um
specifically handles touch events. So
when you use your finger uh on the phone
and then for example there's also the
keyboard sensors and they allow you to
implement this drag and drop operation
only by using the keyboard. So this
means we want to set up our sensors and
we want to specifically say we want to
specifically define uh what sensors we
want to use. This means we can just copy
this code example constant sensors. We
can go back and paste it just underneath
this uh function handle track end. So
use sensors this is imported from D&D
kit core. Use sensor this is imported
from D&D kit core. Pointer sensor this
is also imported from D&D kit core.
Keyboard sensor this is imported from
D&D kit core. And then sortable keyboard
coordinates this is imported from D&D
kit sortable. So again sensors are there
to literally just track the movement and
we have specific um sensors for specific
use cases. One is there for the mouse,
the other one is there for the keyboard,
the other is there for uh touch uh
sensitive things and stuff like that. So
with that we just track at the end of
the day how the user tries to drag our
item. Then of course we can pass the
sensors to our D&D context. So here we
will get a sensors property and this
will be equal to sensors. to the
constant which we just created. So
what's the next step? Well, the next
step is to right here they say you can
also update for example the distance and
delay and stuff like that. We won't do
that. The default is fine enough. So we
can skip this section. And then the next
step is to add the correct sorting
strategy. So the supported use case um
of the sortable preset include vertical
lists, horizontal lists, grids, and
virtualized lists. Because of the wide
variety of use cases supported, it would
be difficult to write a single strategy
to cover all of these different use
cases. Instead, the sortable preset
exposes a number of different
strategies. And as you see, for our
sortable context, we use the vertical
list sorting strategy. And here they say
this strategy is optimized for vertical
lists and supports virtualized lists.
Since we at the end of the day have a
vertical list. That's also the reason
why we use it. We don't have a
horizontal list. We don't need this swap
swapping strategy. Vertical list sorting
strategy. This is the correct strategy
for us. Then the next step is to add a
collision detection algorithm. As you
already know, we already implemented
one. This is the rect intersection
algorithm. So by default the collision
detection algorithm of D&D context is
rectangle intersection algorithm. While
the rectangle intersection strategy is
well suited for many use cases, it can
be unforgiving since it requires both
the dragable and droable bounding
rectangles to come in direct contact and
intersect. But in this case, this is
fine. And that's also why I use this
rectangle intersection algorithm or in
short wacked intersection. And the next
step is to just connect all of the
pieces. This means we can map over our
items and then just display the
individual sortable item for the
individual item. This means we can go
back into the sortable context inside of
here. We want to map over our items.
This means items do map as a param or
you know what I will just copy paste
this. Why not? So we will copy paste
this and paste it again inside of here.
So items do map as a param we get the id
and then we render the sortable item
component we pass a key since we have to
do that when we use react and also for
the ID we pass the ID because again if
we go to the sortable item function
component if you want to call it like
that it needs the ID the ID is required
and then if you scroll a bit more to the
bottom you will find the section. So I
have scrolled quite a bit through that
but we already implemented the co uh
collision detection algorithm. We
implemented the strategy. We don't need
to implement everything again. We want
to find this or you want to go to this
section. So finally we need to set up
the event handlers on the D&D context
provider in order to update the order of
the items on drag end. This means we
want to use the handle drag end
function. So I will just copy paste it
again. I know we already copied it but
we will again copy it and paste it for
this handle drag and function. So this
is relatively interesting because we
want to update our items. So first of
all we can go back to our state. We have
the getter items. We want to also create
the setter set items and then let's
analyze this handle drag and function.
What does it do? Why do we need it? Good
question. So first of all where do we
call or when do we call the handle drag
and function? Well, if you go back to
the return statement to the D and D
context, the on drag and property is set
equal to the handle drag and function.
So this means it will fire whenever we
are finished with dragging our items. So
when we reorder our structure and we
need this handle drag and function to
update our state because we want to then
rearrange our items. So this event
itself which we get through the params
fires when a user finishes dragging an
item and drops it. The main job is to
update our application state as you see
here because we use the set items setup
the function. So first of all we
destructure active and over from the
event itself. Then we check if the item
was dropped into a new position. This
means if the new dropped uh ID is not
equal to the old ID then this means the
arrangement has changed. If so we then
use the setter to update our state. We
first of all find the old index. So this
means the original index. So if the item
before had an index of one and has been
then dropped or sorted to be rendered a
bit down below. So the new index is
three and the old index is one. This
means it moved two numbers right. So
this means we have the old index the new
index and then using this array move
function we can then return the newly
sorted arrays. So now it will say 1 2 3.
So this array move function is imported
from D&D kit sortable and again this
function takes three events the items
array in general the old index and then
the new index. It will then combine
everything and it will move an array
item to a different position. It then
returns a new array with the item moved
to its new position and it won't break
anything because it will return a new
array. So this is what this function
does and it's very essential to use it.
And you know what? Let's test it out. So
if I go back, we see nothing. What's the
problem? Well, it's quite simple. The
sortable item returns absolutely
nothing. And what we want to render or
we return something the div but for the
div the item itself there's nothing it's
an empty div. This means we want to just
return for example the props do id. This
means if we again go back we now see and
if I also do a hard refresh and go back
to the core structure 1 2 3 and maybe I
can also zoom in a bit. So if I reorder
this from one you see this is um
dragable. I can drag it and I can drop
it into position number two. Uh-huh. our
whole array updated. I can then take the
number three, this item, and drag it and
drop it right here. So, this works
beautifully. Wow. So, we just
implemented a very basic version of drag
and drop. So, we are finished with drag
and drop, which means we can uh head
over to the public facing dashboard,
right? No. I mean, yes, drag and drop
works, but we want to reorder our
chapters and lessons. So before we
create the real UI for that we have to
first of all update our schema because
currently there's no way to create a
chapter and also no way to create
lessons. This means underneath this enum
we can create a new model. This will be
chapter and as you all know uh in a
relational database you have to provide
a primary key in this case this will be
the id which will be of type string at
id at default uyu ID. Then what will a
chapter have? It will have a title. This
will be of type string. It will also
have a position. And this will be of
type int. But now you might ask me, hey
Jan, position, what is that? Why do we
need this position integer? Good
question. So if we go back to the course
structure, how do we order our items? We
use this ID 1 2 3. This is the order.
The problem is this yuyu ID. It won't be
like 1 2 3. No, the UYU ID will be
something like gibberish dash gibberish
dash gibberish. As you see this won't
work. We want numbers 1 2 3. And for
that we will create or we will use this
position. This means for example one
chapter will have the position one then
the next chapter position two the next
chapter position three and so on. So we
have to have a logical order and we will
create that using this position integer.
Then I want to also create created at
and updated at timestamps. So created at
will be of type date time at default
now. And then also we want to create a
updated at time stamp and this will be
of type daytime at updated at. So the
chapter table model is finished. And
then as a next step we can create a
lesson model. So underneath this model
we want to create a new model. This will
be lesson. We can open it again. We want
to create an ID. ID will be of type
string. At id default uyu id. Then what
fields, what columns will our lesson
have? It will first of all have a title.
This will be of type string. It will
also have a description. It will be of
type string. But this description will
be optional. This means if we add this
question mark at the end, we tell our
database that this description is
optional. Then we want to also get a
thumbnail URL. So this will be like the
image. This will be of type string also
optional. And then also a video URL
because at the end of the day we will
then showcase a lesson. lesson will
first of all then have a thumbnail and
then once the user clicks on play we
will display the video itself and and
for that we need the thumbnail and also
the video URL and this will be of type
string and then this will be optional
and also you know what thumbnail URL
video URL do I want to really store URLs
I mean it will be at the end a key right
so maybe this should rather be called
thumbnail key and then also video key
and Then we want to also create the
created add and updated add timestamps.
This means we can just copy them from
the chapter and paste them inside of
here. So our two tables, our two models
are created. They are finished.
Nevertheless, we are missing relations.
So first of all, let's start with the
chapter. What relations will the chapter
have? Well, let's for now forget the
lesson. We have the course and the
course will have a relationship with the
chapter. What relationship will this be?
A onetoone relationship? a one to many
relationship, a many to many
relationship. Well, let's go through the
relationship types. A onetoone
relationship would mean that one chapter
could only have one course or in other
words, one course could only have one
chapter. That's not the case. One course
can have many chapters. This means we
want to create a one to many
relationship. How do you create a one to
many relationship in Prisma? You should
all know it. We want to go into the
course model. We want to go underneath
the user ID and then we can say chapter
this will be lowercased will be equal to
the chapter model and we want to append
an array symbol because we want to
create a one to many relationship. If I
click on command S it will autogenerate
the relationship in theory and yes this
worked nicely. The only problem is it
made these fields these columns these
properties um optional. This means we
can delete these question marks. We
don't need them. So this is our first
relationship. But we also have a
relationship between the chapter and
lesson. What relationship is this? One
to one, one to many or many to many?
Well, it's a one to many relationship
because each lesson has to be related to
one chapter. But every chapter can have
many many lessons. 10 lessons, 20
lessons, I don't care. This means we can
go underneath this course ID and then we
can just say quite simply um lesson
lowerase will or lessons this will be
equal to the lesson model we want to
append array symbols and if I click on
command s then we will autogenerate the
relationship of course again this
shouldn't be optional so we can delete
the question marks uh in the lesson
model so in theory this should be
already it which means we want to sync
our remote database with our local
database schema This means we can open
our terminal, stop the dev server and
then run pnpm dlx prisma db push. I
almost forgot the command. My god. And
yes, your database is now in sync with
your Prisma schema. This means we can
restart our dev server. And this is
finished. So before we continue with our
course structure, I want to first of all
fix one problem which I have with my
edit route because again if we go back,
we have two sections. the basic info
section and the course structure. I want
to first of all again fix one problem
with the basic info structure or page.
So here's the thing. If the user or so
we have a server action as you know this
server action is a public endpoint even
though we make sure that the user is
verified or is authenticated and has an
admin role. I want you first I want to
still protect this server action. This
means I want to implement arcjet again
and thankfully we already did it in the
creation route which means we can also
do a bit of copy pasting. So I want to
again implement the uh the detect bot
rule and also the fixed window rule.
This means we can copy this constant AJ
from the creation route. Go back to the
actions uh file to the act to the server
action for the edit route. Then we can
paste it above. So we want to of course
also import everything. Arcjet is
imported from the lip folder. Detect bot
this is imported also from the lip
folder and fixed window is imported from
the lip folder. So we implemented or we
defined our rules which means we can
also now get the decision. So in the try
statement above the result we can create
a constant decision and this will be
equal to a rate arjet or not arjet but
aj.protect
and then as an argument we want to pass
our request. This means if we go back to
the creation server action, we can just
copy this code. So we can get the
request and this will be equal to this
uh request function. We will paste it
above the decision. We want to import
request from um arcjet / next. And then
we want to create an if statement. As
you know right here, we already created
one. So if the decision is denied and if
the reason is weight limit, then we will
return this error message. And if it's a
different error, then we will return
this error message. This means we can
just copy this and paste it underneath
our decision. So um as you see we get
still one error. What's the problem? We
well we have to pass the request and as
an argument and also we have to pass our
fingerprint. In this case this will be
the user ID. This means fingerprint will
be equal to the user dot user id. This
means we identify the request or yeah we
identify and we track the request using
the user ID. So this optimization is
also finished and we can continue with
our course structure. So first of all I
want to get my data. This means we can
create an interface. This will be called
I app props. And inside of here we want
to get data. What type will data have?
Well if we go back to the page.tsx or if
we go to the edit course form then you
will see that we get our data and we
pass the type admin course singular
type. This means we can just copy this
and paste it inside of here. So admin
course singular type. If you forgot
about this type, don't worry. In our
data access layer where we fetch our
data, we infer the type. So if I find it
quickly, what was it? Get course. Yes,
we infer the type as you see. And we
pass it right here. This means in our
params we can destructure them. And this
will be of type I props. And then where
we the structure, we can get our data.
If we go back to the page.tsx, we get
one error. And that's because we have to
provide the data. So data will be equal
to data. This means if we go back to the
course structure, we can use our data.
So what's the next step? Well, as a next
step, I have to first of all again
update my query because our data
currently only gets uh gets the course
basic info, but we don't get our
chapters and we also don't get our
lessons. This means we can open the
explorer, go back into our data access
layer and go into the admin get course
file. Then inside of here, we want to
update our select statement. Again, I
want to get the chapters and I want to
also get the related lessons. This means
we can go underneath the category. Then
we can get the chapter. We can open it.
We want to select a few properties from
the chapter model. And this will be the
ID. So this will be true. And also the
title, so true. and of course the
position and we can set this to true.
Then we can also get the lessons. This
means underneath the position we will
get lessons. We can open this. We want
to again create a select statement. And
then we want to get an ID. This will be
true. Then of course the title. Then the
description of course also the thumbnail
key. Then we want to also get the
position and where is my position? Why
don't I get it? Did I forget to add it
in my schema? So title, description. Ah,
I forgot the position. My god. So for
the lesson we have to also of course add
a position because we will have to order
our result. This means underneath the v
video key we can get a position and this
will be of type int. Then of course we
want to again sync our database. This
means in the terminal we can run pnpm
dlx prisma db push. This will sync our
database and in theory everything should
be successful in a second. Yes,
everything worked. we can restart our
dev server and then we can continue with
this uh query. So we get our thumbnail
key and then we want to also get the
position and then also the video key and
this should be it I think. So yes, then
we have the if statement return data.
Yeah, this all looks good. We can again
close this and we can continue with the
course structure. So here's the thing.
Currently for my array I pass this
default value. Of course this is not
what we want to pass. We want to pass
our data. This means what we will do is
go above this constant items and we will
create a constant. This will be called
initial items and this will be equal to
data dot chapter dot map since we will
have multiple chapters. Then as a param
we can get this singular chapter the
iterator and then we want to just return
it and open an object inside of here. I
want to restructure my items because
currently the data structure is fine but
it's not that easy to work with it.
That's why I want to restructure
everything. So first of all we will have
an ID. This will be of or this will be
equal to the chapter do ID. Then we will
have the title. This will be equal to
the chapter.title.
Then also the order itself and this will
be the chapter.
Then we will also have an isopen
boolean. So later on we will have like
this collapsible element and for that we
need this state and or this property and
this will be as a default true. This
means as a default the chapter will be
open this collapsible item. We can also
create a comment and say default
chapters to open. Yeah I think this is
fine. Then we can also get our lessons
and we want to again first of all map
over our lessons. This means we can get
the chapter lessons do map as a param.
We can get a singular lesson. We want to
return it. Open an object. And then
inside of here, we will have an ID. This
will be of or equal to the lesson do ID.
Then also the title itself. This will be
equal to the lesson.title.
And then also the order and the order
will be equal to the lesson dotposition.
This should already be it. We get our
lesson uh initial items. But here's the
thing. This could be undefined. What I
mean by that is we could have no
chapters because when we create our
initial course it's empty. This means we
don't have any chapters and we don't
have any lessons. This means if this is
not defined we can create an or symbol.
So or and then this will just be an
empty array. And then instead of passing
these initial values we can just delete
them or this array and we can paste
instead the initial items array which we
just configured or in other words
created. So this is finished. We can
first of all collapse the initial items.
We are finished with the use state. We
will continue with the sortable item in
a second. So with this function, first
of all the sensors. Are they configured
correctly? Pointer sensor, keyboard
sensor. Yes, this looks good. So this is
also finished. So I think we want to
first of all continue with the general
UI. So with this one. So currently we
pass our sortable context and then we
already map over our items. That's not
what I want to do. This means I can
delete this mapping first of all and
inside of here I want to map over my
items. This means we will get our state
here items and I want to map over these
uh items. This means we can get the
items do map as a param. We will get an
item and then we can just return this
inside of here. We want to pass the
sortable item or we want to render the
sortable item. So we can get the
sortable item and then we can open this.
This won't be self-closing. This will
just be a standard component. And here's
the thing. Currently, we get an error
and it says missing key. No problem.
Let's pass a key. And the key will be
equal to our item do ID. So, this error
is gone. But you know what? Before we
continue with the UI, I want to first of
all update the sortable item itself
because currently it's a bit broken. I
want to render a lot of things and it
should look nice. So, this means we can
again go back to the sortable item
function. We can again expand it. And as
you see first of all our props throw an
error. That's because the type is
currently just any. This means what we
will do instead is create a new
interface so that we know what we get
here. This means above our export
function we can create a new interface
and this will be called sortable item
props. We can open it and inside of here
we will first of all get an ID. This
will be of type string. Then we want to
also get children because here's the
thing. You can render the sortable item
as a self-closing self-closing
component. That's what we did a second
ago. But what I want to do is render
children in this sortable item. This
means we will open this and inside of
here render a lot of content. That's why
I need to get children in the params. So
in the interface we will get children
and this will be a standard error
function and it will return react note.
So react note is imported from react
because this is the type for children
and as a param we can also get listeners
and this will be of type dragable
synthetic listeners. What a hard word.
So we can import this from D&D kit core
again dragable synhatic listeners. God
what a word. Then we want to also get
the class name property. This will be
optional and of type string. This means
a user can style the sortable item
dynamically but he does not have to do
it or we don't have to do it as
developers. This will be of type string.
And then also we want to get data. This
will be optional and it will be an
object. And inside of here we will get
two things. First of all a type because
we can either drag a chapter or we can
drag a lesson. And we have to know that.
This means this will be either a chapter
or we can get the vertical line. It will
be a lesson. And here's the thing. If
this currently confuses you, don't
worry. I know right now it's a bit hard
to understand everything, but once we
write a bit more code, it will become
clearer or the picture will become
clearer. And then we want to also get
the chapter ID. This will be optional
and of type string. We can also create a
comment to not get confused. This is
only relevant for lessons. This means
when we drag over a lesson or when we
take a lesson and drag with it, then we
will need the chapter ID because we have
to then know where to place it. If we
only drag a standard chapter, then the
chapter ID is not important. We can
again go back to our sortable item.
Where is it? And then we can delete the
props. Instead, we will structure this.
This will be of type sortable item
props. And then where we the structur we
can get the children we can get the id
of course also the class name and then
also the data as you see we get one
error for our use sortable hook and
that's because the ID uh does not exist
props do ID is not something that we
have so ID will be equal to ID and then
also we can get data and data will be
equal to data then we can continue so
the use sortable hook seems finished
right now the style is also finished and
for the div we pass a ref set note ref.
Yes, that's fine. For the style style,
yes, that's fine. We um spread our
attributes. We spread over our
listeners. This is not quite what I want
to do. Instead, we will delete this
spreading of the listeners. And we will
do it as a child. I will show it to you
in a second. For now, we can first of
all add a class name. Then we can use
the CN helper function imported from the
lip folder. And as a default style, this
will be touch-none.
And then also um we can add a comma. and
then pass our class name so that the
user can then also dynamically style the
sortable item. Here's also the thing in
our use um sortable hook where we
destruct we can also get the is dragging
boolean and this is dragging boolean
will be set to true if we take an item
and just drag with it then this will be
true and I want to use this boolean to
update my class name. So we can add
another comma and then say if is
dragging is true. So we can create a
turnary then we want to say uh Z 10 this
means we want to overlay the item and if
this is not true then this will just be
nothing an empty string. Then for the
value itself instead of rendering props
do ID we want to get our children we
want to invoke our children and pass as
an argument our listeners. This means
this is finished the sortable item. Do
we get any errors here? Um no I don't
think so. This means we can collapse the
sortable item and then we can continue
right here with our general UI. And as
you see the sortable item throws an
error and it says uh we are missing the
following properties from the sortable
item props. And this is the id and then
also children. So the id will be equal
to our item do ID. Then we can also pass
a data prop. And here we have to define
what type this is. So we can add another
object and then we can get the type
itself. So what is this sortable item?
Well, this sortable item will display
the chapter. This means type will be
equal to chapter not lesson. We will
after or we will render the lesson after
we defined this chapter. So this is
finished which means we can open the
sortable item and inside of here we have
to pass children and inside of here I
want to create a standard uh callback
function. This means inside of here we
want to get as a param listeners. So
listen us and then we want to just
return it. Don't open a standard
function or object. Just return this.
And inside of here we can get the cart
component. It's already imported. Then
in the cart we can get the collapsible
component from the components. And what
is this collapsible component? Very good
question. We can head over to shy and UI
and then we can search for collapsible.
As you see this is collapsible and this
state is currently collapsed. And if I
click on this then it will expand as you
see. So this is what we want to do. Um I
can show it to you with a little diagram
again. So this is our card. Uh I can
zoom in a bit here. We will have chapter
one as an example. So this is the title.
Then we will also have a little icon
here. So I will say icon and if the user
clicks on the icon then we will collapse
literally everything inside of here. So
we won't display any lessons. So I can
just create a little line here. But if
the user again clicks on the button then
we will expand everything and then we
will again display lesson one, lesson
two, lesson three blah blah blah. So
this is this collapsible component. It
allows us to collapse and then also
expand content. So this collapsible
component expects two key properties.
First of all the open state and open
will be equal to item is open because
again as a default we set our item. So
if I open it as a default it's open the
chapter but we can also toggle it and
then set it to I guess false. This means
that it will be closed and we want to
also of course get the onopen change
property and this will fire whenever the
user clicks on the button. Here's the
thing. We want to update our state. This
means what we also have to do is create
a new function a new toggle chapter
function. So we can go above the return
above the sensors and then we can create
a function which will be called toggle
chapter and then we can just open this
function as a param we want to get the
chapter ID and this will be of type
string because we want to specifically
know what chapter the user wants to
collapse because we will have multiple
chapters and we don't want to collapse
any uh chapter but a specific one. This
means we can get our set items function
or setter. Then we want to invoke it.
And inside of here we want to say items
do map as a param we will get the
individual chapter. And we want to check
if the chapter iterator is the same as
the chapter ID which we pass. So if the
chapter do ID is equal to the chapter ID
which we pass through the params then we
can use a turnary create an object then
map or spread our chapter properties add
a comma and then set is open to the
opposite value of is open right now. So
this means it will be equal to
exclamation mark chapter is open. As you
see we get also one error and that's
because we are also missing the colon.
And if the chapter ID is not the same as
the chapter ID which we pass then we
will just return the chapter. So what
did we just do right here? I know this
kind of looks a bit confusing. So again
we update our state with the set items
setup inside of here. We map over our
items over our chapters because we have
multiple chapters. We try uh we try to
find the specific chapter ID which
matches the chapter ID which we provide.
If this is true, this means if we find
the correct chapter, then we will first
of all spread all of our old properties
like the title, order, uh ID. We don't
want to update that. We want to only
update is open. And is open will be
equal to the opposite value of is open.
So if this currently is true, then we
will set it to false. If it's currently
set to false, then we will set it to
true. Then we can use this toggle
chapter function. We can scroll to the
top or to the bottom, not to the top.
And inside of here we can create an
inline callback function and this will
be equal to toggle chapter and then as
an argument we want to provide the item
do id. So this is finished and then in
this collapsible component we can render
a div. So for the div we can give it a
class name and this will be flex items
which will be center then justify which
will be between padding three and then
border bottom and also border border. So
what is this div element? Why do we
create one? Well, this will be a wrapper
div and we will use it because on the
left side we will render the title and
then also like this little dragable
button which showcase or which shows
like a little grip button and then on
the right side or not button but icon
and then on the right side we want to
render another button to delete the
chapter. That's why we have this justify
between and the border bottom because we
want to have a nice border. So again if
we look at this diagram which I closed.
So as you see we will have a title then
we have this border then we have this
button on the right side to delete the
chapter and stuff like that. So that's
why we have this div element. Then
inside of here we want to create another
div element and this will house the
button and then also the um content
itself. So the title in this case. This
means we can also give it a class name.
And this will be then flex items which
will be center and also gap too. Inside
of here, we want to get a standard
button. Not a button component, but a
standard button. And then for the
button, I want to render the grip
vertical icon. So the grip vertical icon
is imported from Lucid React. This is
self-closing. And of course, we want to
also style it and give it a class name
which will be size 4. Then for the
button, we can also style it. So the
class, we can give it a class name. This
will be cursor grab. So we will change
this um how how do you call it? The
cursor. Yeah. So instead of having this
cursor will be like this hand which
tries to grab something. Then also we
want to add an opacity which will be 60.
This means 60%. And then on hover we
want to say opacity 100. So the full
opacity. And then we want to also spread
the listeners for the button. This means
we can open an object inside of here and
then spread the listeners. So this in
theory should already display something
which means if we again go back and do a
hard refresh will we see something? I'm
not even sure to be honest with you. And
as you see we don't see anything. What's
the problem? Well the problem is quite
simple. We don't have any chapters. We
don't have any items which means we also
don't display anything. So what we can
do is open again Prisma Studio. I will
um stop my def uh def server and then
inside of here I will run pnpm dx prisma
studio. Then inside of here I want to
create a new chapter. So I can go into
the chapter. I can also collapse this.
Then we want to add a new record. Then
for the title this will be chapter
number one. For the position this will
just be one. Then for the created at
time stamp and updated at time stamp we
don't have to add anything. Then for the
course I want to select my only course.
I have only created one. So I can select
this one. And then for the lessons we
currently don't have any. So we can just
save the change. Then we want to also
create a new lesson. So we can go into
the lesson model and we want to create a
new record. For the title this will be
lesson number one. Then for the
description some gibberish. Then for the
thumbnail uh key and file key I or video
key I will leave it empty. For the
position, this will be one. For the
created ad and updated ad timestamps, we
don't have to add anything. And then for
the chapter, we can relate it to the
chapter which we just created. So I can
select this and then save one change. So
in theory, we should now have one
chapter and one lesson. And this chapter
should also be directly related to this
one course. This means we can restart
our dev server again. And if I again go
back and do a hard refresh in theory, I
should also get something. And yeah, you
see absolutely. Well, what do I mean?
You see something, right? And you know
what? I can even drag this card. Wow,
this is fancy. So, we can continue. We
can again go back and we want to also
display this collapsible trigger. Uh, so
to collapse everything even though
there's nothing to collapse right now.
This means underneath the button but
still in this div we want to get the
collapsible trigger component from the
components we can open it and inside of
here we want to render a button element
we want to also give the collapsible
trigger an as child property and then
for the button you know what um I want
to render an icon but here's the thing
if our collapsible content is open then
the icon should be a chevron down icon
if the item or if this content is not
collapsed Then I want to showcase a
chevron right icon. This means we want
to create a turnary. If item is open is
true, then we can get the question mark
and return the chevron down icon
imported from lucid react. For the class
name, this will be size 4. And if this
is not true, we can get a colon and then
instead return the chevron white icon
imported from lucid react. And for the
class name, this will also be size 4. So
then we can also style the button itself
and for the class name this will be flex
and items center. So if we again go back
we should see something and yes this is
this collapsible button. If I let me
also zoom in a bit and as you see if I
click on this icon it changes to the
chevron down icon and if I again click
on it it changes to the chevron right
icon. This means we can again go back
and as a next step I want to also render
the title. This means underneath the
collapsible trigger we can get a P tag
inside of here. We want to get the item
title. This means the chapter title. And
then we can also add a class name which
will be cursor pointer hover. And this
will be text primary. This means this
orange color. And if we go back you will
see this. So again this is our toggle.
This is our collapsible trigger. And
then this is our text the title of the
chapter. On the right side I want to
then also render a button to delete the
chapter. But for now we will just skip
this. And you know now where I look at
the code would it maybe make sense to
render the button components instead of
the standard button element? I think so.
So we can go back to the collapsible
trigger. Instead of rendering this
button element, we will get the button
component. Then we want to add a size
which will be icon and also a variant
which will just be ghost. We can do the
same thing for this button with the grip
vertical icon. Again, we can get the
button component. And then for the
variant, this will also be ghost. And
for the size, this will be icon. We can
then also delete the class name. We
won't need it anymore. And if I hover
over it, yeah, this looks quite nice.
So, we can leave it as is. And if I zoom
out, yeah, I think this is finished. You
know what? Is the padding the gap too
big?
I don't know. I think this text needs a
bit more margin to the left. This means
we can say padding left of two. Will
this look a bit better? Yeah, I think
this is a bit more proportional as you
see. And you know what? You could also
change the variant. I will check later
on. For now, this is fine enough. Maybe
I will change it later on. I'm not sure.
As mentioned on the right side, I will
also render another button. This means
we can go underneath the P tag,
underneath the div, but we want to stay
in the main div. And we want to again
get the button component. And inside of
here, we can just render a delete X or
is it called X icon? Yeah, I think X
icon or no trash to icon. Yes, this is
imported from Lucid React. For the class
name, this will be size 4. And then for
the button, we can also give it a size
which will be icon. And for the variant,
this will be maybe outline. How does
this look? Yeah, outline for now is fine
enough. I will probably change it later
on. I don't know. Then we want to also
render the collapsible content because
currently there is no content. This
means we can go back. We can go
underneath this div but we want to stay
in the collapsible component itself and
we want to get the collapsible content
component. This is imported from the
components. We can open it and inside of
here we want to render a standard div.
First of all we want to give the div a
class name which will be padding one.
And inside of here we want to again
first of all render a new sortable
context because there are two ways to
sort our items. First of all we can sort
the chapters but we can also sort the
items. That's why we need a second
sortable context. So we can get the
sortable context. This is already
imported and as you all know it needs um
two key properties. First of all the
items and this will be equal to our item
dot lessons do map as a param. We can
get the singular lesson and then we want
to return the lesson do id. So this
already looks way better. And then we
have to also pass the strategy and this
will be our vertical list sorting
strategy because we want to sort our
items vertically. Then in the sortable
context we want to map over our items.
This means we can get our item dot
lessons dot map as a item or as a param
we will get the lesson and then we can
just return it inside of here. We have
to first of all again get the sortable
item component. This isn't self-closing.
This is a standard component and as you
see it complains that's because we have
to pass a key. This is always important
when you map over properties over items.
Then for the key this will be equal to
the lesson do ID because the ID is
unique. Then we can also pass um an ID
and the ID will be equal to lesson do
ID. Then we want to also pass data and
data we want to the structured and pass
the type. The type will be equal to
lesson because this is a lesson. And
also we want to pass the chapter ID
because again the chapter ID is only
needed if we use it um or if we use
lessons when we reorder lessons we need
the chapter ID. This means for the
chapter ID this will be equal to the
item do ID because the item is the
chapter and then the lesson this is the
individual lesson. So in the sortable
item itself we want to render children
and for that we first of all have to get
the lesson listeners. This means this is
again we can um as a param get the
lesson listeners and then we can just
return it. The code itself will be quite
similar to the code above. This means we
want to again render a div element. For
the div we can give it a class name.
This will be flex items center. Then
also justify between to put the children
to the most outer corner. padding to
hover which will be BG accent. This is
like the secondary color and then also
rounded which will be SM. Then inside of
here we want to create another div
element and that's because we want to
again create the same structure. On the
left side we will have this drag button.
Then um an icon or yeah I think an icon
will work quite good and then also the
lesson title and then on the right side
we will again have a delete button. This
means we want to create a new div
element. So div and then inside of here
we can first of all give it a class
name. This will be flex items center and
then gap 2. And for the children we want
to get a button and again we can use the
button component. Why not? And then for
the button we want to give it a variant
which will be ghost. And for the size
this will be icon and inside of here we
want to again get the grip vertical
icon. This is self-closing. We want to
give it a class name and this will be
size four. Our button has to also get
this or these lessons um listeners. This
means we can again spread the lesson
listeners. And now you might ask me, hey
Jan, lesson listeners, what even is
this? I mean we spread it into our
button. But what do we really do? Well,
this lesson listeners is an object. And
when we spread the lesson listeners, we
apply the necessary um how do you call
it? Handlers. This means like the on
pointer down and on key down. So this is
there to then detect and manage the drag
and drop interaction and we applied
specifically to the button because the
button is the how would you call it like
the element which is there to
specifically then drag the items because
we don't want to allow a user to drag an
item if he clicks on the title. No, only
if the user clicks on this specific
button. Then this should be it. Um after
the button we can get a little icon.
This will be the file text icon imported
from Lucid React. And then we can give
it a class name which will be size 4.
How does this already look? Um, we don't
see anything. That's because our items
are collapsed or our content. This means
if we click on this collapsible trigger
button thingy, then our items will be
here again. And as you see, this is the
icon. We can then also continue after
the file text icon. I want to also
render the title. Here's the thing. If
the user clicks on the title, we will
redirect the user to then edit the
specific course structure item if this
makes sense. Uh to edit the specific
lesson. That's what I wanted to say.
This means we can get the link component
from next /link and inside of here we
want to get the lesson.
And then we can give the link and href
and this will be equal to optics because
inside of here we will also pass the
dynamic course ID. This means for the
href um again optics and then we want to
say slashadmin slashcourses
slash the course id this means data do
id then slash the individual item ID so
the category ID in this case so dynamic
value item do ID and then also slash the
lesson ID so this means again a dynamic
value and this will be the lesson id so
the full um href will be slashadmin
slashcourses
slash data ID this is the course ID
slash item ID this is the category ID
slash lesson ID which is the lesson ID
and then we pass the lesson title this
is fine do we need to style it I don't
think so this means if we go back you
will see lesson number one on the right
side we want to again display a button
this means we can go underneath this div
but we want to stay in this big div and
then we want to get a button and for the
button uh again we can give it first of
all a variant. This will be for example
outline. For the size, this will be
icon. And then inside of here, we can
get the delete icon from Lucid React.
And as you see, um, yeah, delete icon
isn't that nice. I think the trash to
icon will work a bit better. And then
for the class name, this will be size 4.
And yeah, this is way better. And then
also underneath this sortable context.
So, or underneath this section. So, if I
get my line, uh, as you see, this is our
sortable context. And the thing is here
I want to render a button which says
create a new lesson or something like
that. This means we can go back. We want
to go underneath the sortable context
but we want to um stay in this div. We
want to create a new div and inside of
here we can use the button component and
then we can just say new lesson or
create new lesson. As you see this
button does not take the whole width and
I don't know it does not look that nice.
This means we can give this div first of
all a class name which will be padding 2
and then for the button we can give it a
variant and the variant will be outline.
I think outline should look quite nice.
This is uh quite uh appealing. The only
problem is it does not take the whole
width. So we can give the button also a
class name which will be width full. And
what do you think? Does it look
beautiful or does it look beautiful? It
looks very beautiful. We can drag and
drop. Yes, it's still buggy. That's
because our on drag end function is
still not implemented and that's why
this is kind of buggy. I mean the
chapter is not buggy but the lesson drag
and drop is quite um buggy. Don't worry
we will fix it. Nevertheless, I have one
problem currently. If I copy this URL
and open it in a new incognito tab, I
get redirected. That's very cool. But if
I go into the dashboard, copy the URL
and again paste it into my incognito
tab. I see this. This shouldn't happen.
only authenticated users and only admins
should be able to see this route. Even
though I don't fetch any data and even
though this is dummy data, I still don't
want to give the a fake user at the end
of the day the ability to view this data
and I don't mean a fake user but a
nonauthenticated user. So here's the
thing. How can we make sure that only
authenticated users and also admins see
this page? We could for example open the
page.tsx. This is one idea. So, right
here, page.tsx. My god, where is it? Um,
I can open it in a core structure. Why
not? So, app folder admin page.tsx. And
we could just go inside of here and say
constant data or constant session equals
to array require admin. Then we could
get the user session and check if the
user is an admin. Yes, this works. And
also, this is a server component. So,
this is all fine. We can do that. But
what's the problem? Well, currently this
is all fake data. What I mean by that is
we don't fetch any data for the section
cards for the chart area interactive and
also for this data table. We don't fetch
any data. So this means when we will
later on deploy our application this
data or this page for now later on we
will fetch data but right now it would
be a static route because again no data
is fetched. NextJS will see that next.js
is smart and it will opt this route into
static rendering. This means it will be
pre-generated at buildtime or
pre-rendered at build time. If we get
our user session inside of here, it will
go through the session or through the
server. This means this page will be
opted into dynamic rendering. We don't
want that. So, we need some sort of
other solution and thankfully there is a
great solution and the solution is
called middleware. What is middleware?
Middleware allows you to run code before
a request is completed. Then based on
the incoming request you can modify the
response by rewriting, redirecting,
modifying the request or response
headers or responding directly. So how
will everything work? Well, we will have
a request. So you as a client make a
request to our website in this case kind
of to our server, right? So you make a
request and before the middleware uh
before the request hits the server,
middleware will intercept the request.
It's like a layer in front of our
server. It will intercept the request
and it will check hm does the user have
a valid session. Is the user an admin?
If not then middleware will respond and
will say hey I will redirect you to /lo
or/notadmin whatever middleware will
just respond in some sort of way. If the
request is fine, this means or in other
words, if the user session is fine and
stuff like that, then the request will
just be forwarded to the server and then
the server will forward the request to
the database. We will get all of the our
data and then return the response. This
is great. But you know what? Sorry for
that. The problem with middleware is you
can create a matcher and then in the
matcher you specifically define in which
routes middleware should not run. So for
example, our index page. So I can go to
localhost 3000. This is a public route.
This means even if a user is not
authenticated, the user should still be
able to view this data or this page. The
same thing is also true for courses and
then the individual page for the
courses. These are public routes. And
this means in our matcher we will say
hey this route is a public route. This
route is a public route. But what if we
accidentally also add our admin index
page? Then this layer of defense will
pretty much not work and our fake user
in this case will or not fake user but
our malicious user will still be able to
view our page. Now we can't really stop
this. This is as it is. You shouldn't
forget it but it can happen. That's why
we also use the data access layer
because our middleware is like the first
line of defense. In case a user forgets
to add a specific path to middleware,
then we will still have our data access
layer. Because here's the thing, we
still have our client. A client or our
client makes a request to our server.
Middleware will still intercept our
request. But in this case, let's say
middleware won't work because we forgot
to add the specific path or middleware
for example recently had a
vulnerability. Um I can also open the
page. Why not? So nextjs middleware
vulnerability. We can just open it. Uh
what do we want to open? Which link? I
think this one. So security alert. How
attackers can bypass NexJS middleware
with a single HTTP header. So um
middleware next.js allows you to run
code before a request is completed. Yes,
we know that already. The attack
exploits the X middleware sub request
header an internal implementation detail
that was never meant to be exposed to
user uh to users. By supplying a
specific value to this header easily
inferred from the target application
structure, attackers can completely
bypass Nex.js's middleware execution.
Now this bug has been fixed. Middleware
is again safe. But let's just imagine
that your application would have been
created 3 months ago and the attacker
could just bypass your middleware. This
is the reason why we also created this
data access layer because in case our
middleware gets um yeah in case our
middleware just does not work because
some sort of user passes this X or
pasted this X request header then our
data access layer would still function
because the request will first of all
hit the server that's fine but before we
retrieve our data our data access layer
will again check if the user has the
correct authorization status. So if the
user is a real user and has or is an
admin and stuff like that that's why in
this application we will implement
middleware and the data access layer. We
already implemented the data access
layer but now we want to also implement
middleware. At the end of the day this
will be multi-layered security because
you don't want to have one line of
defense. No, the more lines of defense
you have the better. In case this one
breaks we still have the data access
layer. In case the data access layer
breaks, we still have middleware. And
the nice thing with middleware is that
it also preserves static rendering. Um
because again our index page, so the
admin index page currently does not
render or does not fetch any data. This
means our data access layer won't even
be in effect because we won't fetch any
data which means it won't really exist.
We won't have this line of defense. And
again we could of course fetch the user
session in the page but then we would
opt the route into dynamic rendering and
with middleware we will preserve static
rendering. And yeah that's what I wanted
to explain to you guys. That's the
reason why we implemented the data
access layer and why we will now also
implement middleware. So what we can do
is go back to better off. Then we can
head over to the documentation. We want
to scroll to the bottom. Then we want to
go to what was it? Integrations or
guides. Um sometimes this documentation
is a bit confusing. So it's integrations
and then we want to go to nextjs.
So here they again talk about the
integration, how to create an API route
and stuff like that. We already did all
of this annoying stuff and we want to
scroll a bit further. So on the right
side we want to go to middleware and
here they say in nextJS middleware it's
recommended to only check for the
existence of a session cookie to handle
redirection to avoid blocking requests
by making API or datab uh database
calls. You can use the get session uh
cookie helper from better off for this
purpose. So here's the thing for now we
will only check if the user has a valid
session. We will later on also check if
the user is an admin and stuff like
that. But this will take a bit of time
because there's a lot of things that I
have to explain for that. So for now we
will just check if the user has a valid
session. So we can just copy this code
example which they provide here. So the
get session cookie function does not
automatically reference the off config
specified in off.ts. Therefore if you
customize the cookie name or prefix, you
have to do a lot of other things. But we
don't uh we did not customize anything.
Everything is set as the default which
means we can just copy this code
example. We can then go back open the
explorer and we want to create a new
middleware file. This means
middleware.ts
and then we can paste uh this code
example. So here's the thing this uh
here we define the middleware itself.
Then we use this get session cookie
helper function provided by better off
to check if the user has a valid
session. If not, if there's no session
cookie, then we just redirect the user
back to the index page. We can also
redirect the user to the login route,
for example. It does not really matter.
Let's just redirect the user to the
login route. Why not? And then we also
have this matcher. So, export constant
config matcher. And here you specify the
routes the middleware applies to. So, we
want to um apply the middleware to our
admin route. This means instead of
saying / dashboard, we want to say
/admin. But this brings one huge problem
because this will only run on this admin
index page. So we can save this right
now. We can go back and we can just copy
this index page. Let's do a hard
refresh. Then we can copy this URL, open
it in a new incognito tab. And in
theory, everything should be protected.
Yes, this works nicely. But if I go for
example to the creation route. So in the
creation route we don't fetch any data.
So again inside of here our data access
layer does not check anything which
means this is currently unprotected. But
in theory we have middleware right? Yeah
kind of. I mean if I copy this URL and
again open it in a new incognito tab I
will see the data. But wait we just uh
defined middleware right? Yes. But this
again only applies to the index page.
This means what what you want to do is
say /admin then slash colon path star.
This will then apply to all admin
routes. This means if I save this again
and do a hard refresh in this incognito
tab I will get redirected. This means
our whole admin page our whole admin
dashboard is completely protected with
middleware. And again middleware is now
applied on the page level itself. It
protects the pages individually and the
data access layer protects our data
double layered security. Very cool. So
before we continue with our drag and
drop thingy for our course structure. So
this here I want to first of all push
the code into a GitHub repo. So we want
to store the code in GitHub which means
we can go to github.com/new
and we want to create a new GitHub
repository. For the name this will be
marshall-l
at least in my case. Then for the um how
would you call it visibility this will
be a private repo and I don't want to do
anything else and then I can create the
repository. The next step is to connect
our codebase or in other words to push
our code into this remote GitHub repo.
This means we can go back. We want to
open the terminal. We want to stop our
dev server and then run get innit. This
will reinitialize the existing git
repository. And then the next step is to
say get add everything with a dot. This
will then just add all of our files. And
then we want to also create a commit
message. So get commit-m
and for the message this will be I will
call it version one. And then I can
click on enter. As you see all of these
files have been committed. And then the
next step is to also add our remote
origin or to we want to first of all add
a new branch. So we can go back to this
quick start guide and then we want to
copy get branch- m main. So this will
create a new branch and the name will be
main. Then we want to also add a remote
origin. So we can copy this, paste it
inside of here. This will add the remote
origin and then we want to push our code
into the main branch. This means we can
copy this and paste it inside of here.
This will take all of our committed
files and push it into the remote um URL
or it will push it into the remote repo.
So if I do again a hard refresh, I
should get all of my files. And yes,
this looks absolutely beautiful. So
version one, version one, and then
initial commit from create next app. So
this worked exactly as expected. So here
are a few things I want to mention.
First of all, if you bought access to
this GitHub repository, then thank you.
I appreciate it. Thank you for
supporting this channel and thank you
for supporting me, Jan Marshall. I
appreciate it very very much. If you are
a customer, if you bought access to this
GitHub repository and if you have
questions or problems, then email me. I
read emails from customers and I also
respond instantly. If you are a customer
again then secondly this video will now
finish. Stop. Why is that? Here's the
thing. NextJS has a or not next.js, my
god, YouTube has a time limit 12 hours.
I know YouTube or some people upload
videos which are 20 hours long, 30 hours
long. I tried it, it never worked. I
contacted support. They said, "Hey, Jan,
officially we only allow 12 hours.
That's it. Not anymore." So, I'm not
sure how these people upload such long
videos. I would love to do the same
thing, but it does not work. I tried it
once, it never worked. So, that's why I
will have to create a second part. But
don't worry, this second part will also
be free. It will also be uploaded to the
main YouTube channel, Jan Marshall. You
don't have to sign up for it. You don't
have to pay for the video. No, it will
be a normal free video. The GitHub repo
access is paid. Yes, but the video
itself is completely free and it will
come out in about 3 to 4 days again on
this channel. Jan Marshall also for
everybody who bought GitHub or who
bought access to this GitHub repository.
Here on the right side you see the
commits currently there are two commits.
Later on I will create another commit
version two once version two or once the
second part comes out the YouTube video.
For now, this will only be version one,
but once the second YouTube video comes
out, you will also see version two here.
That's because we will rewrite a lot of
things in version two. And if you want
to reference all of the code from this
part one, then you can just go here,
click on version one, and then you can
access the whole code. So you can say
somewhere, where was it? Browse files.
So then you will see all of the code
exactly when we push the code into this
repo. And also before I let you go off,
I want to say thank you everybody for
supporting this channel. It's actually
the 2-year anniversary of this YouTube
channel. Yes, two years. Quite some
time. And yeah, enjoy your day and I
hope I see you in part two. So, bye-bye.